<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>product on hack(pravj)</title>
    <link>https://hackpravj.com/tags/product/</link>
    <description>Recent content in product on hack(pravj)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 10 Oct 2021 11:30:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hackpravj.com/tags/product/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>How will a drone deliver your food?</title>
      <link>https://hackpravj.com/blog/how-will-drone-deliver-food-order/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Oct 2021 11:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hackpravj.com/blog/how-will-drone-deliver-food-order/</guid>
      <description>The title looks like a good interview question. So here is the right follow-up question, Why?
Let’s list down the contributing factors and follow up from there.
Have you ever been in a situation when you’re (hungry) about to place a food order and the application is showing you 40+ minutes to deliver? It’s a complete turn-off.
 You start to think of some other food item that will be delivered early.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Anatomy of a Finshots story: Art of Effective Storytelling</title>
      <link>https://hackpravj.com/blog/finshots-storytelling-product-teardown/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Mar 2021 04:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hackpravj.com/blog/finshots-storytelling-product-teardown/</guid>
      <description>Finshots is an India-focused daily newsletter explaining the important financial news in a simplified language.
The application has nailed the financial-education category and was a winner of Google Play’s Best of 2020 award. 🏆
It has a 4.9/5 rating on the Play Store and has 100K+ downloads. On top of everything else, it has true fans loving the product and spreading the word around.
This article is a product-teardown with an objective to understand what sets the application apart from existing players.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A framework for using automation in product design</title>
      <link>https://hackpravj.com/blog/automation-product-design-framework/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jan 2021 15:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hackpravj.com/blog/automation-product-design-framework/</guid>
      <description>This article is an attempt to dissect and explain automation, and to provide a framework on how to use automation during product design.
It&amp;rsquo;s based on the paper titled, &amp;ldquo;A Model for Types and Levels of Human Interaction with Automation,&amp;rdquo; by R Parasuraman et al.
Disagreement with the definition There are many opinions on automation without understanding it fully.
Even the dictionary gets it wrong perceiving it as a binary mode of operation (either 0 or full human replacement).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Opportunities in Indian railway commute: Next Billion Users perspective</title>
      <link>https://hackpravj.com/blog/indian-railways-next-billion-users/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2019 18:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hackpravj.com/blog/indian-railways-next-billion-users/</guid>
      <description> This article is being updated. Thank you for your patience.
 </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using GitHub to build a missing GitHub feature</title>
      <link>https://hackpravj.com/blog/building-missing-github-feature/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2019 18:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hackpravj.com/blog/building-missing-github-feature/</guid>
      <description> This article is being updated. Thank you for your patience.
 </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
