<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Rant on hack(pravj)</title>
    <link>https://pravj.github.io/tags/rant/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Rant on hack(pravj)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 12:15:24 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://pravj.github.io/tags/rant/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>2015 - A year in review</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/2015-year-in-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 12:15:24 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/2015-year-in-review/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s that time of year when people are writing about what they accomplished in the year, sites are publishing countless the-best-of lists and the only thing I&amp;rsquo;m left wondering seeing YouTube Rewind is - &amp;ldquo;How come I&amp;rsquo;ve never heard any of this?&amp;rdquo;
Since last year, I too have started this ritual of writing down key highlights of my year so that I can look back a few years from now and have a chuckle at my naiveté.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Month of March</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/the-month-of-march/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Mar 2015 06:58:24 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/the-month-of-march/</guid>
      <description>Being busy with a couple of important things, both personally and professionally, this blog did not see any new post published this month. So before this month ends, I decided to quickly summarize the major things that happened in March.
EasyCredit For the past 6 months, I&amp;rsquo;d been working intermittently on a pretty cool application at my workplace, finally shipped in the first week of March. The app, built on Flask and Backbone, allows users to pay for their installments via an easy and intuitive user interface.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>One Thing Today</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/one-thing-today/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2015 19:06:12 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/one-thing-today/</guid>
      <description>Every morning in basic SEAL training, my instructors, who at the time were all Vietnam veterans, would show up in my barracks room and the first thing they would inspect was your bed.
If you did it right, the corners would be square, the covers pulled tight, the pillow centered just under the headboard and the extra blanket folded neatly at the foot of the rack—rack—that’s Navy talk for bed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2014 - A year in review</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/2014-year-in-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 23:15:24 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/2014-year-in-review/</guid>
      <description>With 2014 over, I think it&amp;rsquo;s a good time to get introspective and spend time thinking about key developments that happened throughout the year. My main motivation for this post is to be able to look back a couple of years from now and remember how 2014 was for me.
Writing 2014 was finally a year where I&amp;rsquo;d like to think that I succeeded in blogging. Although I did fall short of my initial goal of one post per week I averaged around 3 posts a month which, for someone who&amp;rsquo;s failed regularly at blogging, is a great success.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>University Courses</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/university-courses/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2014 20:33:29 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/university-courses/</guid>
      <description>It would be an understatement to say that one of my favorite pastime is hoarding (no not the kind where I can hoard physical goods to drive up prices). I hoard blog posts, videos, E-books, Dribbble screenshots and almost anything I can lay my hands on in the hope that one day I&amp;rsquo;ll have to time to actually go through it.
While working through recent MOOCs and frequently stumbling on academic papers, I felt that there&amp;rsquo;s a whole load of treasure hidden deep within university pages.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Happy Accident</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/a-happy-accident/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Sep 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/a-happy-accident/</guid>
      <description>Last week, I was pleasantly surprised to find an email by a correspondent of Economic Times (a leading newspaper in India) asking for permission to quote a comment I made on Hacker News in the newspaper&amp;rsquo;s front page!
 I hope they have India on their radar! It would be awesome for the Indian Startup scene to hear all those great speakers live!
   Who knew that a comment on HN would end up on the front-page of a newspaper!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Maciej on Matasano</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/maciej-on-matasano/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/maciej-on-matasano/</guid>
      <description>Just when you promise yourself that you are going to work on systems for a couple of weeks and not get diverted, you get to hear about new ways to kill time learning crypto
 As a programmer, my core strengths have always been knowing how to apologize to users, and composing funny tweets. While I can hook up a web template to a database and make the squigglies come out right, I cannot efficiently sort something for you on a whiteboard, or tell you where to get a monad.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>It Ends</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/it-ends/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/it-ends/</guid>
      <description>Github Streak.  And so it ends! For the past 64 days, I&amp;rsquo;ve been working hard to keep contributing to open source, to keep committing meaningful commits each day. Yesterday, I decided to end it. Nearing the end, it started getting a bit tiring. I was spending my time in office thinking what will I work on today. In the start it was good, I had a couple of good postman projects to take care of.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evan Priestly on PHP</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/evan-priestly-on-php/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 May 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/evan-priestly-on-php/</guid>
      <description>At Facebook, I described myself as &amp;ldquo;the engineer who hates PHP the least&amp;rdquo; and have also been called a &amp;ldquo;PHP idiot savant&amp;rdquo;. While I&amp;rsquo;m not really a fan of PHP, my understanding of it is extremely deep so there&amp;rsquo;s a huge activation energy for me to learn something else. I also think language choice is far less important than most people make it out to be; in my experience, the people who I have encountered who scoff the hardest at PHP and cry the most loudly about the importance of languages tend to also be really bad at doing any useful work in the languages they advocate.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Write Code Everyday</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/write-code-everyday/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Apr 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/write-code-everyday/</guid>
      <description>It’s important to note that that I don’t particularly care about the outward perception of the above Github chart. I think that’s the most important take away from this experiment: this is about a change that you’re making in your life for yourself not a change that you’re making to satisfy someone else’s perception of your work. The same goes for any form of dieting or exercise: if you don’t care about improving yourself then you’ll never actually succeed.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>