<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>hack(pravj)</title>
    <link>http://pravj.github.io/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on hack(pravj)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://pravj.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Information Dynamics on the GitHub Network</title>
      <link>http://pravj.github.io/blog/information-dynamics-on-github/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pravj.github.io/blog/information-dynamics-on-github/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Exploring the &amp;ldquo;social coding&amp;rdquo; behavior.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social groups have a system of behaviours occuring within the group or between groups, called &amp;ldquo;Group dynamics&amp;rdquo;. GitHub, being a social coding network, is the host to millions of developers and software projects. This report will use openly available data to unveil such behaviors in an intellectual-focused social network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;social-coding&#34;&gt;Social Coding&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The growth of GitHub has been significantly different from other OSS communities such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://alioth.debian.org&#34;&gt;Alioth&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://freecode.com&#34;&gt;Freecode&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://savannah.gnu.org/&#34;&gt;Savannah&lt;/a&gt;. It has experienced an &amp;ldquo;explosive growth&amp;rdquo;, defined as the &amp;ldquo;outburst-type&amp;rdquo;. &lt;a href=&#34;http://yuyue.github.io/res/paper/crowdsoft2014.pdf&#34;&gt;(Yu et al. 2014)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following chart demonstrates the growth of GitHub, Alioth, Freenode, and Savannah. It&amp;rsquo;s made by approximating the data points in the pictures (using &lt;a href=&#34;http://arohatgi.info/WebPlotDigitizer&#34;&gt;WebplotDigitizer&lt;/a&gt;) embeded in the above-mentioned paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://plot.ly/~octogrid/143/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; title=&#34;oss-growth&#34; style=&#34;display: block; text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://plot.ly/~octogrid/143.png&#34; alt=&#34;oss-growth&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;width: 640px;&#34;  width=&#34;640&#34; onerror=&#34;this.onerror=null;this.src=&#39;https://plot.ly/404.png&#39;;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;script data-plotly=&#34;octogrid:143&#34;  src=&#34;https://plot.ly/embed.js&#34; async&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can notice that the GitHub has experienced a big leap in a short time. On the other hand, the growth of other communities gradually slows down after a period of rising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GitHub keep promoting the &amp;ldquo;social coding&amp;rdquo; ideology, &lt;a href=&#34;https://help.github.com/articles/be-social/&#34;&gt;Be Social&lt;/a&gt;. They have multiple social features such as &lt;em&gt;networking based on following developers&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;sharing based on repository forking&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;watching a project&amp;rsquo;s development&lt;/em&gt; etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The social features are the core factors behind this explosive growth of GitHub, setting it apart from other open source software communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;distribution-channels&#34;&gt;Distribution Channels&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;custom-quote&#34;&gt;
  &lt;h1 class=&#34;icon-quote-left&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    The worst thing to happen with your repository is, &lt;i&gt;nobody will see it&lt;/i&gt;.
    &lt;span class=&#34;author&#34;&gt;
        - &lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;https://twitter.com/captn3m0&#34;&gt;Nemo&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, even worse is that the &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=10101469&#34;&gt;government will see it&lt;/a&gt; and ask you to stop working on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever &lt;em&gt;a new repository is created&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;an issue is filed&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;a pull-request is submitted&lt;/em&gt;; there exist several mediums to notify interested users about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;internal-distribution-channels&#34;&gt;Internal distribution channels&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Watch&lt;/em&gt; a repository to get notified about the development and discussion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Discover interesting projects in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/explore&#34;&gt;Explore GitHub&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/trending&#34;&gt;Trending&lt;/a&gt; sections.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find a repository in your public activity timeline if anyone from your network has &lt;em&gt;created&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;starred&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;forked&lt;/em&gt; it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;external-distribution-channels&#34;&gt;External distribution channels&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find a repository in the manually or algorithmically crafted digest emails.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Locate a repository outside of the GitHub; on Hacker News, Reddit, Twitter, or blogs etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A user &lt;em&gt;starring&lt;/em&gt; a repository can propogate it to his/her direct (first-degree) followers. If anyone from those connections &lt;em&gt;star&lt;/em&gt; the repository, it has the chance to appear in the activity feed of their followers and so on&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a repository is being starred by someone disconnected (without any connection to the creator), we can say that it has traversed far away in the network or &lt;em&gt;gone viral&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;contribution-of-external-channels&#34;&gt;Contribution of external channels&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;External distribution channels have a significant impact on the popularity of a repository. They allow a repository to be viewed by &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; people compared to all the users it could have reached by the internal distribution channels of GitHub. (a paper on virality)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;hacker-news&#34;&gt;Hacker News&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;YCombinator&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://news.ycombinator.com&#34;&gt;Hacker News&lt;/a&gt; is a news aggregator website focusing on &lt;em&gt;computer science&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;technology&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;entrepreneurship&lt;/em&gt;; known for its frontpage blessings. It has a dedicated section called &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/showhn.html&#34;&gt;Show HN&lt;/a&gt; to share something that you&amp;rsquo;ve made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@iamclovin/hacker-news-vs-product-hunt-a-launch-story-db18a23bc56a&#34;&gt;multiple&lt;/a&gt; startups &lt;a href=&#34;http://pitchpigeon.com/blog/10-lessons-learned-from-a-successful-hacker-news-launch.html&#34;&gt;successfully&lt;/a&gt; launching their products on Hacker News.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Paul Graham, the frontpage works in a self-protecting way, advertising what type of submissions are expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, &lt;em&gt;everyone want to see their submission on the frontpage&lt;/em&gt;. So in GitHub&amp;rsquo;s context, they post about their repository on HN &lt;strong&gt;as soon as&lt;/strong&gt; they open-source it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the following chart showing the &lt;em&gt;submission delay&lt;/em&gt; (difference between the time of a Hacker News submission and repository creation), I have collected submissions (linking to a GitHub repository) from the past 100 days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://plot.ly/~octogrid/145?show_link=False&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; title=&#34;hn-delay&#34; style=&#34;display: block; text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://plot.ly/~octogrid/145.png&#34; alt=&#34;hn-delay&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;width: 640px;&#34;  width=&#34;640&#34; onerror=&#34;this.onerror=null;this.src=&#39;https://plot.ly/404.png&#39;;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;script data-plotly=&#34;octogrid:145&#34;  src=&#34;https://plot.ly/embed.js&#34; async&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!--hover trace-name--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can observe a &lt;em&gt;long tail&lt;/em&gt; in the submission delay distribution. There are &lt;strong&gt;3261&lt;/strong&gt; HN stories linking to a GitHub repository in these 100 days, with more than &lt;strong&gt;33%&lt;/strong&gt; of them (&lt;strong&gt;1078&lt;/strong&gt;) being posted in the &lt;strong&gt;first week&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;15%&lt;/strong&gt; in just &lt;strong&gt;24 hours&lt;/strong&gt; of repository creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It implies that people tend to use these external channels more often, to get visitors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;effect-of-internal-and-external-distribution-channels&#34;&gt;Effect of internal and external distribution channels&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s consider a recent trending repository, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/minimaxir/big-list-of-naughty-strings&#34;&gt;minimaxir/big-list-of-naughty-strings&lt;/a&gt; to compare the effect of &lt;em&gt;external&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;internal&lt;/em&gt; distribution channels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the following chart you can see the &lt;em&gt;stars&lt;/em&gt; it has received every day since its creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://plot.ly/~octogrid/147/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; title=&#34;minimaxir-repo-stars&#34; style=&#34;display: block; text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://plot.ly/~octogrid/147.png&#34; alt=&#34;minimaxir-repo-stars&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;width: 640px;&#34;  width=&#34;640&#34; onerror=&#34;this.onerror=null;this.src=&#39;https://plot.ly/404.png&#39;;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;script data-plotly=&#34;octogrid:147&#34;  src=&#34;https://plot.ly/embed.js&#34; async&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can easily notice &lt;strong&gt;4 local maximas&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/minimaxir/big-list-of-naughty-strings#social-media-discussions&#34;&gt;corresponding to a Hacker News or Reddit submission featuring this repository&lt;/a&gt;. It has scored relatively less &lt;em&gt;stars&lt;/em&gt; on other days, except the day it was created.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re wondering why does it has almost 1000 stars on the day 1 before the first HN submission, &lt;em&gt;keep reading.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mention the recursive mentions of issue&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, external channels have more impact than internal distribution channels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;how-does-it-reach-so-far&#34;&gt;How does it reach so far?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, let&amp;rsquo;s consider another repository titled &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/Doga&#34;&gt;pravj/Doga&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m fortunate enough to have written it. You &lt;em&gt;can explore&lt;/em&gt; how Hacker News had contributed to its &lt;em&gt;small success&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m choosing this repository because it has relatively less number of stargazers, 229 precisely at the time of data collection. So it&amp;rsquo;s easy to visualize them, still a little hard to make a responsive visualization given that it&amp;rsquo;s my first &lt;em&gt;production level&lt;/em&gt; encounter with D3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following interactive visualization demonstrates the &amp;ldquo;stargazers network&amp;rdquo; that contains the stargazers of this repository. You can &lt;em&gt;hover on a node&lt;/em&gt; (user) to see its connected stargazers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &amp;lsquo;stargazer network&amp;rsquo; is a &lt;strong&gt;directed graph&lt;/strong&gt; of all stargazers of the repository.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There exist an edge (U&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; → U&lt;sub&gt;j&lt;/sub&gt;) in the network &lt;strong&gt;if&lt;/strong&gt; U&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; is following U&lt;sub&gt;j&lt;/sub&gt; &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt; has starred the repository &lt;strong&gt;after&lt;/strong&gt; U&lt;sub&gt;j&lt;/sub&gt; has starred (or created) it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The size of a node in a row is proportional to its &lt;strong&gt;in-degree&lt;/strong&gt;, the number of users it &lt;em&gt;might have told&lt;/em&gt; about the repository by starring it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Users having a high in-degree (more number of GitHub followers) have relatively high probability of spreading the news about the repository &lt;strong&gt;inside the GitHub network&lt;/strong&gt;. Just like the repository creator did on his own, spreading it to a few users before the HN submission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to WSJ Graphics&amp;rsquo; &lt;a href=&#34;http://graphics.wsj.com/anatomy-of-a-hit/&#34;&gt;Anatomy of a hit&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Audience size&lt;/strong&gt; is a role playing factor in the success of open source software. That&amp;rsquo;s why &lt;em&gt;minimaxir&lt;/em&gt; was able to spread his repository &lt;em&gt;big-list-of-naughty-strings&lt;/em&gt; to more people before the first HN submission, because he has more followers than me (@pravj).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#39;chart&#39;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can label the stargazers at network distance &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; as &lt;em&gt;disconnected stargazers&lt;/em&gt;, because they have no &lt;em&gt;following&lt;/em&gt; relation to other users, &lt;strong&gt;out-degree being 0&lt;/strong&gt; for them. There are a total of 139 such stargazers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disconnected stargazers at network distance &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; don&amp;rsquo;t have any successors, that means they have discovered the repository somewhere &lt;strong&gt;out of the GitHub network&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;!--
rawgit production level

Google analytics

Hacker News story submission

Stars of minimaxir repository

How far does it go? (Doga)
--&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-do-you-get-more-visitors-to-your-repository&#34;&gt;How do you get more visitors to your repository?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GitHub models user-actions on the platform as &lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.github.com/v3/activity/events/types/&#34;&gt;various events&lt;/a&gt;, they &lt;em&gt;may&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;may not&lt;/em&gt; appear in the public activity timeline based on the event types.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.github.com/v3/activity/events/types/#memberevent&#34;&gt;MemberEvent&lt;/a&gt; is one such event, triggered when a user is added or removed as a collaborator to a repository, or has their permissions changed. (GitHub API v3)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever a user U&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; adds another user U&lt;sub&gt;j&lt;/sub&gt; as a collaborator to the repository R, all the followers of U&lt;sub&gt;j&lt;/sub&gt; will receive it in their activity feed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s relate it with &amp;ldquo;Influence Maximization&amp;rdquo; (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cornell.edu/home/kleinber/kdd03-inf.pdf&#34;&gt;Kempe et al. 2003&lt;/a&gt;). It&amp;rsquo;s a widely studied problem in social networks, trying to find a subset of users (seed users) to adopt a new idea or product to trigger a cascade of further adoptions via &lt;em&gt;social influence&lt;/em&gt;. The problem is to &lt;em&gt;locate those seed users so that the total number of adoptions can be maximized&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a solution to the problem, some GitHub users used to add most-followed users as collaborators. Because it would broadcast about the repository to all their followers, eventually getting more viewers to the repository.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/torvalds-broadcast.png&#34;&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A repository being broadcasted to users in feed&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A user U&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; adding another user U&lt;sub&gt;j&lt;/sub&gt; to the repository R as a collaborator is a &amp;ldquo;collaboration spam&amp;rdquo;, if U&lt;sub&gt;j&lt;/sub&gt; has zero commits in the repository &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt; U&lt;sub&gt;j&lt;/sub&gt; does not follow U&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;it-might-give-false-positive-results-also-but-overall-it-s-a-good-method-for-the-classification&#34;&gt;It might give false positive results also, but overall it&amp;rsquo;s a good method for the classification.&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;for-example-if-the-repository-has-been-deleted-it-ll-count-that-as-a-spam&#34;&gt;For example, if the repository has been deleted, it&amp;rsquo;ll count that as a &amp;lsquo;spam&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following chart shows how many times some popular users were the target in a &lt;strong&gt;collaboration spam&lt;/strong&gt; (in a year).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://plot.ly/~octogrid/153/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; title=&#34;collaboration-spam-vertical&#34; style=&#34;display: block; text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://plot.ly/~octogrid/153.png&#34; alt=&#34;collaboration-spam-vertical&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;width: 100%;&#34;  width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;600px&#34; onerror=&#34;this.onerror=null;this.src=&#39;https://plot.ly/404.png&#39;;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;script data-plotly=&#34;octogrid:153&#34;  src=&#34;https://plot.ly/embed.js&#34; async&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can feel how annoying it would have been for the popular users, specially for the most-followed &lt;strong&gt;Linus Torvalds&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;to-prepare-this-chart-a-total-of-3m-memberevents-were-collected-from-the-bigquery-dataset-then-all-the-events-adding-top-100-most-followed-users-as-a-collaborator-were-filtered-out-for-further-processing-finally-top-10-users-on-the-basis-of-frequency-of-being-targeted-in-spam-are-selected-for-a-year&#34;&gt;To prepare this chart, a total of &lt;strong&gt;3M MemberEvents&lt;/strong&gt; were collected from the BigQuery dataset. Then all the events adding Top-100 most followed users as a collaborator were filtered out for further processing. Finally Top-10 users on the basis of frequency of being targeted in spam are selected for a year.&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &amp;lsquo;collaboration spam&amp;rsquo; &lt;a href=&#34;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/26224256/how-to-reject-remove-yourself-from-a-collaborative-github-repo&#34;&gt;was a real problem&lt;/a&gt;. Finally, GitHub released &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/blog/2170-repository-invitations&#34;&gt;repository invitations&lt;/a&gt; to resolve it. Now you need to accept the invitations to let all your followers know about the repository.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://plot.ly/~octogrid/155/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; title=&#34;collaboration-spam-timeline&#34; style=&#34;display: block; text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://plot.ly/~octogrid/155.png&#34; alt=&#34;collaboration-spam-timeline&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;width: 640px;&#34;  width=&#34;640&#34; onerror=&#34;this.onerror=null;this.src=&#39;https://plot.ly/404.png&#39;;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;script data-plotly=&#34;octogrid:155&#34;  src=&#34;https://plot.ly/embed.js&#34; async&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &amp;lsquo;repository invitation&amp;rsquo; feature has reduced the &amp;lsquo;collaboration spam&amp;rsquo; on GitHub significantly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s my exploration with the information dynamics on GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I do have some questions unanswered. For now, I will keep them as &lt;strong&gt;secret&lt;/strong&gt;. Also, I&amp;rsquo;m envious of the data people at GitHub, because they have access to much more data, I can only dream to have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am thinking of collecting additional data using some other ways, though I don&amp;rsquo;t have the format ready now, just a thought. You can keep an eye on my &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; to get the updates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;data-source&#34;&gt;Data Source&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://hn.algolia.com/api&#34;&gt;Hacker News API (Algolia)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GitHub Archive dataset (BigQuery)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;visualization-courtesy&#34;&gt;Visualization courtesy&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plot.ly&#34;&gt;Plotly&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://d3js.org/&#34;&gt;D3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Breaking into the Indian E-commerce</title>
      <link>http://pravj.github.io/blog/indian-ecommerce/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pravj.github.io/blog/indian-ecommerce/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Before I start telling you the story, I&amp;rsquo;m going to do an experiment. I&amp;rsquo;ll write the summary of this post first, just to stick you around, in case you are one among the people who don&amp;rsquo;t read to the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;tl-dr&#34;&gt;tl;dr&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.myntra.com/&#34;&gt;Myntra&lt;/a&gt; is India&amp;rsquo;s largest online fashion and lifestyle store, as they say. Which is owned by &lt;a href=&#34;http://flipkart.com/&#34;&gt;Flipkart&lt;/a&gt;, one of the big players in Indian E-commerce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found a little opening in the flow of their online movement and used it to collect some information(&lt;em&gt;not private though&lt;/em&gt;). Using this information we can see the way &amp;lsquo;online shopping&amp;rsquo; is escalating in the country, and the role &lt;em&gt;Myntra&lt;/em&gt; and the people are playing in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sounds interesting? Hold on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;emergence-of-the-idea&#34;&gt;Emergence of the idea&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me tell you, how did I get started with this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this happened recently, when I was looking for some &lt;em&gt;T-Shirts&lt;/em&gt; with my friend. We placed a shared order for two and a pair of shoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever you order from Myntra, you get a &lt;em&gt;text message&lt;/em&gt; on your registered mobile number, giving you a link where you can &lt;em&gt;track your order&lt;/em&gt;. Each order is given a unique identifier of length 4 because it&amp;rsquo;s a shortened URL to fit well in a text message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I opened that link in my phone and it worked, saying that the details of your order are yet to be updated. Then I tried a different URL, not mine, of course, all thanks to my disruptive mind. It worked again, now this was something to pay attention to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know, 4 is a &lt;em&gt;nanoscopic&lt;/em&gt; number if a computer is your best friend. I think you can guess what happened next, I couldn&amp;rsquo;t sleep properly thinking about my next move to just have all the order details. Right from crawling and storing the data to analysing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;crawler-infrastructure&#34;&gt;Crawler Infrastructure&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being a &lt;em&gt;pessimistic&lt;/em&gt; person, as one of my friends calls me. I end up thinking too much about all the possible edge cases. Something similar happened with the design of the crawling system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the saying goes, &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;A thief believes everybody steals&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;. I was afraid that my collection signatures(IP) will be blocked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have read my last post &lt;a href=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/blog/bangalore-taxis/&#34;&gt;Jump in to ride all the Bangalore taxis, at once&lt;/a&gt;; I said that you should not hit the resource at a constant time period, it&amp;rsquo;s a basic heuristic to identify bots. I considered that, it was a simple thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now comes the main thing I was afraid of, &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;What if they catch me while trying to collect all the orders in a sequential manner (alphabetically increasing uid)&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I couldn&amp;rsquo;t take a risk of losing the data, I designed my solution around it. I developed two things, &lt;em&gt;Engine&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Station&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Engine&lt;/em&gt; is the one who takes care of the identifier generation and distribution. It uses a little &lt;em&gt;group theory&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;anagram properties&lt;/em&gt; to generate &lt;em&gt;non-sequential unique identifiers of fixed length&lt;/em&gt;. It generates them in advance and serve you &lt;em&gt;on demand&lt;/em&gt; while taking care of the stock by generating in the background when you start approaching the bottom of the vessel. To know more about &lt;em&gt;Engine&lt;/em&gt;, you can stalk its &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/engine&#34;&gt;repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Station&lt;/em&gt; is a Node.js package(&lt;em&gt;private obviously&lt;/em&gt;) running a &lt;em&gt;Nightmare&lt;/em&gt; instance for &lt;em&gt;headless browsing&lt;/em&gt;. From &lt;em&gt;Engine&lt;/em&gt;, it collects the next set of identifiers to fetch and then assemble all the necessary information before shipping it to the storage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/crawler-infra.png&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Crawler Design&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together they solve the problem with sequential crawling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now one more thing, the collection signature(IP) is still vulnerable to blocking. I found a (working) solution for it right on the Engineering blog of Myntra. They have an interesting post named &lt;a href=&#34;http://myntra.github.io/2015/01/19/dynamic-bot-detection-using-bloom-filters/&#34;&gt;Dynamic Bot Detection Using Bloom Filters&lt;/a&gt;, which labels you as a &lt;em&gt;bot&lt;/em&gt; if you have sent relatively more requests in the past 60 seconds. So the time difference &lt;em&gt;station&lt;/em&gt; assigns between two consecutive requests is dynamically set such that the &lt;em&gt;Bloom Filter&lt;/em&gt; is unable to catch it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Planning too much on the &lt;em&gt;Information Retrieval&lt;/em&gt; part has been a good exercise though, I&amp;rsquo;m thinking about working on a &lt;em&gt;Machine Learning approach of Bot Detection&lt;/em&gt;, where movement of a user from one page to another on service/website is mapped as &lt;em&gt;state transitions&lt;/em&gt; of a &lt;em&gt;Markov Chain&lt;/em&gt;, and anyone who violates the &lt;em&gt;transition probability range&lt;/em&gt; is a suspicious visitor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rough idea, leave that for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;statistical-nature-of-the-data&#34;&gt;Statistical nature of the data&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I read more and more research papers and live next to some great statistician&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Internet Residences&lt;/em&gt;, I know that you can&amp;rsquo;t conclude &lt;em&gt;a thing&lt;/em&gt; from a small dataset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the dataset that I have collected, there are 1045 &lt;em&gt;Returned Orders&lt;/em&gt;, 4406 &lt;em&gt;Cancelled Orders&lt;/em&gt; and 6368 &lt;em&gt;Completed Orders&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Returned Order&lt;/em&gt; means the package was returned back due to some reasons, and &lt;em&gt;Cancelled Orders&lt;/em&gt; means it was cancelled by the customer before shipping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This could have been a bigger one, so I&amp;rsquo;ll try not to &lt;em&gt;conclude&lt;/em&gt; a result here but we can see the customer behavior and the service &lt;em&gt;Myntra&lt;/em&gt; provides. Coming to a result from this data would be a case of &lt;em&gt;overfitting&lt;/em&gt; essentially.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the dataset is small, it&amp;rsquo;s distributed over a &lt;em&gt;time continuum&lt;/em&gt; instead of being a &lt;em&gt;discrete segment&lt;/em&gt;, because of the internal working of &lt;em&gt;Engine&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/engine.png&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;How Engine generate identifiers&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are all set to take off now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;when-does-india-shops&#34;&gt;When does India shops?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As long as I remember, I have ordered something online in the evening, around 06-07 PM. But this is not the case for everyone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://plot.ly/~pravj/51/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; title=&#34;When does India shops?&#34; style=&#34;display: block; text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://plot.ly/~pravj/51.png&#34; alt=&#34;When does India shops?&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;width: 600px;&#34;  width=&#34;600&#34; onerror=&#34;this.onerror=null;this.src=&#39;https://plot.ly/404.png&#39;;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;script data-plotly=&#34;pravj:51&#34;  src=&#34;https://plot.ly/embed.js&#34; async&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can see that there are two concerted segments. One from 09:00 AM to 05:00 PM in the evening and the other is from 06:00 PM to midnight. Not many orders are there during the &lt;em&gt;bed time&lt;/em&gt;, after midnight till the dawn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The morning peak is around 10:00 AM, which is near the usual opening hours of &lt;em&gt;Myntra&amp;rsquo;s big discount sales&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Returned Orders&lt;/em&gt; are present throughout the days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The presence of orders at every possible time of day shows the ease in the life of people using &amp;lsquo;online shopping&amp;rsquo;. You have got a need and there are platforms to fulfill that. Otherwise, why would someone order at 02:00 AM in the morning?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Myntra&lt;/em&gt; also runs a &lt;em&gt;same day delivery&lt;/em&gt; program where they ship your order in 24 hours, across the country. And in our dataset, a significant number of such orders were placed after midnight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;from-where-does-india-shops&#34;&gt;From where does India shops?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div id=&#39;customer-map&#39; style=&#34;height:400px;&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a clustered map of places in the country, that I found as &lt;em&gt;final destinations&lt;/em&gt; of &lt;em&gt;completed orders&lt;/em&gt;. This means that the map ignores the number of orders at a place, it just represents the &lt;em&gt;geographic distribution&lt;/em&gt; of the orders. Also, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t count a locality multiple times. For example, &lt;em&gt;Agartala&lt;/em&gt; has 2-3 different final destinations but they are clustered to a single place/centre, &lt;em&gt;Agartala COD Centre 3&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was magnificent to see this map when I plotted it first time. Not because my program worked, but to see the markers in extreme areas of the country, especially in the &lt;em&gt;Northeast India&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s good to see that almost every region of the country is here. There are 432 different places in here. You are free to zoom in and check out your region, if available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After seeing this big coverage I would say, they can expand easily to &lt;em&gt;Bangladesh&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have used &lt;em&gt;Google&amp;rsquo;s Geocoding API&lt;/em&gt; to convert a place name to its coordinates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-long-does-it-take-to-deliver-your-order&#34;&gt;How long does it take to deliver your order?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://plot.ly/~pravj648/16/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; title=&#34;How long does it take to deliver your order?&#34; style=&#34;display: block; text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://plot.ly/~pravj648/16.png&#34; alt=&#34;How long does it take to deliver your order?&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;width: 600px;&#34;  width=&#34;600&#34; onerror=&#34;this.onerror=null;this.src=&#39;https://plot.ly/404.png&#39;;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;script data-plotly=&#34;pravj648:16&#34;  src=&#34;https://plot.ly/embed.js&#34; async&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you live in north India or near(&lt;em&gt;measured in terms of direct road connectivity&lt;/em&gt;) the warehouses of &lt;em&gt;Myntra&lt;/em&gt;, you &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; have your package in 24 hours. In the dataset, many orders from Nation Capital Region, Jaipur and Bangalore have delivered in the same day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Otherwise, majority of the orders takes 3 to 4 days across the country, except the &lt;em&gt;North East&lt;/em&gt;(Guwahati, Imphal) and &lt;em&gt;West Coast&lt;/em&gt;(Mumbai Parel, Antop Hill) region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have calculated the delivery delay by subtracting the time of order being placed from the &lt;em&gt;last event time&lt;/em&gt; in the events timeline of a &lt;em&gt;complete order&lt;/em&gt;. The timeline consists of all the sub-details like &lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;Order is placed&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;Order is packed&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;In transit&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;Arrived at delivery center&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;Order out for delivery&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;Delivered&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt; etc. Which is &lt;em&gt;error prone&lt;/em&gt; because they seems to update some order after awhile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the &lt;em&gt;tail&lt;/em&gt; of the curve, the delay in some cases seems to be caused by customers actually, some reason were &lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;CID - COD(cash on delivery) AMOUNT NOT READY&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt;, &amp;lsquo;&lt;em&gt;Consignee Out Of Station; Shipment un-delivered&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;&lt;em&gt;Undelivered due to - Consignee Residence Closed&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rsquo; etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;shared-logistics&#34;&gt;Shared Logistics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://plot.ly/~pravj648/145/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; title=&#34;Shared Logistics&#34; style=&#34;display: block; text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://plot.ly/~pravj648/145.png&#34; alt=&#34;Shared Logistics&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;width: 1258px;&#34;  width=&#34;1258&#34; onerror=&#34;this.onerror=null;this.src=&#39;https://plot.ly/404.png&#39;;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;script data-plotly=&#34;pravj648:145&#34;  src=&#34;https://plot.ly/embed.js&#34; async&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having a great logistics service is a key point for online shops. Both &lt;em&gt;Myntra&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Flipkart&lt;/em&gt; have their own such services named &lt;em&gt;Myntra Logistics&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;EKart Logistics&lt;/em&gt; respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To deliver products out of their range or to overcome the heavy demand during &lt;em&gt;big discount sales&lt;/em&gt;, they ship the products with third party logistic providers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the dataset you can see that majority of the orders have been shipped by &lt;em&gt;Myntra Logistics&lt;/em&gt; itself, and then by &lt;em&gt;EKart&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Delhivery&lt;/em&gt; is an emerging logistic solution provider in the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we can see the regions in which &lt;em&gt;FedEx&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;DTDC&lt;/em&gt; were used for delivery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://plot.ly/~pravj648/159/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; title=&#34;Outsourced Logistic Partner Network&#34; style=&#34;display: block; text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://plot.ly/~pravj648/159.png&#34; alt=&#34;Outsourced Logistic Partner Network&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;width: 1258px;&#34;  width=&#34;1258&#34; onerror=&#34;this.onerror=null;this.src=&#39;https://plot.ly/404.png&#39;;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;script data-plotly=&#34;pravj648:159&#34;  src=&#34;https://plot.ly/embed.js&#34; async&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;end-of-reason-sale-purchase-behavior&#34;&gt;&amp;lsquo;End of Reason Sale&amp;rsquo; Purchase Behavior&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;End of Reason Sale&amp;rsquo; (&lt;em&gt;EORS&lt;/em&gt;) from 18-19 July was one of the biggest sales by &lt;em&gt;Myntra&lt;/em&gt; in the year 2015. It was after when their previous sale faced criticism because of &lt;a href=&#34;http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/tech/tech-news/After-botching-up-sale-Myntra-apologizes-to-users/articleshow/47528824.cms&#34;&gt;technical glitches&lt;/a&gt; in May 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;EORS&lt;/em&gt; started on 18th July from 08:00 AM. Here is a heatmap of order from dataset ranging from 17th July to 20th July.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://plot.ly/~pravj648/166/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; title=&#34;EORS Purchase Behavior&#34; style=&#34;display: block; text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://plot.ly/~pravj648/166.png&#34; alt=&#34;EORS Purchase Behavior&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;width: 1258px;&#34;  width=&#34;1258&#34; onerror=&#34;this.onerror=null;this.src=&#39;https://plot.ly/404.png&#39;;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;script data-plotly=&#34;pravj648:166&#34;  src=&#34;https://plot.ly/embed.js&#34; async&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can see a pattern similar to the &lt;em&gt;sale days&lt;/em&gt; for 20th July, which supports the notion that &lt;em&gt;EORS&lt;/em&gt; was &lt;a href=&#34;http://webcache.googleusercontent.com/search?q=cache:DuSB-kY2Il4J:https://batch.com/insights/push/ey8v28jv00zd+&amp;amp;cd=7&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;ct=clnk&amp;amp;gl=in&#34;&gt;extended after its official period&lt;/a&gt; for some styles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;brands-on-the-platform&#34;&gt;Brands on the platform&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Myntra&lt;/em&gt; being an online shopping service mainly, also &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rediff.com/business/report/myntra-to-have-usd-100-mn-in-house-brands/20150805.htm&#34;&gt;owns in-house fashion brands&lt;/a&gt; like Roadster, Dressberry, Anouk (for women), Mast &amp;amp; Harbour, Kook N Keech, Yellow Kite (for kids) and Invictus etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is an &lt;em&gt;approx&lt;/em&gt; gender segmentation of brands(top 50 in the dataset) on the platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://plot.ly/~pravj648/105/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; title=&#34;Gender Segmentation of brands&#34; style=&#34;display: block; text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://plot.ly/~pravj648/105.png&#34; alt=&#34;Gender Segmentation of brands&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;width: 600px;&#34;  width=&#34;600&#34; onerror=&#34;this.onerror=null;this.src=&#39;https://plot.ly/404.png&#39;;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;script data-plotly=&#34;pravj648:105&#34;  src=&#34;https://plot.ly/embed.js&#34; async&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;do-small-shopkeepers-purchase-online-to-sell-in-their-locality&#34;&gt;Do small shopkeepers purchase online to sell in their locality?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do you generally purchase online? Whatever it&amp;rsquo;s, but you don&amp;rsquo;t actually buy 3 shirts of the same type, do you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is something I found suspicious when I was looking in the dataset for orders having a lot of products in one shipment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/bulk-order.png&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Does small shopkeepers purchase from Myntra to sell in their locality?&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This picture shows products in a shipment which contains shoes only, of similar types.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although it&amp;rsquo;s exactly how the selling process works, you buy from a person and sell to someone else. But in this case, it seems weird to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought &amp;lsquo;online shopping services&amp;rsquo; are just adjacent node to us on the &lt;em&gt;Internet Services Graph&lt;/em&gt; and this is how people use it. This indicates towards the existence of a community which is still away from the Internet, its benefits and is being cheated. Cheating in the sense that shopkeepers may buy from online services during sales and then sell them at relatively high prices to local customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;inference&#34;&gt;Inference&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I have said that I won&amp;rsquo;t conclude results from this data, but I guess we can&amp;rsquo;t deny some facts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;Online Shopping&amp;rsquo; is a perk that the boom on Internet and Startups has given to the country. It&amp;rsquo;s shaping the economy by creating a variety of employments. Still a lot of people are yet to go through this makeover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the number of Internet users is growing in the country, we can expect more good to happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;probable-fix&#34;&gt;Probable Fix&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think a simple solution can be employed here to avoid intruders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To ask for the associated &lt;em&gt;mobile number&lt;/em&gt; while checking details of an order, if the user is not logged in. One can guess the &lt;em&gt;unique id&lt;/em&gt; for orders but not the &lt;em&gt;mobile number&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;disclaimer&#34;&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is going to be a little contradictory. According to Oxford Dictionary, &lt;em&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/em&gt; means &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;A statement that denies something, especially responsibility&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won&amp;rsquo;t do that. This time again, I&amp;rsquo;m aware that such collection of data is a wrong act in &lt;em&gt;Internet terms&lt;/em&gt;. But I can&amp;rsquo;t control myself when I get such an idea and some questions that can only be solved by visualizing the data, referring to &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anscombe%27s_quartet&#34;&gt;Anscombe&amp;rsquo;s quartet&lt;/a&gt;. I just wish I&amp;rsquo;m not getting prosecuted for this. The dataset doesn&amp;rsquo;t contain any private information(&lt;em&gt;name, mobile number, home address&lt;/em&gt;) of someone, &lt;em&gt;it&amp;rsquo;s not at all available.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/blitz.engine&#34;&gt;Engine&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Station&lt;/em&gt;? I have decided not to open source the &lt;em&gt;Station&lt;/em&gt;, which was used to collect the data. Almost all programs I have used to &lt;em&gt;analyse&lt;/em&gt; the data are available at &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/Fuel&#34;&gt;Fuel&lt;/a&gt;, without the actual data I have collected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are reading this, you have passed my experiment. Let me gift you a free &lt;b&gt;Happy New Year&lt;/b&gt; wish.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jump in to ride all the Bangalore taxis, at once</title>
      <link>http://pravj.github.io/blog/bangalore-taxis/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pravj.github.io/blog/bangalore-taxis/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;All right, just imagine that you have popcorn with you, because I know that you don&amp;rsquo;t have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to do this report when I was in Bangalore this summer, &lt;em&gt;Sillicon Valley of India&lt;/em&gt;. You can observe a gob of information flowing through in such metropolitan population. People ordering/delivering meal, groceries or literally everything by online orders, people booking a vehicle and riding in no time, people booking a seat for dinner/movie and many more thing to generate the logs. Which is fascinating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One day while riding a cab, I got this plan to go into the rectangle map the app was showing, and run around. Just like what &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oKCIMX2dsEc&#34;&gt;Joey did in an episode of Friends&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To execute this all, I had to collect the relavent information and work on the possible outcomes of the collected information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here in this post I have written the procedure I followed, things I have feared of, interesting results I saw and count of tea cups I have sipped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-brick-wall&#34;&gt;The brick wall&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A little more theory and then we will get right to the practicals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While setting up the collection infrastucture, I realised that I might be under the &lt;em&gt;terms and services&lt;/em&gt; monster. This suspicion helped me lading in the depression zone where I wasn&amp;rsquo;t sure if the work I have done so far was worth doing or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought about asking the respective organization for a permission but I was too afraid to hear a negative reply. So I went ahead and ignored this. Because this report does not publicize any private property like vehicle numbers, mobile numbers and all. Even I wasn&amp;rsquo;t able to access such private properties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The major reason was, I have already bunked too many classes for this, so terminating the work wasn&amp;rsquo;t an option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m aware that it&amp;rsquo;s a wrong act but I couldn&amp;rsquo;t stop the &lt;em&gt;David McCandless&lt;/em&gt; inside me from doing this. I hope I&amp;rsquo;m not getting sued for this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This report is based on the data from a particular taxi service in a single day&amp;rsquo;s time span, so it may be a little baised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;information-retrieval&#34;&gt;Information Retrieval&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Collecting the right information was the foundation for the whole game. Possibility of getting blocked was also there, once you come under the &lt;em&gt;Night&amp;rsquo;s watch&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The task reduces to finding &lt;em&gt;how many taxis are there in the city&lt;/em&gt; (at a time), &lt;em&gt;where they are&lt;/em&gt; and then keep doing this all the day &lt;em&gt;without getting caught&lt;/em&gt;. Easy Peasy?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I came up with the solution to find places in the city which are equally seperated and then drawing circles on those points would cover the entire city. A fake &lt;em&gt;cab search request&lt;/em&gt; would return us the status of cabs around that place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For that I planned to start from the center of the city, iterate this on adjacent places using a &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Finite-state_machine&#34;&gt;Finite State Machine&lt;/a&gt; to stay aware of the ending state (when we are done with all such place-combinations) and state changes (when we are out of the city&amp;rsquo;s boundary in a particular direction).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While writing the FSM, I found an efficient alternative to iterate over all the equally separated places which comes under the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minimum_bounding_rectangle&#34;&gt;Minimum Bounding Rectangle&lt;/a&gt; of Bangalore, and check if the cab service is available in that area or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Equally spacing those spots minimizes the total number of requests made, which descreases the chances of getting blocked, &lt;em&gt;if there is such service on the other side&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/point-net.png&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Equally separated places&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once all those places were spotted, I made a &lt;em&gt;cab search request&lt;/em&gt; on all those spots every 15 minutes. I think it&amp;rsquo;s a bit more time than the &lt;em&gt;average trip duration&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later I realised a mistake that I have forgot to count the time making requests to all the places, so the separation went up to almost 19 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I continuously pumped all those responses to a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iron.io/mq/&#34;&gt;IronMQ&lt;/a&gt; powered message queue and then imported all the data into a local &lt;a href=&#34;http://rethinkdb.com/&#34;&gt;RethinkDB&lt;/a&gt; instance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One should try not to hit the source at a constant timeperiod (like 15 minutes in this case), because that&amp;rsquo;s the basic heuristic for smart &lt;em&gt;bot detection&lt;/em&gt; systems. I had to do that because it was needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;service-availability&#34;&gt;Service Availability&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;em&gt;Minimum Bounding Rectangle&lt;/em&gt;, I found a total of 272 spots but only 96 of them have the cab service available. The distance between adjacent places is 2 Mile (3.2186 KM.), which is almost same as the equivalent area we see while booking a cab on mobile applications (on default zoom level).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&#39;availability-map&#39; style=&#34;height:400px;&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although this is biased because it represent only a single day of activity but it gives us a little overview of the situation. I&amp;rsquo;m not that familier with the places in the bangalore but I found an interesting thing, maybe a native resident can confirm this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See those two circles at the top of the rectangle, they are too far from the main localities but we have the service there. Those circles contains places like &lt;em&gt;Rajanukunte&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Doddajala&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Chikkajala&lt;/em&gt; etc. On googling their name, you will get comparatively more listings about property/real-estate business compared to other areas in the city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s like the scenario we had with &lt;em&gt;Delhi - Gurgaon&lt;/em&gt; some time back, those places are under &lt;em&gt;Industrialization&lt;/em&gt;. Which makes it a good reason to have the taxi services availability, no matter some famous places around the city doesn&amp;rsquo;t have this cab service, like the &lt;em&gt;Bannerghatta National Park&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;guardians-vehicles&#34;&gt;Guardians (Vehicles)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the day, the system spotted a total of 897 different cabs, with 4 different types.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;RethinkDB query&lt;/em&gt; to count different type of cabs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;r.db(&#39;taxis&#39;).table(&#39;datacenter&#39;)
	.filter({available: true})
	.pluck(&#39;type&#39;, &#39;cab_id&#39;)
	.distinct()
	.group(&#39;type&#39;)
	.count()
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;row&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;col s12 m6 l3 center-align&#34; style=&#34;color:#DDD;background:#00648C;&#34;&gt;
      &lt;h4&gt;#Hatchback 525&lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;col s12 m6 l3 center-align&#34; style=&#34;color:#DDD;background:#10698C;&#34;&gt;
      &lt;h4&gt;#Sedan 324&lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;col s12 m6 l3 center-align&#34; style=&#34;color:#DDD;background:#4F7B8C;&#34;&gt;
      &lt;h4&gt;#Nano 46&lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;col s12 m6 l3 center-align&#34; style=&#34;color:#DDD;background:#7497A5;&#34;&gt;
      &lt;h4&gt;#SUV 2&lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cab-availability-according-to-time&#34;&gt;Cab Availability (according to time)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do you think about the number of cabs available at 8:30 AM and 8:30 PM? You will see that the number is more in the morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a theory, &lt;em&gt;Utilitarianism&lt;/em&gt;. Which states that everyone wants to maximize their utility. Take the example of E-commerce. Between so many brands, sellers and customers, everyone wants to increase their benefits. For e-sellers, scheduling an online sell is just like a game of chess. Each team want to win it. (Quoted by a good person)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is how the cab availability distribution over time looks like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/distribution.png&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Cab availability distribution over time&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it goes like, the probability of a taxi being hired is high during the morning when people are going to the office/college, then it decreases during the noon-time, increases again during the 4 PM - 6 PM window when people are going back home or going out for their evening gig, and decreses in the night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is how drivers play their part as per &lt;em&gt;Utilitarianism&lt;/em&gt;, which reflects in the number of available taxis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;rise-of-the-guardians-vehicles&#34;&gt;Rise of the Guardians (Vehicles)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the responses I got for the cab search requests, there was a field representing a timestamp, constant for a particular cab. Initially when I saw that, I thought it&amp;rsquo;s the last time a cab was booked but it wasn&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5 out of the 897 total cabs have that field equal to 1, which translates to January 1, 1970. This indicates that initially the field wasn&amp;rsquo;t part of their architecture, but later they adopted it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The uniqueness and time range of all those fields strongly supports that it was the time when a cab got associated with the organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/cab-timeline.png&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Cab timeline&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Horizontal scale for this graph is cropped because almost 85+ % events belongs to the year 2015 itself. Which seems a bit weird, but it&amp;rsquo;s what it&amp;rsquo;s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cabs-around-the-city-throughout-the-day&#34;&gt;Cabs around the city throughout the day&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div id=&#39;map&#39; style=&#34;height:400px;&#34;&gt;
    &lt;span id=&#39;info&#39; class=&#39;info&#39; style=&#39;padding:10px;background:#fff;position:relative;top:17px;right:-50px;z-index:100;&#39;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This particular map represents the geographic view of the &lt;em&gt;cab availability&lt;/em&gt; (according to time) diagram. Where total cabs at a time are distributed accross the city according to their actual positions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now if you are thinking about the places where most of the cabs are, I have created another map for that, scroll down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cab-availability-index&#34;&gt;Cab Availability Index&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This map is somewhat inspired from the Housing&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://housing.com/blog/2013/11/14/launching-child-friendliness-index-heat-maps/&#34;&gt;Child Friendly Index&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It uses those equally seperated circles to count total cabs in them throughout the day, and uses the relative percentage as the opacity of each circle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;RethinkDB query&lt;/em&gt; that counts the cabs which are in a 2 mile circle centered at &amp;lsquo;centerPoint&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;r.db(&#39;taxis&#39;).table(&#39;datacenter&#39;)
	.filter({available: true})
	.pluck(&#39;cab_lat&#39;, &#39;cab_lng&#39;)
	.distinct()
	.map(function(instance) {
		return r.circle(centerPoint, 2, {unit: &#39;mi&#39;})
			.includes(r.point(instance(&#39;cab_lat&#39;), instance(&#39;cab_lat&#39;)))
	})
	.count(true)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;div id=&#39;dmap&#39; style=&#39;height:400px;&#39;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neighbourhoods having maximum availability index are mostly in the &lt;em&gt;northern-western&lt;/em&gt; and a little &lt;em&gt;central&lt;/em&gt; part of the bangalore. Which consists of some big educational institutes as &lt;em&gt;Indian Institute of Science&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Bangalore University&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;R.V. College of Engineering&lt;/em&gt;, some famous tourist spots as &lt;em&gt;Lalbagh Botanical Garden&lt;/em&gt; to contribute to the higher availability density.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along with that, reports shows that &lt;em&gt;northern-western&lt;/em&gt; bangalore has maximum population density in the city. Check out these images (&lt;a href=&#34;http://wgbis.ces.iisc.ernet.in/biodiversity/pubs/ETR/ETR55/Population%20Density.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;latest&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://wgbis.ces.iisc.ernet.in/biodiversity/pubs/ces_tr/TR118_SPoonancha/Index1_clip_image002_0000.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;old&lt;/a&gt;) from &lt;em&gt;Centre for Ecological Sciences, IISc&lt;/em&gt; for the reference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cab-that-travelled-the-most&#34;&gt;Cab that travelled the most&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I have told you that initially I&amp;rsquo;d misread a timestamp field as the time when a cab was last hired. Writing a precise (almost) algorithm to find the path travelled by cab using current/past location and the last booking time would have been easy that way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the currecnt implementation, I have used the locations between adjacent appearances of a cab to find the approximate distance travelled by the vehicle. It assumes that the cab travelled from position A to position B despite being sufficient time difference between both appearances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;RethinkDB query&lt;/em&gt; that collects the chronological appearances of each taxi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;r.db(&#39;taxis&#39;).table(&#39;datacenter&#39;)
	.filter({available: true})
	.without(&#39;id&#39;, &#39;place_lat&#39;, &#39;place_lng&#39;, &#39;duration&#39;, &#39;distance&#39;)
	.group(&#39;cab_id&#39;)
	.pluck(&#39;cab_lat&#39;, &#39;cab_lng&#39;, &#39;index&#39;, &#39;timestamp&#39;)
	.orderBy(&#39;index&#39;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To watch the jounrney &lt;em&gt;time-lapse&lt;/em&gt; of the cab who travelled the most, press the &lt;em&gt;play button&lt;/em&gt; below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&#39;cmap&#39; style=&#39;height:400px;&#39;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style=&#39;width:60px;margin: 0 auto;&#39;&gt;
    &lt;h2 id=&#34;replay-btn&#34; style=&#39;position:relative;top:-100px;padding-left:15px;color:#343434;background-color:rgba(255, 255, 255, 0.8);width:60px;height:50px;cursor:pointer;&#39;&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#39;ion-play&#39;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;is-this-all-fake-just-like-uber-illusion&#34;&gt;Is this all fake, just like Uber illusion?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you remember those &lt;em&gt;phantom car&lt;/em&gt; stories of Uber?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a research which revealed that Uber shows a mirage of tiny black cabs moving around you, when you do a cab search. Just to convince you that a cab is there for you. Study concluded that the cab network you see around, is not real-time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to analyse the &lt;em&gt;traffic status&lt;/em&gt; using the response data I had. My objective was to find the regression in the &lt;em&gt;cab response time&lt;/em&gt; (time taken by a cab to reach you) and &lt;em&gt;time of the day&lt;/em&gt;. Because the sixth sense says that the &lt;em&gt;cab response time&lt;/em&gt; should be high when there is &lt;em&gt;high traffic&lt;/em&gt; in some areas of the city, likely in those peek hours (morning and evening time).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;cab response time&lt;/em&gt; seems to be dependant on the distance only, which looks like a &lt;em&gt;step function&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/restime.png&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Cab Response Time&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I realised that there wasn&amp;rsquo;t any fluctuation in the &lt;em&gt;response time&lt;/em&gt;, it was same for a particular distance between the cab and the user (simulated), all the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which implies that similar to Uber, this cab network isn&amp;rsquo;t real-time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A nice explanation of the &lt;em&gt;phantom cars&lt;/em&gt; is available &lt;a href=&#34;http://motherboard.vice.com/read/Ubers-phantom-cabs?update&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;people-don-t-solve-a-problem-until-they-get-one&#34;&gt;People don&amp;rsquo;t solve a problem until they get one&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This simulated user interaction is wrong to the system. Can be easily converted into a &lt;em&gt;service denial&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my case, I was changing the user(simulated) location frequently, so fast that a human can&amp;rsquo;t reach there in a fraction of second (traversing whole Bangalore in 3 minutes).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the service allows a user to book a cab for someone else (who is far away from where the real user is), the monitoring system should take care of the conversion rates. Someone trying to book a cab for someone else this fast, then not booking a single cab, and then repeating this every 15 minute all the day is a plain pattern to detect. Which should be detected. I hope somebody will fix this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s it, get out of the cab now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have decided not to release the collected data and code for the data retrieval. Everything else including the data processing part can be found at &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj&#34;&gt;pravj/bangalore-taxis&lt;/a&gt; repository. Thanks to &lt;em&gt;RethinkDB&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Mapbox&lt;/em&gt;, you guys are really amazing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script src=&#39;{{http://localhost:4000}}/public/lib/taxis.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Development story of puzzl</title>
      <link>http://pravj.github.io/blog/development-story-of-puzzl/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pravj.github.io/blog/development-story-of-puzzl/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Lets start with that old promotion rant I use all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should have a look at &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/puzzl&#34;&gt;puzzl&lt;/a&gt;, if you haven&amp;rsquo;t yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-this-is-all-about&#34;&gt;What this is all about?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is about development of a sliding-puzzle game I made recently, named &lt;em&gt;puzzl&lt;/em&gt;. I refer it as an &lt;em&gt;intelligent version&lt;/em&gt; of the classical sliding puzzle game, and I&amp;rsquo;ll explain the reason behind this. Stay awake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/puzzl.gif&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Puzzl in action&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;for-what-joy&#34;&gt;For What Joy?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, that&amp;rsquo;s the best question. Why did I do that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a force behind everything we do, so the same goes for any new software product we see in the jungle or a new medicine or whatever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They all try to solve some problems. A new version of a software has some bugs fixed from the older one and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But hey! you can develop a game without such force anytime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specially, when you are supposed to study for your exams. Tested, &lt;em&gt;rule of thumb&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;exam-time-bamboozlement&#34;&gt;Exam-time bamboozlement&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;session&lt;/em&gt; when your mind&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;stream&lt;/em&gt; is *grep*ing too many *event*s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You feel like, put this exam thing in left and consider this problem-&lt;em&gt;blah&lt;/em&gt;, because the world needs you. Right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s gone after a nice sleep, like hangover. But it may attack you again on the next exam day, depending on your performance in last exam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You think about too many things, however some are out of your domain though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, &lt;em&gt;A bicycle for old aged people&lt;/em&gt;. I found it an actual problem by the way, as I often see them having trouble riding the native big bicycles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then you think that it should run on its own, so you draw a sketch and invest your time in adding solar panels at proper orientation, so that charging is not something to worry about, no matter where the sun is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then you suddenly realize that you&amp;rsquo;re about to transform into &lt;em&gt;Tony Stark&lt;/em&gt;. You&amp;rsquo;re working on a problem which comes under &lt;em&gt;Mechanical Engineering&lt;/em&gt;. And there is no chance you can complete this without either having a degree in it or a girlfriend from that stream. By the way, both the solutions are difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A similar bamboozlement was the reason behind the game &lt;em&gt;puzzl&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was setting up my camp for the mid-term exam of &lt;em&gt;Artificial Intelligence&lt;/em&gt; course. And then I stumbled upon this &lt;em&gt;sliding-puzzle&lt;/em&gt; game thing in book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I thought, what about a sliding-puzzle game for terminals?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s it. I was done with further preparation. I even spent the entire exam time divising the &lt;em&gt;scoring mechanism&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;logo&lt;/em&gt; for the game. The last page of the solution paper and my low score is the proof.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-problem-statement&#34;&gt;The problem statement&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sliding-puzzle&lt;/em&gt; games have many variants. I decided to move ahead with the one having a 3x3 board, the &lt;em&gt;8-puzzle&lt;/em&gt;. 8 out of 9 tiles have some numbers on them, one tile is blank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All you have to do is, arrange all tiles in a particular order. Lets say, in increasing order with the blank tile being the last one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/states.jpg&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;8 puzzle game states&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sounds a little easy, taking user inputs, moving the tiles accordingly and checking that whether we are done with the game or not. So, I decided to enhance both the development and playing processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To solve the game in background and track user moves accordingly or give them hints. Poor humans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-solution&#34;&gt;The solution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution is pretty simple actually. There is a blank tile in the game board and you can reach to a different configuration by moving that blank tile in atmost 4 directions, according to its current position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, how do you make a computer solve this, efficiently?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can be reduced to a problem where any game board configuration is a &lt;em&gt;node&lt;/em&gt; and you can reach to a &lt;em&gt;node&lt;/em&gt; from its &lt;em&gt;parent node&lt;/em&gt; by applying a &lt;em&gt;successor function&lt;/em&gt;, which is the movement of the blank tile in this case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, this is a &lt;em&gt;graph search problem&lt;/em&gt; now. You have a &lt;em&gt;start state&lt;/em&gt; and you have to reach at a &lt;em&gt;goal state&lt;/em&gt; in minimum steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;puzzl&lt;/em&gt;, the algoirthm which solves this &lt;em&gt;graph search problem&lt;/em&gt; is &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A*_search_algorithm&#34;&gt;A* algorithm&lt;/a&gt;. As of now, it uses the easiest &lt;em&gt;Heuristic Function&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heuristic_function&#34;&gt;Misplaced Tiles Count&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The auto solving part sounds pretty easy, right? Like a walk while eating a cake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there were some other interesting challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;primary-language&#34;&gt;Primary Language&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I opted for Golang as the primary language of &lt;em&gt;puzzl&lt;/em&gt;, just because &lt;em&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m loving it&lt;/em&gt; and I wanted it to takeoff comparatively faster than other solutions, let&amp;rsquo;s say Python.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some work, I started getting ideas of other features and I was happy with my language choice, as Go is the best solution I can think of for them. I&amp;rsquo;ll talk about those features in a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;solvability-of-the-problem&#34;&gt;Solvability of the problem&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of those interesting parts I faced while making it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not all 8- puzzle game configurations are solvable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, for a 3x3 game board, there are a total of 362880 configurations possible(9!), but only half of them are actually solvable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially it took me a while to get it that why only some of them are solvable? But after going through &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;Notes on the 15 puzzle&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; paper by &lt;em&gt;Wm. Woolsey Johnson and William E. Story&lt;/em&gt; it was clear to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the &lt;em&gt;Mathematical Induction&lt;/em&gt; on what it was there in the paper, I have a sample game for you. You can spend rest of your life solving this, if you want to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/unsolvable-game.jpg&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Unsolvable sliding puzzle&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I added a package named &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/puzzl/blob/master/scanner/scanner.go&#34;&gt;scanner&lt;/a&gt; in the game, with the help of &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;Analysis of the Sixteen Puzzle&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;. It makes sure that any game configuration we are using, is really solvable. It uses another for the game, if one is not actually solvable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;notification-system&#34;&gt;Notification System&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this was the most interesting part. Developing a &lt;em&gt;Real time Notification System&lt;/em&gt; according to the game state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was done with writing the auto-solving background process for the game, I noticed that sometimes it takes a while to solve from the initial game configuration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, the hardest game configuration is solvable in 31 moves. So, when the game is solving it, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t properly respond to user inputs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It won&amp;rsquo;t respond in this way because the control flow architecture is &lt;em&gt;Synchronous&lt;/em&gt; now. It means that firstoff the game will solve itself in background and then stars accepting user inputs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this goes worse when the game is solving itself on each move because user input was wrong. A serious problem it was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here comes the concurrency primitives of Golang.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Concurrent programming is the beauty in Go. The language comes with built-in weapons, &lt;em&gt;goroutines&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;channels&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution works like this, we have to change the control flow architecture into &lt;em&gt;Asynchronous&lt;/em&gt; mode. Where the game would be notifying us that &lt;em&gt;OK, now I&amp;rsquo;m done with solving and you can give any input&lt;/em&gt;, and avoiding all user inputs gracefully till then without a crash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this can be used in many other aspects, notifying on a particular internal event. Like &lt;em&gt;the game is complete&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;you just did a right/wrong move&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;there are no hints left&lt;/em&gt; etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two &lt;em&gt;goroutines&lt;/em&gt;, one for &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/puzzl/blob/master/surface/surface.go#L406-L417&#34;&gt;handling the notification events&lt;/a&gt; and another for &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/puzzl/blob/master/surface/surface.go#L406-L417&#34;&gt;solving the game in background&lt;/a&gt;, both are non-blocking in nature to other routines like &lt;em&gt;user inputs&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;game display&lt;/em&gt; etc. A &lt;em&gt;channel&lt;/em&gt; named &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/puzzl/blob/master/notification/notification.go#L19&#34;&gt;Tunnel&lt;/a&gt; was the messenger for these &lt;em&gt;goroutines&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/architecture.jpg&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Asynchronous Gouroutines Architecture&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is like feeding each other. Best friends forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;game-interface&#34;&gt;Game Interface&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Box-drawing_character&#34;&gt;Box-drawing characters&lt;/a&gt;, the best old way to develop text based user interfaces. And thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/nsf/termbox-go&#34;&gt;termbox-go&lt;/a&gt;, an awesome library for such interface development in Golang.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;arxiv-submission&#34;&gt;arXiv submission&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I loved working on it so much that I even framed its development in shape of a research paper, sort of. It&amp;rsquo;s available on the arXiv digital library, here &lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/abs/1503.08345&#34;&gt;arxiv-1503.08345&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Implementing an intelligent version of the classical sliding-puzzle game for unix terminals using Golang&amp;rsquo;s concurrency primitives.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not in LaTeX, so the arXiv stamp is absent in PDF format there. They replied that they don&amp;rsquo;t have any technique yet to stamp other formats. I&amp;rsquo;ll probably port it in LaTeX one day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;reference&#34;&gt;Reference&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jstor.org/stable/pdf/2369492.pdf?acceptTC=true&#34;&gt;Notes on the 15 puzzle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://kevingong.com/Math/SixteenPuzzle.html&#34;&gt;Analysis of the Sixteen Puzzle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ai-php.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/AI8pzzle.jpg&#34;&gt;ai-php.com&lt;/a&gt; for the 8-puzzle game states image&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://captnemo.in/&#34;&gt;Abhay Rana&lt;/a&gt; for teaching me what &lt;em&gt;For What Joy&lt;/em&gt; is. #FWJ?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;behind-the-scene&#34;&gt;Behind the scene&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I framed all this story for you, the truth is something else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guess what? It&amp;rsquo;s my exam-time again that made me write this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The source code for &lt;em&gt;puzzl&lt;/em&gt; is on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/puzzl&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. Do whatever you want, just respect licensing and other respectful things.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Holy Aesthete : painting a virtual wall</title>
      <link>http://pravj.github.io/blog/virtual-wall/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pravj.github.io/blog/virtual-wall/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, it&amp;rsquo;s the day of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holi&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Holi&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, the festival of colors in India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, it was the end of our midterm exams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such Time. Much Rhyme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/wall.jpg&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Virtual Wall&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the last minutes, I decided to stop writing after matching an answer with the person sitting next to me. I was all set to run outside the hall and smell the &lt;em&gt;woot! no more exams left&lt;/em&gt; scent in the air.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have one strange habit of drawing random things in my notebook, ranging from literally anything to &lt;em&gt;K-nearest&lt;/em&gt; girls. All the drawings are terrible though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I started utilizing rest of the time by drawing in the backside of exam paper. After a little journey to some wonderland, I had this weird sounding thought in my mind, &lt;em&gt;to write something that simulates a painted wall.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then the exam ended, we left the hall, enjoyed the &lt;em&gt;Holi&lt;/em&gt; all day with batchmates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That &lt;em&gt;weird thought&lt;/em&gt; was still there in my mind, deep somewhere. I decided to give it a shout next morning. And you never need a &lt;em&gt;halcion&lt;/em&gt; after ~40 hours of &lt;em&gt;not sleeping&lt;/em&gt; and doing &lt;em&gt;not so successful&lt;/em&gt; attempt of &lt;em&gt;cram&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I started justifying that thought, picked up &lt;em&gt;golang&lt;/em&gt; for it and created a directory, &lt;em&gt;~/go/src/github/pravj/wall&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wait! let&amp;rsquo;s talk over. Have you ever painted a wall before?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well! I have. If not, you must have seen people doing it. &lt;em&gt;What happens when you start with the brush?&lt;/em&gt; Something like this picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/wall-paint.jpg&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Wall Paint&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here in the picture, the part painted by each color doesn&amp;rsquo;t have a specific shape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, in my attempt, I assumed that there exists a central rectangular shape in color block generated by each brush swipe. And the final block also contains some &lt;em&gt;noise&lt;/em&gt; around that rectangle, resulting in the final irregular shape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started with those rectangles, equally spaced with each other. The space was for the noise interference I was planning. Result was this, fix colored image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/first-stage.jpg&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;First Stage&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I added the &lt;em&gt;noise&lt;/em&gt; on each rectangle. For this, instead of fix sized rectangle. I added some random lengthy stripes around the block, colored same as the block. The result was this image, fixed color again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/second-stage.jpg&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Second Stage&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After applying random colors to each block, it generates image similar to the one given below. The ideal thing to do would be, coloring each block in a way that it&amp;rsquo;s different from its surrounding block color. Something like the classical &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Four_color_theorem&#34;&gt;Four Color Theorem&lt;/a&gt;, variant of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constraint_satisfaction_problem&#34;&gt;Constraint satisfaction problem&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/third-stage.jpg&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Third Stage&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in this case, the probability of the ideal case violation is &lt;em&gt;lilliputian&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Precisely, for a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cross&#34;&gt;slanted saltire(cross)&lt;/a&gt; shape divided in five squares, the probability of central square having same color as any surrounding square will be around 2 in 10 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/probability.png&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Probability&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let&amp;rsquo;s ignore it like a pigeon closing its eyes in front of a venerer cat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I was concerned about the equally spaced color blocks. Things were still not in the way I wanted them to be. It looked like there is a pattern inside. As systems having more entropy are more stable and &lt;em&gt;beautiful&lt;/em&gt;. I decided to put color blocks at random places in the image, result was this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/fourth-stage.jpg&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Fourth Stage&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After this all, the central rectangle that I have assumed for the structure, was clearly visible in the block. To conceal that, I formatted the block such that the &lt;em&gt;noise&lt;/em&gt; along the block-width depends on the index of the row in block matrix. Now, it was better than the last one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/final-stage.jpg&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Final Stage&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what I have thought about. A wall painted by some children in their tiffin time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may sound like a dumb thing to work on, it&amp;rsquo;s actually. It&amp;rsquo;s just a combination of some &lt;em&gt;for&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;if-else&lt;/em&gt; loops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is more than just dumb, now I feel relieved as I made it real what I have thought about, something like Aaron has said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;behind-the-scene&#34;&gt;Behind the scene&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;While doing this, I painted one of my room wall, &lt;em&gt;hypothetically&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You must have got the idea behind this post&amp;rsquo;s heading. &lt;em&gt;The Holi Fever&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Today, my room&amp;rsquo;s light is not working and I wrote this in the screen light.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source Code : &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/virtual-wall&#34;&gt;virtual-wall&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introducing Penticons : The Hash Game</title>
      <link>http://pravj.github.io/blog/penticons-the-hash-game/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pravj.github.io/blog/penticons-the-hash-game/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Jennifer Lawrence fan, huh? It was &lt;em&gt;The Hash Game&lt;/em&gt; by the way. Still in? Kewl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-s-the-buzz-all-about&#34;&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s the buzz all about?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, there is no buzz. This post is about development of &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/penticons&#34;&gt;Penticons&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;penticons-what&#34;&gt;Penticons. What?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember those &lt;a href=&#34;http://a0.twimg.com/sticky/default_profile_images/default_profile_6_normal.png&#34;&gt;egg shaped profile pictures&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter? They are automaticaly linked to your profile, when you forget to upload your custom profile picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Different services uses different default profile pictures. For example, Quora uses &lt;a href=&#34;http://qph.is.quoracdn.net/main-qimg-caf2e843c5e4c9dfec11bf60f9e82ccb?convert_to_webp=true&#34;&gt;this image&lt;/a&gt; of their co-founder Charlie Cheever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Internet&amp;rsquo;s language, these profile pictures are called &lt;em&gt;Avatars&lt;/em&gt;. They represents a particular user or object on the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we have seen, Quora provides a single image as the default avatar. What if, you want to distinguish between users on the basis of their &lt;em&gt;avatars&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This particular problem to recognize users or objects according to their &lt;em&gt;avatar&lt;/em&gt; images was the main force behind the invention of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Identicon&#34;&gt;Identicons&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An Identicon is a visual representation of a &lt;strong&gt;hash value&lt;/strong&gt;, uniquely* mapped to any object on the internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Penticons&lt;/em&gt; are just another implementation of identicons. But it tries to solve a key problem with available identicons. Let&amp;rsquo;s see how.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;hash-value-what&#34;&gt;Hash value. What?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s put this identicon thingy in the left and talk on something interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you know, How do they store your password in the Facebook? Obviously you do, but in case you don&amp;rsquo;t, let me confess something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have some guys sitting there, they remember all your passwords and match it to your input whenever you log in to the service. That simple it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facebook also keeps a &lt;em&gt;hashed&lt;/em&gt; version of your passwords, in case all those smart guys are on leave, they just &lt;em&gt;hash&lt;/em&gt; your input again to match with their stored value. They log you in, if both of the values are same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case you are thinking, why do they &lt;em&gt;hash&lt;/em&gt; your passwords? They do it to make sure that nobody really knows your passwords except those &lt;em&gt;smart and loyal&lt;/em&gt; guys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;hash-hash-what-the-hash&#34;&gt;Hash.. Hash.. What the Hash?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s fly back to the junior mathematics class and consider this tiny function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/function.png&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, if I ask, what is the value of x when the value of function is 0? You can answer this easily by solving this simple quadratic equation. The values will be 2 and 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if I change the function to a bit more horrible one. For example, take this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/hard-function.png&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feeling cold, huh? Well! you can still find the roots but with a bit more effort. One simple effort you can do is to &lt;em&gt;google&lt;/em&gt; this equation and you&amp;rsquo;ll find it on the very first result page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Hash Function&lt;/em&gt; we were talking about is one similar function that takes a value and returns the mapped value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in case of the &lt;em&gt;Cryptographic Hash Functions&lt;/em&gt;, it&amp;rsquo;s pretty hard to get back the &lt;em&gt;pre-image&lt;/em&gt; of a function value, somewhat like the second function above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, these &lt;em&gt;Hash Functions&lt;/em&gt; are supposed to be &lt;em&gt;injective&lt;/em&gt; in nature. Unlike the first function above, which has two roots 2 and 1. In reality they are not totally injetive, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MD5&#34;&gt;MD5&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SHA-1&#34;&gt;SHA-1&lt;/a&gt; are two such &lt;em&gt;Cryptographic Hash Functions&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;any-wrong-with-these-hash-functions&#34;&gt;Any wrong with these Hash Functions?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah! Let&amp;rsquo;s consider the MD5 hash function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It generates a 128 bit hash-value for any argument. In the text format, it&amp;rsquo;s written as a 32 digit hexadecimal number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, the word &amp;ldquo;alpha&amp;rdquo; results in, &lt;em&gt;2c1743a391305fbf367df8e4f069f9f9&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can you guess, what is the maximum possible hash count MD5 can generate?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/md5-count.png&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if you have more elements than this count to hash, MD5 would be producing similar hashes for all the extra elements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the case when MD5 is pure as hell, but it&amp;rsquo;s not actually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many reports showing cryptographic weakness of MD5. For example, consider &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mathstat.dal.ca/~selinger/md5collision/&#34;&gt;this report&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;why-penticons&#34;&gt;Why Penticons?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Penticons tries to solve one key problem with available identicons.&lt;/em&gt; Let me explain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are developed on top of the identicons that &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/blog/1586-identicons&#34;&gt;GitHub provides&lt;/a&gt;. There are &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/search?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;amp;q=identicon&#34;&gt;many other&lt;/a&gt; similar identicon implementations available on GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s take an inside on How these identicons works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They generates a 5x5 pixel sprites, where they choose to color some of the pixel and left rest pixels as blank, according to the hash of user&amp;rsquo;s handle. They also have a vertical axis of symmetry, so the identicon is similar from left to right. Finally they color non-blank pixels with a color.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, what is the maximum number of identicons generated this way?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suppose they are using 20 colors to fill in the non-blank pixels, they are &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/cupcake/sigil/blob/6bf9722f2ae82f58a0c7d48daeb40ec844b78eae/server.go#L20-L29&#34;&gt;not using&lt;/a&gt; this much colors, though. Then total possible identicon count will be :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/total-identicon.png&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, &lt;em&gt;Penticons&lt;/em&gt; uses &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/penticons/penticons.go/blob/master/utils/utils.go#L21-L25&#34;&gt;5 colors&lt;/a&gt; only, from GitHub&amp;rsquo;s contribution calendar. They also have a vertical axis of symmetry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But instead of using a fix color to fill in, it uses any one of the 5, according to the hash value. This way, total number of identicons will be the following.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/total-penticons.png&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which is way more than other implementations, so the rate of collision is also less here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;now-what&#34;&gt;Now what?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made an organization for &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/penticons&#34;&gt;Penticons&lt;/a&gt;; just to look cool, though. I think so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last night, I wrote the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/penticons/penticons.go&#34;&gt;golang implementation&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;em&gt;Penticons&lt;/em&gt;. My friend &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/nkman&#34;&gt;Nairitya&lt;/a&gt; will be writing some more very soon, at-least he promised me. Let&amp;rsquo;s see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Avatar&lt;/em&gt; for the organization is a penticon itself, of the word &amp;ldquo;Penticons&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/avatar.png&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Penticon Avatar for the word &#34;Penticons&#34;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open Source Presence Infographic of Indian Startups</title>
      <link>http://pravj.github.io/blog/open-source-presence-infographic/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pravj.github.io/blog/open-source-presence-infographic/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Technically speaking, organizations used in this report are no more only a &lt;em&gt;startup&lt;/em&gt; now, but I hope you people won&amp;rsquo;t mind this and aren&amp;rsquo;t gonna launch a drone on me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think, &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; is clear from the name itself, is it? Well! it should.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report tries to plot all the involved organizations on the Open-Source portal. It tries to tell that, in the race to achieve their goals, what different organizations are doing there, for/in the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s pretty biased though, because this report uses only one platform of the Open-Source community, GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This report doesn&amp;rsquo;t measure the success of involved organizations; it simply can&amp;rsquo;t. They all are doing good in their fields, that&amp;rsquo;s why they are here.&lt;/em&gt; :tophat:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;motive&#34;&gt;Motive&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it was almost mid of the December last year when I saw the &lt;a href=&#34;http://yourstory.com/2014/12/techie-tuesdays-amod-malviya-cto-flipkart/&#34;&gt;interview&lt;/a&gt; of Flipkart&amp;rsquo;s CTO &lt;em&gt;Amod Malviya&lt;/em&gt; in a YourStory article. I started reading that and kept reading till the end. At the end my reaction was, &lt;em&gt;wow! this man is awesome&lt;/em&gt; and he is indeed. I have seen many of his talks after reading that interview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That interview made a different impression on me. I liked his words where he was talking about building a top class internet infrastructure in India. I don&amp;rsquo;t know what you people think of Flipkart, Myntra etc. but what I think is that they are evolving continuously, at least in the technical aspect. That&amp;rsquo;s why they are in the marathon and Amazon itself is in the race with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, after a while I found myself on the GitHub organization of Flipkart and I was scrolling through their projects there. Then the idea of this report popped-up in my mind and here I&amp;rsquo;m, struggling with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;for-what-joy-is-there-a-need&#34;&gt;For What Joy? Is there a need?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The earth will keep rotating without this report but it&amp;rsquo;s kinda necessary for technical organizations to be a part of current Open-Source era. I mean as they say in the &lt;em&gt;Group Dynamics&lt;/em&gt;, If you&amp;rsquo;re part of a group then you learn for other members and they learn from you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you remember something named Facebook? Lets take an example from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe that you take PHP as &lt;em&gt;a language for the kids&lt;/em&gt; but keep in mind that &lt;em&gt;The Social Network&lt;/em&gt; was initially developed in that same PHP. But as they started growing and feeling glitch using it; seeing that the :santa: was not coming to help them, they attempted building something on their own. Finally today, we know the inventions as &lt;a href=&#34;http://hhvm.com/&#34;&gt;HHVM&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://hacklang.org/&#34;&gt;Hack language&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, the thing is &lt;em&gt;don&amp;rsquo;t wait for santa and build cool things that matters&lt;/em&gt;. Big organizations are already doing it, be it &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/facebook/hhvm&#34;&gt;hhvm&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/facebook/react&#34;&gt;react&lt;/a&gt; by Facebook or &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/twitter/typeahead.js&#34;&gt;typeahead.js&lt;/a&gt; by Twitter or &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/google/web-starter-kit&#34;&gt;web-starter-kit&lt;/a&gt; by Google and many more by others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;involved-organizations&#34;&gt;Involved Organizations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do believe that the organization selection part was a bit biased as I wanted to have my favorite organizations first on the list, like HackerEarth, Hasgeek, Housing, Flipkart, Wingify and Zomato etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was disappointing to see that Housing was not on the GitHub by that time and Zomato&amp;rsquo;s organization was having zero public activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I selected 15 startups, giving priority to my favorite ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cucumbertown.com/&#34;&gt;Cucumbertown&lt;/a&gt; - Follow great cooks, showcase your cooking, build a following&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://exotel.in/&#34;&gt;Exotel&lt;/a&gt; - Reliable Cloud Telephony System for your business&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flipkart.com/&#34;&gt;Flipkart&lt;/a&gt; - Online Shopping India&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://freshdesk.com/&#34;&gt;Freshdesk&lt;/a&gt; - Online customer support software and helpdesk solution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hackerearth.com/&#34;&gt;HackerEarth&lt;/a&gt; - Programming challenges and Developer jobs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://hasgeek.com/&#34;&gt;HasGeek&lt;/a&gt; - HasGeek organises events for geeks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.instamojo.com/v2/&#34;&gt;Instamojo&lt;/a&gt; - Easiest Way to Collect Payments Online&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.myntra.com/&#34;&gt;Myntra&lt;/a&gt; - Online Shopping India&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mysmartprice.com/&#34;&gt;MySmartPrice&lt;/a&gt; - Compare the best prices from online retailers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.practo.com/&#34;&gt;Practo&lt;/a&gt; - Find Best Doctors and Book Appointments Online&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.shephertz.com/&#34;&gt;ShepHertz&lt;/a&gt; - Complete Cloud Ecosystem for App/Game Developers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.urbanladder.com/&#34;&gt;Urban Ladder&lt;/a&gt; - Furniture Online Shopping Store&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://webengage.com/&#34;&gt;WebEngage&lt;/a&gt; - On-Site Customer Engagement Suite&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://wingify.com/&#34;&gt;Wingify&lt;/a&gt; - Website Optimization tools that simply work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.zomato.com/&#34;&gt;Zomato&lt;/a&gt; - Discover great places to eat around you&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a section here in this report, which uses last year&amp;rsquo;s GitHub activity of organizations, so I killed my idea of replacing Zomato by someone else as the year was gone and it was kinda tough to jump traditional API &lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.github.com/v3/repos/statistics/#participation&#34;&gt;bumper&lt;/a&gt; and collect data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said Zomato have zero public activity last year but it doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean they are not good, they are doing pretty good; aquiring it all, at a rate of hurricane wind speed and serving in cities more than you&amp;rsquo;ve ever been in your life. Maybe they are using some other platform, a local Git hosting or something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You better zoom-in the images or open them in a different tab.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;1-appearance-timeline-of-organizations&#34;&gt;1. Appearance Timeline of Organizations&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you know, when all of these organizations were found? Not sure?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/appearance-timeline.png&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Apperance Timeline&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This plot shows &lt;em&gt;relative appearance&lt;/em&gt; of selected organizations both in the public world as well as in the open-source world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Add legend text in the image.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t know that Myntra was founded a bit earlier than Flipkart, who &lt;a href=&#34;http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/tech/tech-news/Flipkart-acquires-Myntra/articleshow/35472797.cms&#34;&gt;aquired&lt;/a&gt; the older player recently.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Myntra and Flipkart came in existance before the GitHub itself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We can see a large gap between apperance on these two portals for Flipkart, Myntra and Zomato, Myntra being the slowest one to join.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some organizations like Instamojo, HackerEarth and HasGeek felt the need of time and took no significant time in this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well! in case if you&amp;rsquo;re thinking that this information is all chatter, let me present something interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go back and see the image carefully and you&amp;rsquo;ll notice something different from others for Cucumbertown and HasGeek.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes! the GitHub organizations for these two were created before their public launching itself. &lt;em&gt;Sounds interesting, right?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can&amp;rsquo;t say for Cucumbertown now but I can present a supporting theory to prove this for the HasGeek.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you guys remeber what was the first event that HasGeek organised? It was &lt;a href=&#34;http://wiki.hasgeek.in/DocType_HTML5&#34;&gt;DocType HTML5&lt;/a&gt;, you silly. The event was held on October, 2010 and HasGeek was pubilcally launched in December, 2010. You can fly to their GitHub account and check that they are developing &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/hasgeek/doctypehtml5&#34;&gt;hasgeek/doctypehtml5&lt;/a&gt; since then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe organising this event was the inspiration behind launching the HasGeek, I need to hear HasGeek founder &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/jackerhack&#34;&gt;Kiran&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s words on it, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;2-repository-status&#34;&gt;2. Repository Status&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we all know, repository is an important component of GitHub&amp;rsquo;s ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;2-1-public-repository-status&#34;&gt;2.1. Public Repository Status&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This section deals with no. of public repositories for each involved organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/repository-status.png&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Public Repository Count&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cloud services provider ShepHertz has maximum no. of public repositories there, mainly based on their &lt;em&gt;App42&lt;/em&gt; service stack. Flipkart and HasGeek also have significant no. of repositories, rest are the organizations are building their store gradually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No. of repositories on GitHub is not the right thing to measure about, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;2-2-stars-distribution&#34;&gt;2.2. Stars Distribution&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said, having more number of repositories doesn&amp;rsquo;t explicitly show your popularity. It&amp;rsquo;s not an old wars between states where king with more elephants was supposed to be the winner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But no. of stars on any GitHub repository can represent its vogue, &lt;em&gt;leave the case where they&amp;rsquo;re fake.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/stars-distribution.png&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Stars Distribution&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This graph represents the stars distribution on all the repositories of involved organizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Top 10 repositories according to no. of stars&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/wingify/please.js&#34;&gt;wingify/please.js&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#183; 211 &amp;#x2606;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/flipkart/hostdb&#34;&gt;flipkart/HostDB&lt;/a&gt; 190 &amp;#183; &amp;#x2606;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/myntra/MYNStickyFlowLayout&#34;&gt;myntra/MYNStickyFlowLayout&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#183; 133 &amp;#x2606;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/wingify/dom-comparator&#34;&gt;wingify/dom-comparator&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#183; 129 &amp;#x2606;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/hasgeek/lastuser&#34;&gt;hasgeek/lastuser&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#183; 113 &amp;#x2606;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/flipkart/phantom&#34;&gt;flipkart/phantom&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#183; 71 &amp;#x2606;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/hasgeek/hasjob&#34;&gt;hasgeek/hasjob&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#183; 70 &amp;#x2606;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/wingify/agentredrabbit&#34;&gt;wingify/agentredrabbit&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#183; 49 &amp;#x2606;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/wingify/lua-resty-rabbitmqstomp&#34;&gt;wingify/lua-resty-rabbitmqstomp&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#183; 45 &amp;#x2606;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/hackerearth/hackerearth.vim&#34;&gt;hackerearth/hackerearth.vim&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#183; 28 &amp;#x2606;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see Wingify, Flipkart and HasGeek are ruling the leader-board here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;2-3-relative-repository-attributes&#34;&gt;2.3. Relative Repository Attributes&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GitHub provides a feature named &lt;em&gt;fork&lt;/em&gt;, using that you can contribute to awesome projects of others like it was your own project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This section deals with attributes of repositories, counting which one of them is a &lt;em&gt;forked&lt;/em&gt; repository or which one is a &lt;em&gt;source&lt;/em&gt; repository.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/repository-attributes.png&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Repository Attributes&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This plot shows which organization have all their own &lt;em&gt;source&lt;/em&gt; repositories and which one is having &lt;em&gt;forked&lt;/em&gt; repositories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the development, I also calculated &lt;em&gt;active&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;inactive&lt;/em&gt; percentage of the &lt;em&gt;forked&lt;/em&gt; repositories. You can have a look &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/ospi/blob/master/Terms-and-conditions.md#section-7&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;em&gt;how this was calculated&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can see that HasGeek is doing fairly good here, having more share of &lt;em&gt;source&lt;/em&gt; repositories than &lt;em&gt;forked&lt;/em&gt;. A large portion of Flipkart and Freshdesk&amp;rsquo;s repositories are &lt;em&gt;inactive-forked&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;3-development-activity&#34;&gt;3. Development Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the involved organizations have somewhat for the community; projects born as solutions of some problems, projects born in some hackathons and so on. They&amp;rsquo;re gradually building things to enhance their infrastucture and market position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;3-1-repository-creation&#34;&gt;3.1. Repository Creation&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This section deals with creation of repositories of all the organizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/repository-creation.png&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Repository Creation Frequency&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can see that Urban Ladder, HasGeek and Exotel created their first repository almost at the same time of their GitHub organization creation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ShepHertz, HasGeek and Flipkart have kinda continuous repository creation events through out the timeline.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, if you think that it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;general knowledge&lt;/em&gt;, then let me show you the &lt;em&gt;magic&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go back and watch the image carefully and you&amp;rsquo;ll notice something weird for HackerEarth, are you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes! you see there, HackerEarth&amp;rsquo;s first repository was created before creation of their GitHub organization itself. &lt;em&gt;How is this even possible?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well! ladies and gentlemen, this is possible. Let me introduce a new theory in support of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HackerEarth&amp;rsquo;s oldest repository in the time series is &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/hackerearth/django-storages&#34;&gt;django-storages&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s the same repository, which is creating the confusion. But the fact is that this repository was initially &lt;em&gt;forked&lt;/em&gt; by HackerEarth&amp;rsquo;s Co-founder &lt;em&gt;Vivek&lt;/em&gt; on his GitHub &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/vivekp&#34;&gt;account&lt;/a&gt;. After the creation of a separate organization for HackerEarth, he merged that repository to the organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s why this repository&amp;rsquo;s creation date is before creation of their organization. Well! again, I need &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/vivekp&#34;&gt;Vivek&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s approval on this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;3-2-commit-activity&#34;&gt;3.2. Commit Activity&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This section deals with the commit activity of all the organizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/commit-activity-zoom.png&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Commit Activity&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This plot shows weekly commit activity of all the organizations. This is pretty much mixed-up though, but this was the only plot-type in my mind at the time, when I was developing this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see a relatively more development activity in the start of the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flipkart development team &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Flipkart/linux&#34;&gt;keeps&lt;/a&gt; a &lt;em&gt;fork&lt;/em&gt; of the &lt;em&gt;linux&lt;/em&gt;, it&amp;rsquo;s not a &lt;em&gt;forked repo&lt;/em&gt; though. I removed its activities because this was making the plot even more cluttered. You can check &lt;a href=&#34;{{site.url}}/assets/ospi/commit-activity.png&#34;&gt;that plot&lt;/a&gt; also, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;4-technology-stack&#34;&gt;4. Technology Stack&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Different organization are working in different fields of the technology; be it medical services, developer events, online shopping, food, cloud services, online payments etc., so they&amp;rsquo;re encountering different problems in the path and managing it accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;4-1-programming-languages-in-production&#34;&gt;4.1. Programming Languages in Production&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This section deals with use of different programming languages in the involved organizations&amp;rsquo;s infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/language-uses.png&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Language Used&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This plot uses colors from GitHub&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/linguist&#34;&gt;linguist&lt;/a&gt; for different programming languages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This helps us understanding tech-stack of all the organizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flipkart uses Java, HasGeek uses Python, Practo uses PHP and Freshdesk uses Ruby as their major programming language.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Organizations have started using &lt;em&gt;non-traditional&lt;/em&gt; languages like Lua, Erlang and Scala etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ShepHertz uses maximum no. of programming languages(14), in their quest to serve all &lt;em&gt;in-demand&lt;/em&gt; programming language in their service.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;4-2-field-of-work&#34;&gt;4.2. Field of work&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This section deals with the fields, different organization are working in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To calculate the results, I have used &lt;em&gt;repository names&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;their description&lt;/em&gt; here.
Actually I wanted to have relative sharing in fields of working of all the organizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, initially, my plan was to use &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Latent_Dirichlet_allocation&#34;&gt;Latent Dirichlet Allocation&lt;/a&gt; on the &lt;em&gt;repository-description-text&lt;/em&gt; corpus for &lt;em&gt;Topic Modeling&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where I had use &lt;em&gt;concatenated repository descriptions&lt;/em&gt; of organizations as a &lt;em&gt;document&lt;/em&gt; but then I droped this idea because of asymmetrical repository distribution. It was resulting in a corpus of 14 documents only (Zomato excluded).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can have a brief knowledge about LDA, &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.echen.me/2011/08/22/introduction-to-latent-dirichlet-allocation/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I changed the plan and moved towards &lt;em&gt;Naive Bayes Classifier&lt;/em&gt; and used word frequencies only.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can check the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/ospi/tree/master/classifier&#34;&gt;classifier&lt;/a&gt; topic results based on probability or frequency, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/ospi/blob/master/results/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, some of the topic results from Classifier for organizations are :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cucumbertown : &lt;em&gt;Django, Gearman, Email, Commit, Notifier&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exotel : &lt;em&gt;Audio, IVR, Music, SMS&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flipkart : &lt;em&gt;REST API&amp;rsquo;s, MySQL, lucence, Redis, HTTP proxy, load balancer&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Freshdesk : &lt;em&gt;Databases, Rails, API, Websockets, Socket.io, YUI, Resque&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HasGeek : &lt;em&gt;Workshop, Lastuser, App management, TV, Job, GitHub&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HackerEarth : &lt;em&gt;Django, API documentation and clients, extensions and editors&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Instamojo : &lt;em&gt;API clients, Wordpress, Frameworks, Huxley&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Myntra : &lt;em&gt;iOS, Cocoa, Android, ElasticSearch, Docker, Librato&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MySmartPrice : &lt;em&gt;Technology Blog, Gearman workers, Cookbook&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Practo : &lt;em&gt;OpenID, Flask, Sentry, Symfony, Raven, Mail clients, Messages&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ShepHertz : &lt;em&gt;App42, PaaS, SDK, API clients, MongoDB, MySQL, Redis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;WebEngage : &lt;em&gt;Message, API, Website, Speech&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wingify : &lt;em&gt;Angular.js, DOM, RabbitMQ, iOS, Data, Bootstrap, VWO&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we can see that Flipkart&amp;rsquo;s stack includes things related to distributed computing, Networking, Databases on the other hand Wingify&amp;rsquo;s stack includes things related to Frontend, Data, Networking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, this is it. Open Source Presence Infographic of Indian Startups. :octocat:.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re thinking that &lt;em&gt;santa&lt;/em&gt; helped me in all this; then you are wrong, my friend.
I was all alone everytime, thinking about it, collecting the data, managing R source files in Rstudio, writing Python for it and all that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re feeling that you can do &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; much more awesome than this.
&amp;gt; You can do whatever you want; It&amp;rsquo;s hosted on GitHub, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/ospi&#34;&gt;pravj/ospi&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open Source Presence Infograohic : &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/ospi/blob/master/Terms-and-conditions.md&#34;&gt;Terms and Conditions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The git-game Write-up</title>
      <link>http://pravj.github.io/blog/the-git-game-writeup/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pravj.github.io/blog/the-git-game-writeup/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Spoiler Alert&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should go and check this out, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/hgarc014/git-game&#34;&gt;git-game&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a nice little &lt;em&gt;complete-a-task-and-upgrade-level&lt;/em&gt; type of game layered on top of Git.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It is a terminal game designed to test your knowledge of git commands. Each level in the game is a task to perform on this repo. Once you perform that task, you will be given your next task. There are a total of ten levels, each one harder than last!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw the reference to this game floating around in my GitHub feed yesterday. The concept is awesome as there are already &lt;a href=&#34;http://pcottle.github.io/learnGitBranching/&#34;&gt;many&lt;/a&gt; online tutorial courses on the Internet that uses interactive &lt;em&gt;learning-with-doing&lt;/em&gt; methods for Git.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the repository, I started the adventure with cloning the repository using &lt;code&gt;git clone git@github.com:hgarc014/git-game.git&lt;/code&gt; command.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;default branch&lt;/em&gt; was &lt;em&gt;master&lt;/em&gt; and there were only two files in repository&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;working directory&lt;/em&gt;, README.md and LICENSE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started with the README.md file and &lt;code&gt;cat README.md&lt;/code&gt; revealed all its content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should always check the README.md file for your next clue!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your first task is to checkout the commit whose commit message is the answer to this question:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a programmer is born, what is the first thing he/she learns to say?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well! a programmer is also a boy/girl, so first thing they do is &lt;em&gt;cry&lt;/em&gt; but in the current context that thing will be &lt;em&gt;Hello, World!&lt;/em&gt; :grinning:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I had to find the commit whose commit message was &lt;em&gt;Hello World&lt;/em&gt;, so the command &lt;code&gt;git log --graph --online&lt;/code&gt; resulted this commit history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;* 25bfa08 added information for people that don&amp;rsquo;t know git&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*   27e9786 Merge pull request #6 from riqpe/master&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;|&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;| * 3893960 Corrected description of difficulty progression&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;|/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;* bc9641f updated README&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;* 9b9380b Hello World!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;* 8cafb7c Initial commit&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can you see the &lt;em&gt;Hello World! commit&lt;/em&gt; now? Yeah! we can represent it by HEAD~3.
As that commit is &lt;em&gt;directly at level 3&lt;/em&gt; or we can say &lt;em&gt;great-grandparent&lt;/em&gt; of the HEAD commit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So all I needed to do was the command &lt;code&gt;git checkout HEAD~3&lt;/code&gt;, doing so we&amp;rsquo;re now done with the first task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After completing the first task when the HEAD is at that particular commit, the README.md file was ready with its new task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;git-game&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;========&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hello World!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It looks like you have some knowledge about traversing commits!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, let&amp;rsquo;s get this party started!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to get to a branch whose name is the answer to this riddle:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a creature that is smaller than man, but many times more in number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In code, my appearance can be subtle and no matter where I am found, I am unwanted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What am I?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Easy Peasy? Yeah, the answer is &lt;em&gt;bug&lt;/em&gt; obviously, so lets fly to same &lt;em&gt;branch&lt;/em&gt; using the &lt;code&gt;git checkout bug&lt;/code&gt; command.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this &lt;em&gt;branch&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;working directory&lt;/em&gt; there were two extra files, &lt;em&gt;cool.cpp&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;remember&lt;/em&gt; and the README.md was saying that :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;git-game&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;========&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Congratulations, it looks like you found the &amp;ldquo;bug.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you work with other programmers on the same project, bugs are bound to appear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to create bugs is by changing code that you did not write without understanding what the code is doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes we like to blame others for introducing bugs in our code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think you can find out who introduced a bug into our file cool.cpp?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We think he had something to do with the development of git.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And from what we hear he also made a branch under his name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Checkout to that branch after you find out who the culprit is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It says that there is a bug in the file &lt;em&gt;cool.cpp&lt;/em&gt;, lets see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;#include &amp;lt;iostream&amp;gt;

using namespace std;

int main()
{
   string mesg = &amp;quot;Hello! Who are you?&amp;quot;;
   string input;
   cout &amp;lt;&amp;lt; mesg &amp;lt;&amp;lt; endl;
   cin &amp;gt;&amp;gt; input;
   cout &amp;lt;&amp;lt; &amp;quot;Loops are fun!&amp;quot; &amp;lt;&amp;lt; endl;
   while(1);
   string reply = &amp;quot;Well, &amp;quot; + input + &amp;quot;, we hope you are having fun with our git-game!&amp;quot;;
   cout &amp;lt;&amp;lt; reply &amp;lt;&amp;lt; endl;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah! there is one; the &lt;em&gt;while loop&lt;/em&gt; will refuse the program from terminating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, who did this? Well! that&amp;rsquo;s what we have to answer now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;git blame - Helps you finding who committed what.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Show what revision and author last modified each line of a file&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;git blame cool.cpp&lt;/code&gt; is here for our rescue. It says that :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;ce59bbfd (Henry Garcia      2014-12-08 18:22:35 -0800 10)    cin &amp;gt;&amp;gt; input;
3922a6d8 (LinusTorvalds2014 2014-12-09 12:37:10 -0800 11)    cout &amp;lt;&amp;lt; &amp;quot;Loops are fun!&amp;quot; &amp;lt;&amp;lt; endl;
3922a6d8 (LinusTorvalds2014 2014-12-09 12:37:10 -0800 12)    while(1);
ce59bbfd (Henry Garcia      2014-12-08 18:22:35 -0800 13)    string reply = &amp;quot;Well, &amp;quot; + input + &amp;quot;, ...
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Damn! someone with a similar name to the great &lt;em&gt;Linus Torvalds&lt;/em&gt; is the culprit, he wrote that buggy line in the file. OK, lets move to his &lt;em&gt;branch&lt;/em&gt; as the README says, using &lt;code&gt;git checkout LinusTorvalds2014&lt;/code&gt; command.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time the README.md file was not explicitly directing anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;git-game
========

Looks like you found the branch of the evil Mastermind.
Things may start to get a little more challenging...

The next clue you are looking for --
   is in a file you choose to ignore!
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was doing this I thought may be it&amp;rsquo;s pointing to that useless file named &lt;em&gt;remember&lt;/em&gt; which was back there in the branch &lt;em&gt;bug&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I &lt;em&gt;checked-out&lt;/em&gt; again to the branch &lt;em&gt;bug&lt;/em&gt; and tried to find any clue in the file &lt;em&gt;remember&lt;/em&gt;. Its content looked like RSA Public keys to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;cweJIY8GOo18Usi5ykA4nmhBR0h 6mMpyy4nFY71IhgjGGr0rkY3uE tVTo j5XlwgLZZ PpRK Pwbnd7Z4bpQWc6sU700xfLTI63FbD DsKCQbUKG KS02qfurxMJ3mHHD8f6VhFUmY2rPD NjznQ8mnQvlNwAR1QsLDK Zjl1kGbWQBeGoOBwVMfa790ATCNg fR OLPA0hi7OW N4jUN26mBIwQVhVtteDSDSr OVfhvUwb7ydODX7R2no xxTmrD5IFUXIB8dDhR lpSFaRcbF2up wrWA J2acmA28c2 NhE Bqj7ntV67GTHpVBSwO
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I gave up after scrolling through the lengthy &lt;em&gt;remember&lt;/em&gt; file and &lt;em&gt;checked-out&lt;/em&gt; again to the branch &lt;em&gt;LinusTorvalds2014&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a strange habit to use &lt;code&gt;ls -a&lt;/code&gt; instead of &lt;code&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt; to list content of a directory so I did it and Boy! there it was, hiding all this time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guess what? there was a file named &lt;em&gt;.gitignore&lt;/em&gt; and it said :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# welcome to the ignore file!!

# This file is hidden by default,
# but did you know you have some branches that aren&#39;t shown to you,
# when you check the list of branches?
#
# For your next clue...
# Which abstract data type tends to implement sets and maps??
# The answer is the same answer to this riddle:
#
#   I am both mother and father.
#   I am seldom still
#   yet I never wander.
#   I never birth nor nurse.
#
#   What am I?
#
# Afterwards... well, you
# know, checkout to the answer.

*.rem
a.out
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time the answer of riddle is &lt;em&gt;Tree&lt;/em&gt;, simple. Don&amp;rsquo;t you know? You can &lt;em&gt;google&lt;/em&gt; it any time, I did the same. :wink:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the next thing to do was, &lt;code&gt;git checkout tree&lt;/code&gt; and the README.md file there said :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;git-game
========

Welcome to the &amp;quot;tree&amp;quot; branch.
Looks like good ol&#39; Linus modified the &amp;quot;nextclue_input.cpp&amp;quot; file.
Normally, when ran with the shell script &amp;quot;outputclue.sh&amp;quot;, the &amp;quot;nextclue_input.cpp&amp;quot; file would give us the next hint.

Maybe, you should try running the shell script with the &amp;quot;nextclue_input.cpp&amp;quot; file and see what happens...

You can run the script by running the command &amp;quot;./outputclue.sh FILE&amp;quot; .
If you are on Windows, it&#39;s okey to use `git-bash` that is installed with [msysgit](https://msysgit.github.io/).
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On executing the shell script with the &lt;em&gt;nextclue_input.cpp&lt;/em&gt;, printed something on the STDOUT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Linus has been here...
I love messing with these amateur programmers!!
If you want some real fun, then you should try resolving a conflict between this branch (tree) and code4life.
I introduced a little bug that you should fix in the conflict. &amp;gt;:)
After you merge these 2 files you should run the shell script again!!

Good Luck!!!
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The file &lt;em&gt;outputclue.sh&lt;/em&gt; is a &lt;em&gt;bash&lt;/em&gt; source file and matches the &lt;em&gt;md5sum&lt;/em&gt; of each word in the &lt;em&gt;nextclue_input.cpp&lt;/em&gt; to a local &lt;em&gt;checksum&lt;/em&gt; variable named &lt;em&gt;bug&lt;/em&gt;.
It keeps asking to fix &lt;em&gt;merge conflicts&lt;/em&gt; until the word matching that checksum is present in the file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;#!/bin/bash
if [ -z $1 ]; then
  echo &amp;quot;well, someone didn&#39;t want to run the script with a file...&amp;quot;;
  exit;
fi

file=$1
bug=7c85d987a917c2a555d1391426978f05
mesg=&amp;quot;Linus has been here...\nI love messing with these amateur programmers!!\nIf you want some real fun, then you should try resolving a conflict between this branch (tree) and code4life.\nI introduced a little bug that you should fix in the conflict. &amp;gt;:)\nAfter you merge these 2 files you should run the shell script again!!\n\nGood Luck!!!&amp;quot;
merges=$(git log --format=%h --merges | head -1)
csum=&amp;quot;md5sum&amp;quot;
if [ $(echo &amp;quot;$OSTYPE&amp;quot; | grep darwin) ];then
    csum=&amp;quot;md5&amp;quot;
fi

if [ &amp;quot;$file&amp;quot; = &amp;quot;nextclue_input.cpp&amp;quot; ];then
  if [ ${merges} ]; then
    while read p; do
      for w in $p;do
        if [ `echo $w | $csum | awk &#39;{print $1}&#39;` = $bug ];then
          echo -e $mesg;
          exit;
        fi;
      done;
    done &amp;lt; $file ;
    echo -e &amp;quot;Well, congratulations!! You fixed my conflict!!\nIf you would like to continue, then you should checkout to the $(echo 90mP8ouQHsNe | tr -d &#39;0-9A-Z&#39;) branch!!\n&amp;quot; ;
   else
     echo -e $mesg;
     exit;
   fi;
else
  echo &amp;quot;Looks like you passed in the wrong file&amp;quot;;
fi
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw that the &lt;em&gt;nextclue_input.cpp&lt;/em&gt; file was having a line with an &lt;em&gt;infinite while loop&lt;/em&gt; and my guess was right, the &lt;em&gt;checksum&lt;/em&gt; variable matched the &lt;em&gt;md5sum&lt;/em&gt; of the term &lt;em&gt;while(1);&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So to fix the &lt;em&gt;merge conflict&lt;/em&gt;, I did &lt;code&gt;git merge code4life&lt;/code&gt; and removed the faulty line; It worked like a charm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Well, congratulations!! You fixed my conflict!!
If you would like to continue, then you should checkout to the mouse branch!!
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BTW! It was way more easy. As the answer branch was, mouse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ echo 90mP8ouQHsNe | tr -d &#39;0-9A-Z&#39;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I &lt;em&gt;checked-out&lt;/em&gt; to the branch &lt;em&gt;mouse&lt;/em&gt;, it said :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;nextclue_input.cpp: needs merge
error: you need to resolve your current index first
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But you can get away without merging by &lt;em&gt;stashing the changes&lt;/em&gt;, I did this with &lt;code&gt;git add nextclue_input.cpp &amp;amp;&amp;amp; git stash&lt;/code&gt;.
Now the README.md file in branch &lt;em&gt;mouse&lt;/em&gt; said :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;```&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;git-game&#34;&gt;git-game&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looks like you resolved your conflict and found our branch, congrats!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hmm&amp;hellip;it seems this branch has a file that was seen before in another branch.
Do you &amp;ldquo;remember&amp;rdquo; what it is?
I think this file has something to do with the next clue, but it seems to be very ugly looking.
Maybe if we compare the &amp;ldquo;diff&amp;rdquo;erences between this file and the file from before we&amp;rsquo;ll know where to go next&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;
Yeah! I do remember that the file *remember* was there in the branch *bug* as I wasted 10 minutes on it.

I did ```git diff mouse bug -- remember``` to see the difference between these two files accross branches and the difference in the files was this one line :

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-Sn The next clue is: YtrydjKsYqebDoI3h bTINUeV6 pTVY8jnK2re HRwwNy25Ps6 u0YChCo5Jtw N3xkH3G nx aGo6yQTW RVZMsf3xk tBL0sG9GAR HQbyGYdqs i6dx1fyIPGJVci
+Sn In a branch named: Henry YtrydjKsYqebDoI3h bTINUeV6 pTVY8jnK2re HRwwNy25Ps6 u0YChCo5Jtw N3xkH3G nx aGo6yQTW RVZMsf3xk tBL0sG9GAR HQbyGYdqs i6dx1fy&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;
So, the next *branch* to move was *Henry*, but ```git checkout Henry``` was a trap.

On *checking-out* it said, *You are in &#39;detached HEAD&#39; state*; means we were not in a *branch* but *tag*. The README.md file was saying the same.

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;git-game-1&#34;&gt;git-game&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome to my Tag!!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re looking for my branch then you have gone the wrong way!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do you checkout to a branch that has the same name as a tag???
Deal with the tag first!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;
The problem was that there was a *branch* with exactly same name as a tag, *Henry*.
So I *renamed* the *tag*, because *who knows when you&#39;re gonna need something?*

```git tag Henry-v0.1 Henry &amp;amp;&amp;amp; git tag -d Henry``` made a new tag pointing to old&#39;s commit and deleted the old one.

Now after *checking-out* to the branch *Henry*, the README said :

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;git-game-2&#34;&gt;git-game&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome!! It looks like you made it to my Branch!!!
Generally you want to refrain from making tags the same name as branches, unless you have a good reason.
The tag is more like the stable release.
While the branch is more like the in progress feature, which will be added soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;re almost done!! Excited?? Hope you are! You have one more thing to do!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now its time to update the master branch, updating is really useful when you fork a repository and your forked repo starts to get behind on commits. The repository to update from is: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/drami025/git-game.git&#34;&gt;https://github.com/drami025/git-game.git&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t cheat!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;
So, according to the task, to update the *master branch* I *checked-out* to it.

With ```git remote add updater git@github.com:drami025/git-game.git``` command, I added the new *remote* to update from, as the README.md said.

Then a simple ```git pull updater master``` did rest of the work and the *master branch* was equal with the new *remote*, all updated. \o/.

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;git-game-finish-line&#34;&gt;Git Game Finish Line&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;if-you-did-not-fork-this-repository-from-the-terminal-then-we-are-disappointed-in-you&#34;&gt;If you did not fork this repository from the terminal, then we are disappointed in you!!&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, if you did, then great Job!!
You completed our Git Game!
```&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have also implemented an &lt;a href=&#34;http://openbadges.org/&#34;&gt;Open-Badge&lt;/a&gt; for this, I got one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, it&amp;rsquo;s complete. And this Write-up too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m feeling pain in my fingers now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;behind-the-scene&#34;&gt;Behind the scene :&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each level was somewhat harder than the previous one but overall it wasn&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yeah! I completed all tasks &lt;em&gt;twice&lt;/em&gt;, the extra one while writing this Write-up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It took me almost 30 minutes to complete all tasks but 2 hours to write this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Today, it&amp;rsquo;s an awesome sunny, winter day here. :sunny:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Post-mortem of an Internet Accident</title>
      <link>http://pravj.github.io/blog/post-mortem-of-an-internet-accident/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pravj.github.io/blog/post-mortem-of-an-internet-accident/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Hi scout, thanks for visiting this node of the Holy Internet Graph; Before the combination &lt;em&gt;Internet Accident&lt;/em&gt; confuse you, let me decode its meaning in the context of this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Encounter with something on an edge node of the Holy Internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this post is all about my attempt to solve a question, I saw on &lt;em&gt;Quora&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.quora.com/What-good-known-project-on-GitHub-uses-the-largest-number-of-programming-languages&#34;&gt;What good known projects on GitHub uses the largest number of programming languages?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I think that my answer is 98.76% correct, respecting the &lt;em&gt;No-Zero-Redundancy&lt;/em&gt; law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw this question while jumping between my chrome tabs when I was struggling with old drafts of my blog.
I clicked the link to give it a separate tab; &lt;em&gt;even questions have self respect&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I stumbled upon it as I saw that the question had a topic named &lt;em&gt;GitHub&lt;/em&gt; also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, to answer this, all I had to do was to find a repository which uses highest number of programming languages in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wait, the question also says a &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;good known project&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;.
Now that&amp;rsquo;s a plot twist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;GitHub&lt;/em&gt; provides an excellent &lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.github.com/v3/&#34;&gt;REST API&lt;/a&gt;, so excellent that it powers some awesome services also, like the &lt;a href=&#34;https://gitter.im&#34;&gt;Gitter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, to look for languages statistics of a repository you need the names of the repository and its owner. Then you can check a repo&amp;rsquo;s languages statistics using.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://api.github.com/repos/{owner}/{repo}/languages&#34;&gt;https://api.github.com/repos/{owner}/{repo}/languages&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;As far as a I know, there is not any way to do a reverse lookup, where you just provide number of programming languages and it gives you all the associated repositories.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I thought, lets give up on it and enjoy the coffee, &lt;em&gt;I had one on my desk&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I closed the question tab and started enjoying the coffee but then I opened it again because I felt that there may be a chance, if I use the &lt;em&gt;GitHub Archive&lt;/em&gt; project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GitHub Archive is a project to record the public GitHub timeline, archive it, and make it easily accessible for further analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This shift in plan was also not enough as &lt;em&gt;GitHub Archive&lt;/em&gt; gives only the major programming language for a project.
Now it was the time to shift to coffee &lt;em&gt;full time&lt;/em&gt; but &lt;em&gt;Nope! I had another idea&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea was to collect &lt;em&gt;good and known&lt;/em&gt; projects of &lt;em&gt;GitHub&lt;/em&gt; and rank them according to no. of programming languages in them. This sounds like &lt;em&gt;Brute Force&lt;/em&gt; but it was the only way left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I headed towards the &lt;em&gt;GitHub API&lt;/em&gt; for it but found that they gives you the first 1000 search results only.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I moved to &lt;em&gt;GitHub Archive&lt;/em&gt; finally and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/Post-mortem/blob/master/bigquery.sql&#34;&gt;downloaded a .csv file&lt;/a&gt; of all the repositories with greater than equal to 500 stars. Now, I think it covers most of your &lt;em&gt;good and known projects&lt;/em&gt;, happy now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I &lt;em&gt;Vimed&lt;/em&gt; the .csv file and found that some URLs were missing the owner&amp;rsquo;s name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/vim-screenshot.png&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Vim Screenshot&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;:g/https:\/\/github.com\/\//d&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I removed all the corrupted lines using this command.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re thinking that by removing lines, we won&amp;rsquo;t consider these repositories then take a deep breath and don&amp;rsquo;t think so, we will consider them, keep reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I wrote a &lt;em&gt;Python module&lt;/em&gt; to interact with the &lt;em&gt;GitHub API&lt;/em&gt;, named it &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/Post-mortem/blob/master/postman.py&#34;&gt;postman&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.
The &lt;em&gt;postman&lt;/em&gt; uses &lt;em&gt;Authentication Token&lt;/em&gt; from &lt;em&gt;GitHub&lt;/em&gt; to prevent the &lt;em&gt;rate-limiting&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t know how much did &lt;em&gt;postman&lt;/em&gt; take in its task as I was attending my classes then.
But when I came back from class in the evening, I saw that &lt;em&gt;postman&lt;/em&gt; was done with the task. &lt;em&gt;Wow, an obedient postman&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Right now if you search in GitHub for repositories having 500 or more stars, you will see around 7,200 results. So we have been doing this right so far as GitHub Archive &lt;a href=&#34;http://git.io/78eKDg&#34;&gt;don&amp;rsquo;t have&lt;/a&gt; all the data&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once all the data is available, it&amp;rsquo;s time to &lt;em&gt;rock &amp;lsquo;n&amp;rsquo; roll&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rstudio.com&#34;&gt;Rstudio&lt;/a&gt; is always there to help us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plotting the stars and languages distribution over all the repositories, we get this graph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/stars-and-languages.png&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Stars and Language distribution&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see that most of our good and known projects are in the bottom-left corner. Almost 90% of our repositories have less than 20,000 stars and 20 languages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is only one repository with more than 40,000 stars, which is the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/twbs/bootstrap&#34;&gt;twbs/bootstrap&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, let&amp;rsquo;s come to the question again. I think ordering repositories according to their no. of programming languages will work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Top 25 projects by their no. of programming languages&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/leachim6/hello-world&#34;&gt;leachim6/hello-world&lt;/a&gt;, languages : 82&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ajaxorg/ace&#34;&gt;ajaxorg/ace&lt;/a&gt;, languages : 58&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ajaxorg/ace-builds&#34;&gt;ajaxorg/ace-builds&lt;/a&gt;, languages : 58&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/freebsd/freebsd&#34;&gt;RMerl/asuswrt-merlin&lt;/a&gt;, languages : 57&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/freebsd/freebsd&#34;&gt;freebsd/freebsd&lt;/a&gt;, languages : 39&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/geany/geany&#34;&gt;geany/geany&lt;/a&gt;, languages : 36&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/xbmc/xbmc&#34;&gt;xbmc/xbmc&lt;/a&gt;, languages : 30&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dspinellis/unix-history-repo&#34;&gt;dspinellis/unix-history-repo&lt;/a&gt;, languages : 30&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/TechEmpower/FrameworkBenchmarks&#34;&gt;TechEmpower/FrameworkBenchmarks&lt;/a&gt;, languages : 28&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/imatix/zguide&#34;&gt;imatix/zguide&lt;/a&gt;, languages : 28&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/apache/thrift&#34;&gt;apache/thrift&lt;/a&gt;, languages : 27&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/msysgit/msysgit&#34;&gt;msysgit/msysgit&lt;/a&gt;, languages : 27&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/kennyledet/Algorithm-Implementations&#34;&gt;kennyledet/Algorithm-Implementations&lt;/a&gt;, languages : 27&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/flycheck/flycheck&#34;&gt;flycheck/flycheck&lt;/a&gt;, languages : 27&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/aichallenge/aichallenge&#34;&gt;aichallenge/aichallenge&lt;/a&gt;, languages : 27&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/triAGENS/ArangoDB&#34;&gt;triAGENS/ArangoDB&lt;/a&gt;, languages : 26&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/offensive-security/exploit-database&#34;&gt;offensive-security/exploit-database&lt;/a&gt;, languages : 25&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/JuliaLang/julia&#34;&gt;JuliaLang/julia&lt;/a&gt;, languages : 23&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/JetBrains/intellij-community&#34;&gt;JetBrains/intellij-community&lt;/a&gt;, languages : 23&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/facebook/pfff&#34;&gt;facebook/pfff&lt;/a&gt;, languages : 23&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ornicar/lila&#34;&gt;ornicar/lila&lt;/a&gt;, languages : 23&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/WebKit/webkit&#34;&gt;WebKit/webkit&lt;/a&gt;, languages : 22&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ariya/phantomjs&#34;&gt;ariya/phantomjs&lt;/a&gt;, languages : 21&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ruby/ruby&#34;&gt;ruby/ruby&lt;/a&gt;, languages : 21&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/coolwanglu/vim.js&#34;&gt;coolwanglu/vim.js&lt;/a&gt;, languages : 21&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, is that all? &lt;em&gt;Not at all! We have a lot to talk about my friend.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lets talk about something interesting I found in the data there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-there-were-382-repositories-without-any-programming-language&#34;&gt;1. There were 382 repositories without any programming language.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most of them are documentations, list of resources for a field.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For example &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/vhf/free-programming-books&#34;&gt;vhf/free-programming-books&lt;/a&gt;, List of free learning resources.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/zero-language-repository.png&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Zero Language Repositories&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Subject to the detection of language by GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Along with the required dataset, I was also collecting the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/Post-mortem/blob/master/log/postman.log&#34;&gt;logs&lt;/a&gt; data.
So, there is something more interesting.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-the-log-file-shows-error-status-404-in-some-lines&#34;&gt;2. The log file shows &amp;lsquo;ERROR : status 404&amp;rsquo; in some lines.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are 214 such lines, it means these projects have shifted their owners as it&amp;rsquo;s unusual to delete such popular repository.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They have evolved to much larger projects and have their own organizations now. For example the projects &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/homebrew/homebrew&#34;&gt;Homebrew&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/docker/docker&#34;&gt;Docker&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll&#34;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;, earlier they were &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mxcl/homebrew&#34;&gt;mxcl/homebrew&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dotcloud/docker&#34;&gt;dotcloud/docker&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll&#34;&gt;mojombo/jekyll&lt;/a&gt; respectively.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The maximum-star-holder-and-ultra-awesome project &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/twbs/bootstrap&#34;&gt;twbs/bootstrap&lt;/a&gt; was earlier at &lt;em&gt;Twitter&lt;/em&gt; by the address, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/twitter/bootstrap&#34;&gt;twitter/bootstrap&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The one-and-only TJ Holowaychuk have changed his username from &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/visionmedia&#34;&gt;visionmedia&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/tj&#34;&gt;tj&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-the-log-file-shows-error-status-403-in-some-lines&#34;&gt;3. The log file shows &amp;lsquo;ERROR : status 403&amp;rsquo; in some lines.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now this is weird, as status 403 denotes the Forbidden state. But underlying secrets are much more awesome here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There were two repositories, disabled due to a DMCA takedown notice.

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/popcorn-official/popcorn-app&#34;&gt;popcorn-official/popcorn-app&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Bukkit/CraftBukkit&#34;&gt;Bukkit/CraftBukkit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There was one repositories which is disabled by GitHub staff.

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mandatoryprogrammer/Octodog_Invasion&#34;&gt;mandatoryprogrammer/Octodog_Invasion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There was one repository which is deleted.

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/NULLPointerDz/test&#34;&gt;NULLPointerDz/test&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t know how but this repository had more than 500 stars once.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The code for this report is on GitHub, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/Post-mortem&#34;&gt;pravj/Post-mortem&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you feel that you can do more after going through this post-mortem report, you are welcome to show your medical skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>geopattern : going on the Go path</title>
      <link>http://pravj.github.io/blog/going-on-the-go-path/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pravj.github.io/blog/going-on-the-go-path/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should have a look at &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/geopattern&#34;&gt;geopattern&lt;/a&gt;, if you haven&amp;rsquo;t yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-s-the-buzz-all-about&#34;&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s the buzz all about?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog post is about development of &lt;em&gt;geopattern&lt;/em&gt; library in &lt;em&gt;golang&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do you think about this my favorite colored &lt;em&gt;concentric circle&lt;/em&gt; pattern?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/concentric-circle.png&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Concentric Circle Pattern&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;geopattern-what&#34;&gt;geopattern. What?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Umm, actually I don&amp;rsquo;t know exactly why the name is &lt;em&gt;geopattern&lt;/em&gt; but I know what it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a &lt;em&gt;golang&lt;/em&gt; library that generates pretty image patterns. It comes with awesome pattern types like nested squares, tessellation, concentric circles, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/geopattern#available-pattern&#34;&gt;13 more&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now if you are thinking, why I don&amp;rsquo;t know the reason behind its naming. It&amp;rsquo;s because &lt;em&gt;geopattern&lt;/em&gt; is actually the golang port of &lt;em&gt;my friend and GitHubber&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/jasonlong&#34;&gt;Jason Long&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/jasonlong&#34;&gt;GeoPattern&lt;/a&gt; Ruby library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jason&lt;/em&gt; created the original Ruby library to power GitHub&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://guides.github.com/&#34;&gt;Guides&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/explore&#34;&gt;Explore&lt;/a&gt; sections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;another-geopattern-why&#34;&gt;Another geopattern. Why?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see the original &lt;em&gt;geopattern&lt;/em&gt; is being used at GitHub itself. &lt;em&gt;What else do you want, huh?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many other &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/jasonlong/geopattern#ports&#34;&gt;implemetations&lt;/a&gt; in different programming languages, trying to help users of each language choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this was not the real force for me to develop one more in golang.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before &lt;em&gt;geopattern&lt;/em&gt;, the last thing I worked on was &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/Doga&#34;&gt;Doga: HTTP log monitoring console for Humans&lt;/a&gt;. I really loved developing it and still love to just watch it working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason behind this special attraction is that :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It helped me landing a summer internship at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.datadoghq.com/&#34;&gt;Datadog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is written in Python. &lt;strong&gt;&amp;lt;3&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I started writing blog for an old project &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/teamwork&#34;&gt;teamwork&lt;/a&gt;, just for the sake of adding an entry to my archives but it&amp;rsquo;s still in drafts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried many things to kill my time :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;watched too much movies, more than too much &lt;em&gt;Animation movies&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tried to read one seventh of the entire internet; I just missed it, though.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;collected some best music and shaped it in a playlist named &lt;em&gt;confusion&lt;/em&gt; on Muzi, so was I.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;managed to complete reading one entire research paper, &lt;em&gt;first time \o/.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;attempted watching Coursera content for two courses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tried to work on something new but got stuck somewhere and paused the work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;managed to contribute to term2048, &lt;em&gt;only one right thing.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short I was doing everything but there was no sign of satisfaction; &lt;em&gt;getting philosophical, lol.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s why I decided to write something. And here comes the &lt;em&gt;geopattern.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;golang-why&#34;&gt;Golang. Why?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please don&amp;rsquo;t kill me, if you use &amp;lsquo;go&amp;rsquo; more than &amp;lsquo;golang&amp;rsquo;. I&amp;rsquo;m just being formal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since this summer I was collecting talks, blogs and other sources etc. about use of different programming languages in the wild. I hope someday I&amp;rsquo;ll be able to convert that all in something readable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Golang was on my list ever since.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have seen many awesome products shifting their infrastructure from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.spacemonkey.com/blog/posts/go-space-monkey&#34;&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.quora.com/Why-did-Koding-switch-from-Node-js-to-Go&#34;&gt;Node.js&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;em&gt;golang&lt;/em&gt;. Even Dropbox &lt;a href=&#34;https://tech.dropbox.com/2014/07/open-sourcing-our-go-libraries/&#34;&gt;migrated&lt;/a&gt; part of their code stack to golang from Python. Also I have read the &lt;em&gt;TJ holowaychuk&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/code-adventures/farewell-node-js-4ba9e7f3e52b&#34;&gt;praising&lt;/a&gt; golang.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this made me to take a walk in the &lt;em&gt;golang&lt;/em&gt; land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;learning-golang-developing-geopattern&#34;&gt;Learning Golang. Developing geopattern.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In starting I spend two evenings reading about formal language convention stuff on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.golang-book.com/&#34;&gt;Golang-Book&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After playing for a while in my &lt;em&gt;~/projects/learn.go/&lt;/em&gt; directory, I started working on &lt;em&gt;geopattern&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love to read source code of every readable thing in any language except assembly, &lt;em&gt;as far as I can understand it&lt;/em&gt;. So I started reading source code of original &lt;em&gt;library&lt;/em&gt; and it was fun. The most helpful thing was Jason&amp;rsquo;s blog &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@jasonlong/generating-visual-designs-with-code-62e59c4881ca&#34;&gt;Generating visual designs with code&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In starting I was having problems that I even googled &lt;em&gt;go sucks&lt;/em&gt;. Because I found that &lt;em&gt;golang&lt;/em&gt; is a bit more verbose language. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t have some generic things so you have to write some work around like absense of optional arguments in functions and a better way to manage classes and stay object oriented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the more I worked with it I found that I&amp;rsquo;m more aware about what I&amp;rsquo;m writing, debugging is hell lot easy and what not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things that helped me from not giving up, are :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://gobyexample.com/&#34;&gt;Go by Example&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://jordanorelli.com/post/32665860244/how-to-use-interfaces-in-go&#34;&gt;How to use interfaces in Go&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.golang.org/godoc-documenting-go-code&#34;&gt;Godoc: documenting Go code&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And the &lt;em&gt;Holy Internet&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mailed Jason asking permission to port it and some other stuff related to licensing. His reply was positive. &lt;em&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s the ideal way you port something.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I called an astrologer for the right time to post about &lt;em&gt;geopattern&lt;/em&gt; on &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=8520961&#34;&gt;Hacker News&lt;/a&gt; and Holy, mother of bull!, He was perfect. It went to 2nd rank on the front page. #ThanksHN \o/.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All this happened a bit fast. In a week or so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;now-what&#34;&gt;Now What?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hated and then loved working with &lt;em&gt;golang; still loving&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, people are using &lt;em&gt;golang&lt;/em&gt; to speed up their projects and scale them upto higher levels. So now I wish to understand more about it. I haven&amp;rsquo;t smoked &lt;em&gt;golang&amp;rsquo;s concurrency primitives - Go routines and Channels yet&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was awesome to see &lt;em&gt;geopattern&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/jasonlong/status/527465160253132803&#34;&gt;leading&lt;/a&gt; GitHub&amp;rsquo;s trending repositories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have noticed that I&amp;rsquo;m not good in managing my past works like some inspiring people do in the GitHub community. It&amp;rsquo;s mainly because I move myself to some other stuff &lt;em&gt;totally&lt;/em&gt; and don&amp;rsquo;t pay much attention to older ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll try to work on this and learn more things about &lt;em&gt;golang&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to answer the question I asked in the start, you can use the &lt;em&gt;Internet of things&lt;/em&gt; to catch me. \o/.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>termping : &lt;3 &#43; Node.js &#43; Streams &#43; CoffeeScript</title>
      <link>http://pravj.github.io/blog/termping/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pravj.github.io/blog/termping/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should have a look at &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/termping.git&#34;&gt;termping&lt;/a&gt;, if you haven&amp;rsquo;t yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-s-the-fuss-about&#34;&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s the fuss about&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Blog is all about development of a game(kind of) &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/termping.git&#34;&gt;termping&lt;/a&gt;, which is a prototype of one of the oldest video game &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pong&#34;&gt;Pong&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this prototype runs in your system&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Computer_terminal&#34;&gt;terminal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/termping.gif&#34;&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;termping in action&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;emergence&#34;&gt;Emergence&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing that I just feel, I am getting good at is
&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;reading and understanding other people&amp;rsquo;s code&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;&amp;#35;notprasingmyself&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this summer I have explored unlimited repository out there on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. some for solving any kind of issues I was facing in using them or some for just sake of learning anything new, be it any new language(Ruby) or a new field(Vim) for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One interesting recap is that I was working on a project for my team(&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/sdslabs&#34;&gt;SDSLabs&lt;/a&gt;) and I was using a ruby library as HTTP client, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rest-client/rest-client&#34;&gt;Rest-Client&lt;/a&gt;. I started facing issue(obviously) as I was new to Ruby. So I started reading code of Rest-Client just to take a look that what are the ingredients and their quantity in this library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;finally I completed Rest-Client with a better understanding that solved all my issues with it and gave me introduction to a new field, which is :
&amp;gt; How does HTTP and REST clients works&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also while learning about the large world of &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/dotfiles/tree/learning/vim&#34;&gt;Vim&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, I started developing on a rough idea in my mind. which was to develop a Pong like game, playable in Vim editor itself. I tried it, under the name of &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/vingvong&#34;&gt;vingvong.&lt;/a&gt;. But I was unable to complete it because Vim does not support Asynchronous subprocesses, so I stopped the development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;May be you have any other way of implementing same or I&amp;rsquo;m wrong somewhere. If so, please let &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hackpravj&#34;&gt;me&lt;/a&gt; know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the same mission, one day I was going through project &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/visionmedia/nshell&#34;&gt;nshell&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;em&gt;one and only&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/visionmedia&#34;&gt;visionmedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. I selected this repository because I recently developed an interest in &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/dotfiles&#34;&gt;bash, shells and dotfiles management&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw, he was using &lt;a href=&#34;http://nodejs.org/docs/latest/api/stream.html#stream_stream&#34;&gt;Stream&lt;/a&gt; in nshell development. I googled about streams and found many resources, this includes &lt;a href=&#34;http://nodejs.org/docs/latest/api/stream.html&#34;&gt;official stream docs&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/substack/stream-handbook&#34;&gt;stream-handbook&lt;/a&gt; and many others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before that day, I have seen many people starring the &lt;em&gt;stream-handbook&lt;/em&gt; in my GitHub feed. But I was like &lt;em&gt;this thing does not belongs to me, right now&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that day I opened &lt;em&gt;stream-handbook&lt;/em&gt; with a motive to learn something. I started reading it and found that &lt;em&gt;Streams&lt;/em&gt; is a nice topic to learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suddenly my mind searched something from it&amp;rsquo;s index and showed me result in form of an idea. It was :
&amp;gt; Why don&amp;rsquo;t you just restart that Pingpong thing with this Stream ?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s all I wanted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;development&#34;&gt;Development&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;when I started thinking about Developing, shaping it as a &lt;strong&gt;Node Module&lt;/strong&gt; was the only and right option. I knew already that writing a Node Module in &lt;strong&gt;CoffeeScript&lt;/strong&gt; is both fancy(for world) and easy(for me).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was another reason for Choosing CoffeeScript, my experience in CoffeeScript was only limited to write &lt;a href=&#34;https://gist.github.com/pravj/2f500607d0aa1bae26a2&#34;&gt;some&lt;/a&gt; hubot scripts for customizing internal communication at &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/sdslabs&#34;&gt;SDSLabs.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was a cool opportunity to learn and do more things in CoffeeScript, so finally I was like :
&amp;gt; OK, lets move with CoffeeScript.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One coolest thing is that for CoffeeScript, I have only used &lt;a href=&#34;http://arcturo.github.io/library/coffeescript/&#34;&gt;The Little Book on CoffeeScript&lt;/a&gt;, no StackOverflow here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current version of &lt;strong&gt;termping&lt;/strong&gt; is open-sourced at &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/termping&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, feel free to contribute to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I&amp;rsquo;ll try to explain Source Code of &lt;strong&gt;termping.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the current file structure of the repository, once you browse it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;.
|__.npmignore
|__src
| |__objects.coffee
| |__game.coffee
| |__movement.coffee
| |__status.coffee
| |__source.coffee
|__Cakefile
|__bin
| |__termping
|__package.json
|__.gitignore
|__README.md
|__docs
| |__termping.gif
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PS : this tree structure is generated from &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/dotfiles/blob/learning/bin/treegen&#34;&gt;treegen&lt;/a&gt;, my own attempt as the alternative of the great &lt;code&gt;tree&lt;/code&gt; command.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;you can see, main things are inside &lt;code&gt;/src&lt;/code&gt; directory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;1-objects-coffee&#34;&gt;1. objects.coffee&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Object class keeps the game objects, including &lt;em&gt;ball&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;paddle&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;data&lt;/em&gt; to be rendered on screen. It also helps to populate the data initially according to terminal size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;2-game-coffee&#34;&gt;2. game.coffee&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Game class combines all available things at one place and makes it possible to play the game. It also invoke things in other classes on some particular events like &lt;em&gt;left&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;SpaceBar&lt;/em&gt; key press, that enable pause/resume or movement of paddle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;3-movement-coffee&#34;&gt;3. movement.coffee&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Movement class handles all movement related things. Ex. moving of user&amp;rsquo;s paddle, movement of ball, movement of computer&amp;rsquo;s paddle and one most useful thing &lt;em&gt;Collision Detection&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;4-status-coffee&#34;&gt;4. status.coffee&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;status.coffee carries all variable and their values that different classes use throughout the game. which includes, velocity of ball, paddle positions, ball positions, state of game etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;5-source-coffee&#34;&gt;5. source.coffee&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Source class is leading character in the movie. This is the place where all that Stream thing shows the magic. What it does is to &lt;strong&gt;pipe&lt;/strong&gt; the data to the &lt;strong&gt;stdout&lt;/strong&gt; that is to be rendered on screen. That&amp;rsquo;s why I named it as Source. Other classes just work together and periodically update the data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;learning&#34;&gt;Learning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;finally the thing is that, was this all worth doing ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answer is : &lt;strong&gt;Obviously, Yes. It&amp;rsquo;s always good to be pragmatic.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now I feel as good with &lt;strong&gt;CoffeeScript&lt;/strong&gt; as I feel with my love, &lt;strong&gt;Python&lt;/strong&gt;.

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;as the Book says, CoffeeScript is a little language, but it&amp;rsquo;s pretty cool one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally I have a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.npmjs.org/package/termping&#34;&gt;NPM Module&lt;/a&gt; under my name \m/.

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have completed things in form of NPM modules 2-3 times but never published them, because I developed them for internal/local use only.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I continued working on it, because I just wanted to complete that un-complete &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/vingvong&#34;&gt;vingvong&lt;/a&gt; thing.

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally now, the revenge has been taken, &lt;strong&gt;Yo&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It was the motive to complete it, that&amp;rsquo;s why I have added that ♥ in starting, instead of adding it in last.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;extra-learning&#34;&gt;Extra Learning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Extra learning just means, things that I explored while developing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;termping&lt;/strong&gt; is entirely developed in &lt;strong&gt;Vim&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;you can smell it&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Git&lt;/strong&gt; repo in &lt;strong&gt;termping&lt;/strong&gt; uses a pattern in it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/termping/commits/master&#34;&gt;commit messages&lt;/a&gt;.

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Commit messages uses a Prefix with them, which is&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;add&lt;/strong&gt; : when your commit is adding something new to the repository.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;change&lt;/strong&gt; : when your commit is changing something that already exists.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;remove&lt;/strong&gt; : when your commit is removing things from the repository.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;fix&lt;/strong&gt; : when commit fixes something wrong with repository.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;update&lt;/strong&gt; : when commit updates version info about repository.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Commit messages respects everything &lt;a href=&#34;http://tbaggery.com/2008/04/19/a-note-about-git-commit-messages.html&#34;&gt;suggested&lt;/a&gt; by the great man of &lt;em&gt;Vim World&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/tpope&#34;&gt;Tim Pope&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;contribution&#34;&gt;Contribution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;termping&lt;/strong&gt; is still not complete, what you can contribute is :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A scoring thing, that counts score and decide winner when one player reach at score limit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A level thing, that divides the game in parts depending on level of difficulty.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feel free to open any &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/termping/issues&#34;&gt;issue&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/termping/pulls&#34;&gt;Pull requests&lt;/a&gt; with a feature you want there.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not directly writing any more code to it right now, because I have to get involved with some other necessary things, but I will try to helps anyone interested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It was a great journey so far, with nice learning experience.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introducing modified-lanyon, Harry, and me</title>
      <link>http://pravj.github.io/blog/introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2014 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pravj.github.io/blog/introduction/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Yes, you don&#39;t know me. Cool, I&#39;m telling you that.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am Pravendra. Developer at awesome &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/sdslabs&#34;&gt;SDSLabs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also a Computer Science undergraduate student at IIT Roorkee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I&amp;rsquo;m not scrolling in sublime-text or vim, I am watching Discovery Channel :bowtie:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a sincere reader and It feels nice to read about other&amp;rsquo;s experiences in different fields.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it shows new things that you are not aware about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;A thought of owning a blog have always excited me.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My choice for a setup was &lt;code&gt;Jekyll&lt;/code&gt; powered blog hosted with &lt;code&gt;Github Pages&lt;/code&gt;, so I started searching for a cool Jekyll theme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;lanyon-https-github-com-poole-lanyon&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/poole/lanyon&#34;&gt;Lanyon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Definition according to it&amp;rsquo;s Developer &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/mdo&#34;&gt;@mdo&lt;/a&gt;
&amp;gt; Lanyon is an unassuming Jekyll theme that places content first by tucking away navigation in a hidden drawer. It&amp;rsquo;s based on Poole, the Jekyll butler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s really a cool theme with pretty nice design and a Toggelable sliding sidebar to provide enough space for your content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Themes avaiable on internet are generally meant to be used as it is or without any hesitation but I wanted something extra in the theme. I wanted to have tags for each post and post sorting according to tags.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One more thing was that original Lanyon theme serves fix posts on a page and provides pagination(customizable). So if you want to read first post, you have to manually visit all pages till you reach at last page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then an old chat with &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/leostatic&#34;&gt;@sm&lt;/a&gt; motivated me to do something on my own , he said :
&amp;gt; its never bad to develop a thing, if you are not copying something entirely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;modified-lanyon&#34;&gt;modified Lanyon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/modified-lanyon&#34;&gt;modified Lanyon&lt;/a&gt; is the jekyll theme, I ended up while customizing original Lanyon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things I added to the original theme are :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;now it shows title, date and related tags for each post on main page&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;It provides easy access to all posts&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;there is a section for all tags in posts, its lists all posts under each tag in archive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Reader can easily visit for each post under a tag.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;there is a timeline section showing all posts sorted according to year of post, having latest post first in timeline.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Clicking on a date of post opens the timeline section&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I added support to have smileys in blog, for this I created a jekyll plugin &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/Harry&#34;&gt;Harry&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Using it, you can use all emojis available on the famous www.emoji-cheat-sheet.com&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;modifying-lanyon&#34;&gt;modifying Lanyon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;each change I did was done with Jekyll Plugins&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://jekyllrb.com&#34;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; have cool &lt;a href=&#34;http://jekyllrb.com/docs/plugins/&#34;&gt;plugin&lt;/a&gt; support that allow you to create custom generated content specific to your site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;according to Jekyll documentation :
&amp;gt; in your site&amp;rsquo;s root directory inside &lt;code&gt;_plugins/&lt;/code&gt; directory any file ending in &lt;code&gt;.rb&lt;/code&gt; will be loaded before Jekyll generates your site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to change the index page rendering style, I used &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Shopify/liquid&#34;&gt;Liquid&lt;/a&gt; Tags and Filters in index.html to show listing of all posts with title, date and tags. see it &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/modified-lanyon/blob/master/index.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to list all posts under a particular tag :&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I created &lt;code&gt;tagger.rb&lt;/code&gt;, placed it in &lt;code&gt;_plugins/&lt;/code&gt;. it maps each tag in archive to related posts having that tag and let you use that mapped data via &lt;a href=&#34;http://jekyllrb.com/docs/variables/#site-variables&#34;&gt;site.pages&lt;/a&gt; variable. see it &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/modified-lanyon/blob/master/_plugins/tagger.rb&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to create the archive timeline :&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am using &lt;code&gt;timeline.rb&lt;/code&gt; from this &lt;a href=&#34;http://tech.pro/tutorial/1299/getting-started-with-jekyll-plugins&#34;&gt;tutorial&lt;/a&gt;, I reversed the data to show latest post first in timeline. see it &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/modified-lanyon/blob/master/_plugins/timeline.rb&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;harry&#34;&gt;Harry&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/Harry&#34;&gt;Harry&lt;/a&gt; is the jekyll plugin I developed, it lets you use any smiley from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.emoji-cheat-sheet.com/&#34;&gt;emoji-cheat-sheet&lt;/a&gt; in your blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was fun developing this, because I just love smileys. specially this :grinning:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It saves any valid smiley image in &lt;code&gt;public/smileys/&lt;/code&gt; from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.emoji-cheat-sheet.com/&#34;&gt;emoji-cheat-sheet&lt;/a&gt; and serve from here. more about using Harry can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/Harry/blob/master/README.md&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;problem-with-using-jekyll-plugins-on-github-pages&#34;&gt;Problem with using Jekyll Plugins on GitHub Pages&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Github Pages don&amp;rsquo;t allow you to use plugins because of security reasons, so I am pushing only generated static files to &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/pravj.github.io&#34;&gt;repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;source-code&#34;&gt;Source Code&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/pravj.github.io&#34;&gt;this blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/modified-lanyon&#34;&gt;modified-lanyon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/Harry&#34;&gt;Harry&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;depreciation&#34;&gt;Depreciation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, the theme that you are seeing right now, isn&amp;rsquo;t the &lt;em&gt;modified-lanyon&lt;/em&gt; theme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read about the current theme&amp;rsquo;s development, here. &lt;a href=&#34;http://pravj.github.io&#34;&gt;A little paint over my webspace&amp;rsquo;s design&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://pravj.github.io/quotes/deming/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pravj.github.io/quotes/deming/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In god we trust, all others must bring data.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://pravj.github.io/quotes/einstein/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pravj.github.io/quotes/einstein/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We act as though comfort and luxury were the chief requirements of life, when all that we need to make us happy is something to be enthusiastic about.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://pravj.github.io/quotes/jim-carrey/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pravj.github.io/quotes/jim-carrey/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I think everybody should get rich and famous and do everything they ever dreamed of, so they can see that it&amp;rsquo;s not the answer.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>