<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>hack(pravj)</title>
    <link>https://hackpravj.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on hack(pravj)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 02 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://hackpravj.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Hacking Semantris: The Google AI Experiment</title>
      <link>https://hackpravj.com/blog/hacking-semantris/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hackpravj.com/blog/hacking-semantris/</guid>
      <description>Semantris is a set of word association games that use semantic search to predict a relevant word in the game based on the player&amp;rsquo;s input.
 ARCADE Arcade mode requires a player to quickly come up with associated words for certain words. You are supposed to think and type as fast as you can before an increasing list of words fills your screen.
BLOCKS Blocks is a turn-based game mode.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inside Cricket</title>
      <link>https://hackpravj.com/blog/inside-cricket/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hackpravj.com/blog/inside-cricket/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contributing to the Go programming language</title>
      <link>https://hackpravj.com/blog/first-golang-contribution-experience/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hackpravj.com/blog/first-golang-contribution-experience/</guid>
      <description>This article describes my experience contributing the first commit to the Go programming language. It might be one small step for you, but it&amp;rsquo;s one giant leap for the gopher inside me.
 Along with my experience, I will outline the article as a (beginner&amp;rsquo;s) gopher&amp;rsquo;s guide for contributing to an open source project (the Go project in this case).
I have started learning Go in the late 2014 and I was lucky enough to receive a healthy appreciation from the community for my very first project in the language.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Information Dynamics on the GitHub Network</title>
      <link>https://hackpravj.com/blog/information-dynamics-on-github/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hackpravj.com/blog/information-dynamics-on-github/</guid>
      <description>Exploring the &amp;ldquo;social coding&amp;rdquo; behavior.
 Social groups have a system of behaviors occurring within the group or between groups, called “Group dynamics”. GitHub, being a social coding network, is the host to millions of developers and software projects. This report will use openly available data to unveil such behaviors in an intellectual-focused social network.
Social Coding The growth of GitHub has been significantly different from other OSS communities such as Alioth, Freecode, and Savannah.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Breaking into the Indian E-commerce</title>
      <link>https://hackpravj.com/blog/indian-ecommerce/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hackpravj.com/blog/indian-ecommerce/</guid>
      <description>Before I start telling you the story, I&amp;rsquo;m going to do an experiment. I&amp;rsquo;ll write the summary of this post first, just to stick you around, in case you are one among the people who don&amp;rsquo;t read to the end.
tl;dr Myntra is India&amp;rsquo;s largest online fashion and lifestyle store, as they say. Which is owned by Flipkart, one of the big players in Indian E-commerce.
I found a little opening in the flow of their online movement and used it to collect some information(not private though).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jump in to ride all the Bangalore taxis, at once</title>
      <link>https://hackpravj.com/blog/bangalore-taxis/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hackpravj.com/blog/bangalore-taxis/</guid>
      <description>All right, just imagine that you have popcorn with you, because I know that you don&amp;rsquo;t have.
I decided to do this report when I was in Bangalore this summer, Sillicon Valley of India. You can observe a gob of information flowing through in such metropolitan population. People ordering/delivering meal, groceries or literally everything by online orders, people booking a vehicle and riding in no time, people booking a seat for dinner/movie and many more thing to generate the logs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Development story of puzzl</title>
      <link>https://hackpravj.com/blog/development-story-of-puzzl/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hackpravj.com/blog/development-story-of-puzzl/</guid>
      <description>Lets start with that old promotion rant I use all the time.
 You should have a look at puzzl, if you haven&amp;rsquo;t yet.
 What this is all about? This post is about development of a sliding-puzzle game I made recently, named puzzl. I refer it as an intelligent version of the classical sliding puzzle game, and I&amp;rsquo;ll explain the reason behind this. Stay awake.
 Puzzl in action  For What Joy?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Holy Aesthete : painting a virtual wall</title>
      <link>https://hackpravj.com/blog/virtual-wall/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hackpravj.com/blog/virtual-wall/</guid>
      <description>Today, it&amp;rsquo;s the day of Holi, the festival of colors in India.
Yesterday, it was the end of our midterm exams.
Such Time. Much Rhyme.
  Virtual Wall  During the last minutes, I decided to stop writing after matching an answer with the person sitting next to me. I was all set to run outside the hall and smell the woot! no more exams left scent in the air.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introducing Penticons : The Hash Game</title>
      <link>https://hackpravj.com/blog/penticons-the-hash-game/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hackpravj.com/blog/penticons-the-hash-game/</guid>
      <description>Jennifer Lawrence fan, huh? It was The Hash Game by the way. Still in? Kewl.
What&amp;rsquo;s the buzz all about? Unfortunately, there is no buzz. This post is about development of Penticons.
Penticons. What? Remember those egg shaped profile pictures on Twitter? They are automaticaly linked to your profile, when you forget to upload your custom profile picture.
Different services uses different default profile pictures. For example, Quora uses this image of their co-founder Charlie Cheever.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open Source Presence Infographic of Indian Startups</title>
      <link>https://hackpravj.com/blog/open-source-presence-infographic/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hackpravj.com/blog/open-source-presence-infographic/</guid>
      <description>Technically speaking, organizations used in this report are no more only a startup now, but I hope you people won&amp;rsquo;t mind this and aren&amp;rsquo;t gonna launch a drone on me.
Abstract I think, something is clear from the name itself, is it? Well! it should.
This report tries to plot all the involved organizations on the Open-Source portal. It tries to tell that, in the race to achieve their goals, what different organizations are doing there, for/in the community.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The git-game Write-up</title>
      <link>https://hackpravj.com/blog/the-git-game-writeup/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hackpravj.com/blog/the-git-game-writeup/</guid>
      <description>Spoiler Alert
You should go and check this out, git-game.
It&amp;rsquo;s a nice little complete-a-task-and-upgrade-level type of game layered on top of Git.
 It is a terminal game designed to test your knowledge of git commands. Each level in the game is a task to perform on this repo. Once you perform that task, you will be given your next task. There are a total of ten levels, each one harder than last!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Post-mortem of an Internet Accident</title>
      <link>https://hackpravj.com/blog/post-mortem-of-an-internet-accident/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hackpravj.com/blog/post-mortem-of-an-internet-accident/</guid>
      <description>Hi scout, thanks for visiting this node of the Holy Internet Graph; Before the combination Internet Accident confuse you, let me decode its meaning in the context of this post.
 Encounter with something on an edge node of the Holy Internet.
 So this post is all about my attempt to solve a question, I saw on Quora.
 What good known projects on GitHub uses the largest number of programming languages?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>geopattern : going on the Go path</title>
      <link>https://hackpravj.com/blog/going-on-the-go-path/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hackpravj.com/blog/going-on-the-go-path/</guid>
      <description>You should have a look at geopattern, if you haven&amp;rsquo;t yet.
 What&amp;rsquo;s the buzz all about? This blog post is about development of geopattern library in golang.
What do you think about this my favorite colored concentric circle pattern?
 Concentric Circle Pattern  geopattern. What? Umm, actually I don&amp;rsquo;t know exactly why the name is geopattern but I know what it is.
It is a golang library that generates pretty image patterns.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>termping : &lt;3 &#43; Node.js &#43; Streams &#43; CoffeeScript</title>
      <link>https://hackpravj.com/blog/termping/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hackpravj.com/blog/termping/</guid>
      <description>You should have a look at termping, if you haven&amp;rsquo;t yet.
 What&amp;rsquo;s the fuss about This Blog is all about development of a game(kind of) termping, which is a prototype of one of the oldest video game Pong.
 But this prototype runs in your system&amp;rsquo;s terminal
  termping in action  Emergence  One thing that I just feel, I am getting good at is &amp;ldquo;reading and understanding other people&amp;rsquo;s code&amp;rdquo; &amp;#35;notprasingmyself</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introducing modified-lanyon, Harry, and me</title>
      <link>https://hackpravj.com/blog/introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2014 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hackpravj.com/blog/introduction/</guid>
      <description>Yes, you don&#39;t know me. Cool, I&#39;m telling you that.
 I am Pravendra. Developer at awesome SDSLabs.
Also a Computer Science undergraduate student at IIT Roorkee.
When I&amp;rsquo;m not scrolling in sublime-text or vim, I am watching Discovery Channel :bowtie:
I am a sincere reader and It feels nice to read about other&amp;rsquo;s experiences in different fields.
Sometimes it shows new things that you are not aware about.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://hackpravj.com/quotes/deming/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hackpravj.com/quotes/deming/</guid>
      <description>In god we trust, all others must bring data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://hackpravj.com/quotes/einstein/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hackpravj.com/quotes/einstein/</guid>
      <description>We act as though comfort and luxury were the chief requirements of life, when all that we need to make us happy is something to be enthusiastic about.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://hackpravj.com/quotes/jim-carrey/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hackpravj.com/quotes/jim-carrey/</guid>
      <description>I think everybody should get rich and famous and do everything they ever dreamed of, so they can see that it&amp;rsquo;s not the answer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://hackpravj.com/quotes/john-nash/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hackpravj.com/quotes/john-nash/</guid>
      <description>Classes will dull your mind, destroy the potential for authentic creativity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://hackpravj.com/quotes/passenger/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hackpravj.com/quotes/passenger/</guid>
      <description>Tie your scarf on tight, it&amp;rsquo;s to be a cold night.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://hackpravj.com/quotes/pull-request/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hackpravj.com/quotes/pull-request/</guid>
      <description>Be the pull request you want to see in the repository.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://hackpravj.com/quotes/realization/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hackpravj.com/quotes/realization/</guid>
      <description>Realize that everything matters only as much as you want it to matter. You have a choice of deciding your priorities, rest everything doesn&amp;rsquo;t really matter to you. Once you convince yourself of the non-importance of most issues, you won&amp;rsquo;t think about them much.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://hackpravj.com/quotes/robin-williams/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hackpravj.com/quotes/robin-williams/</guid>
      <description>You&amp;rsquo;re only given a little spark of madness. You mustn&amp;rsquo;t lose it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://hackpravj.com/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hackpravj.com/about/</guid>
      <description>I am a man of vehement disposition, with violent enthusiasms, and extreme immoderation in all my passions. - Oliver Sacks  Heya!
I&amp;rsquo;m Pravendra Singh, passionate about solving real life problems.
I obtained my undergraduate degree from the Indian Institute of Technology, Roorkee (Computer Science and Engineering, 2016).
My interests are Data Analysis and Visualization, Information Retrieval, Programming Languages, and Distributed Systems. I&amp;rsquo;m eager to work on a combination of these areas to build products having an impact on someone&amp;rsquo;s daily life.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://hackpravj.com/projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hackpravj.com/projects/</guid>
      <description>Projects, out of thin air.
 I nurture my secret chores in the ~/projects/ directory. If you want to see all of my projects that managed to get out of that directory, you can head over to my GitHub.
 Jump in to ride all the Bangalore taxis, at once Data Science, Information Retrieval, Architecture
 Cab availability in Bangalore  How many UBER cars are there around you, 5 to 7?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>