<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>hack(pravj)</title>
    <link>https://pravj.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on hack(pravj)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://pravj.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Information Dynamics on the GitHub Network</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/blog/information-dynamics-on-github/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/blog/information-dynamics-on-github/</guid>
      <description>Exploring the &amp;ldquo;social coding&amp;rdquo; behavior.
 Social groups have a system of behaviors occurring within the group or between groups, called “Group dynamics”. GitHub, being a social coding network, is the host to millions of developers and software projects. This report will use openly available data to unveil such behaviors in an intellectual-focused social network.
Social Coding The growth of GitHub has been significantly different from other OSS communities such as Alioth, Freecode, and Savannah.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2015 - A year in review</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/2015-year-in-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 12:15:24 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/2015-year-in-review/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s that time of year when people are writing about what they accomplished in the year, sites are publishing countless the-best-of lists and the only thing I&amp;rsquo;m left wondering seeing YouTube Rewind is - &amp;ldquo;How come I&amp;rsquo;ve never heard any of this?&amp;rdquo;
Since last year, I too have started this ritual of writing down key highlights of my year so that I can look back a few years from now and have a chuckle at my naiveté.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Breaking into the Indian E-commerce</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/blog/indian-ecommerce/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/blog/indian-ecommerce/</guid>
      <description>Before I start telling you the story, I&amp;rsquo;m going to do an experiment. I&amp;rsquo;ll write the summary of this post first, just to stick you around, in case you are one among the people who don&amp;rsquo;t read to the end.
tl;dr Myntra is India&amp;rsquo;s largest online fashion and lifestyle store, as they say. Which is owned by Flipkart, one of the big players in Indian E-commerce.
I found a little opening in the flow of their online movement and used it to collect some information(not private though).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding RPCs - Part II</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/understanding-rpcs-partii/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Sep 2015 20:33:29 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/understanding-rpcs-partii/</guid>
      <description>In the previous post, we introduced remote procedure calls and their use within a distributed system. In this post, we are going to dive deep into the concept of semantics - first in the context of distributed systems in general and then discuss various RPC semantics.
Semantics We&amp;rsquo;re now going to briefly talk about one of the most important aspects in a distributed systems - semantics. What do you mean by semantics?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding RPCs - Part I</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/understanding-rpcs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Sep 2015 20:33:29 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/understanding-rpcs/</guid>
      <description>Having looked at a distributed system i.e the domain name system in the previous post, lets turn our attention to something more fundamental. In this blog post, we are going to start diving deeper into one of the basic blocks of Distributed Systems - Remote Procedure Calls or RPCs.
The paper that we&amp;rsquo;re going to be looking at today is authored by the duo of Nelson and Birell who were the first set of people to build an RPC implementation for their work at Xerox PARC.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Domain Name System</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/the-domain-name-system/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Sep 2015 20:33:29 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/the-domain-name-system/</guid>
      <description>One of the classes that I&amp;rsquo;ve taken this semester is Advanced Distributed Systems. The course is primarily a research seminar wherein the students are required to read a couple of research topics for each class and participate in a two hour discussion which is guided by the professor. My goal in these series of blog posts is to summarize the papers in an approchable manner primarily to test my own understanding of the topic.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jump in to ride all the Bangalore taxis, at once</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/blog/bangalore-taxis/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/blog/bangalore-taxis/</guid>
      <description>All right, just imagine that you have popcorn with you, because I know that you don&amp;rsquo;t have.
I decided to do this report when I was in Bangalore this summer, Sillicon Valley of India. You can observe a gob of information flowing through in such metropolitan population. People ordering/delivering meal, groceries or literally everything by online orders, people booking a vehicle and riding in no time, people booking a seat for dinner/movie and many more thing to generate the logs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scalable Machine Learning</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/scalable-machine-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jul 2015 20:33:29 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/scalable-machine-learning/</guid>
      <description>A couple of days ago I finally finished the last assignment of the Scalable Machine Learning course. The last few days in Kuwait were a bit tough as I had tons of stuff to do before leaving the country. It turns out leaving Kuwait is even harder than getting there in the first place. Additionally I had set a personal deadline of finishing the course a week before the actual deadline so that I when I reach home I could focus on other work.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 10 - Surveyman</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/surveyman-week10/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2015 15:50:49 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/surveyman-week10/</guid>
      <description>After a fun and productive two weeks at home, I have now rejoined office back in Kuwait. As all good things in life, the vacation has come to an end and it&amp;rsquo;s now time to head back to the usual humdrum of 9 to 5. What also didn&amp;rsquo;t help was the fact that since most of easy (low hanging fruits, if you will) features had already been built, I had no option but to start work on the feature which I most dreaded - implementing sortable on blocks / questions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Intro to Big Data with Apache Spark</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/big-data-with-spark/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jun 2015 20:33:29 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/big-data-with-spark/</guid>
      <description>Last night I finished the final assignment for the new course that I had been working on in the past week called Intro to Big Data with Apache Spark or CS100.1 x. With the course over, I decided to write down a quick review in the hope that it will help others get an idea of what they can expect by enrolling in this popular MOOC by UC Berkeley.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 9 - Surveyman</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/surveyman-week9/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2015 15:50:49 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/surveyman-week9/</guid>
      <description>This is my last week at home (India) and the fact that I had a pretty productive week shows that I&amp;rsquo;m ensconced within the comforts of my home. After the hectic last week which involved traveling, meeting relatives and getting documentation ready for the Visa interview this week was just me sitting at home working on this project without any distractions.
So there were three key features that I tackled this week, namely - TreeView, Option Lists and React transitions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 8 - Surveyman</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/surveyman-week8/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2015 15:50:49 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/surveyman-week8/</guid>
      <description>If you&amp;rsquo;ve read the previous blog post, you would be aware that I&amp;rsquo;m right now back to my home country on a vacation. This week has been quite hectic and filled with anxiety owing to the visa interview that I had scheduled during the start of the week. Since this was my first time appearing for a US Visa interview, I was quite in awe of how the smooth and planned the entire process was, especially compared to the other interview processes I&amp;rsquo;d been in (I&amp;rsquo;m looking at you Kuwait).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 7 - Surveyman</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/surveyman-week7/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jun 2015 15:50:49 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/surveyman-week7/</guid>
      <description>Guess what, I&amp;rsquo;m writing this blog post from my home in Delhi! I&amp;rsquo;ll be in India for full 2 weeks where apart from visiting my family, cousins and friends I&amp;rsquo;ll also be giving my visa interview - which is the main reason why I&amp;rsquo;ve taken a vacation.
As I had been traveling the progress this week has been rather minimal. Keeping the travel schedule in mind, I had kept the goal to be reasonable which was upgrading the react-surveyman project to use React-DnD&amp;rsquo;s latest 1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 6 - Surveyman</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/surveyman-week6/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2015 15:50:49 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/surveyman-week6/</guid>
      <description>So I started this week with the primary goal of re-writing my stores and migrating them to use Immutable collections. In the last week&amp;rsquo;s post, I laid out the motivation on why this is a good idea and how it will speed up the React application.
While the benefits were clear, I was still not sure on how I could implement and exploit the collections provided by Immutable to my advantage.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 5 - Surveyman</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/surveyman-week5/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 May 2015 15:50:49 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/surveyman-week5/</guid>
      <description>I signed off the last post mentioning that I&amp;rsquo;ll be integrating the React tags component into Surveyman which did not turn out to be difficult. As the API of the component was simple, it just meant adding the component and providing the necessary event handlers.
The suggestions are loaded as soon as a Question component is dropped, which after careful thought, sounds like a practical tradeoff. Suggestions are maintained as a set and whenever is new Option is added by the user, it gets appended to the set.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 4 - Surveyman</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/surveyman-week4/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 May 2015 15:50:49 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/surveyman-week4/</guid>
      <description>I closed last week&amp;rsquo;s update giving an indication that I started work on a standalone React component. After working on the component this week, I was finally able to finish it and publish it on NPM.
So before I go into what React-tag-input does, I&amp;rsquo;ll try and explain the motivation for building it. If you&amp;rsquo;ve been following closely, the primary way of building the survey in Surveyman is via Drag and Drop.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 3 - Surveyman</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/surveyman-week3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2015 15:50:49 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/surveyman-week3/</guid>
      <description>This update is coming in a bit late, especially after the week 1 and week 2 updates posted earlier. After progressing a bit on the initial setup and features I decided to take a week off Surveyman and instead wait for the GSOC results to arrive so that I could get feedback from Emma, my mentor for this project and see if I were on the right track.
Much to my delight I got selected in GSOC to work for Surveyman!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Development story of puzzl</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/blog/development-story-of-puzzl/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/blog/development-story-of-puzzl/</guid>
      <description>Lets start with that old promotion rant I use all the time.
 You should have a look at puzzl, if you haven&amp;rsquo;t yet.
 What this is all about? This post is about development of a sliding-puzzle game I made recently, named puzzl. I refer it as an intelligent version of the classical sliding puzzle game, and I&amp;rsquo;ll explain the reason behind this. Stay awake.
 Puzzl in action  For What Joy?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 2 - Surveyman</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/surveyman-week2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Apr 2015 06:58:24 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/surveyman-week2/</guid>
      <description>After the drop targets and drag sources were configured last week, this week my primary motive was to develop a better UI for adding Question types. After mulling over the UI a bit, I decided to replace the existing Javascript prompt with a modal which would allow text entry and multiple radio buttons / checkboxes to configure various parts of a Question type.
  Adding a Bootstrap Modal   UI  The key idea behind Surveyman is that by giving survey authors a way to write their surveys that steers them away from unnecessary ordering constraints, we can apply static analysis, randomization, and statistical dynamic analysis to locate survey errors and ensure the quality of responses.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 1 - Surveyman</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/surveyman-week1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Apr 2015 06:58:24 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/surveyman-week1/</guid>
      <description>Last week, I announced that I have applied for GSOC project called Surveyman as a part of which I&amp;rsquo;ll be building a React application that allows users to build a survey.
How will this be different from the countless other similar tools that exist? For the long answer, I&amp;rsquo;d advise you to read the paper but the short answer is that SurveyMan exposes a lightweight Domain Specific Language for designing and deploying surveys.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Month of March</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/the-month-of-march/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Mar 2015 06:58:24 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/the-month-of-march/</guid>
      <description>Being busy with a couple of important things, both personally and professionally, this blog did not see any new post published this month. So before this month ends, I decided to quickly summarize the major things that happened in March.
EasyCredit For the past 6 months, I&amp;rsquo;d been working intermittently on a pretty cool application at my workplace, finally shipped in the first week of March. The app, built on Flask and Backbone, allows users to pay for their installments via an easy and intuitive user interface.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Holy Aesthete : painting a virtual wall</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/blog/virtual-wall/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/blog/virtual-wall/</guid>
      <description>Today, it&amp;rsquo;s the day of Holi, the festival of colors in India.
Yesterday, it was the end of our midterm exams.
Such Time. Much Rhyme.
  Virtual Wall  During the last minutes, I decided to stop writing after matching an answer with the person sitting next to me. I was all set to run outside the hall and smell the woot! no more exams left scent in the air.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Becoming a Better Developer</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/a-better-developer/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2015 12:06:43 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/a-better-developer/</guid>
      <description>Every programmer has his/her own ideas on becoming a better developer. But if you read into what a few programming greats have to say, you will find a lot of overlap. One such point is about the importance of diving deeper rather than jumping around for variety. Below is a comment by Rich Hickey that I found posted in a gist. Due to the lack of original source, I&amp;rsquo;ve edited and added emphasis while reproducing his response.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The SWIM Membership Protocol</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/swim/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2015 12:42:49 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/swim/</guid>
      <description>Let&amp;rsquo;s say that you asked to build a distributed database similar to Cassandra. Your storage system will store and process large amounts of data running on a huge number of commodity servers. In other words, your system will rely on the power of 100s of nodes to manage data.
At this scale, failures will be the norm rather than the exception. Even if we assume that one node lasts for 1000 days (roughly 3 years), in a cluster of 500 nodes there will be a failure once every 2 days.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introducing Penticons : The Hash Game</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/blog/penticons-the-hash-game/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/blog/penticons-the-hash-game/</guid>
      <description>Jennifer Lawrence fan, huh? It was The Hash Game by the way. Still in? Kewl.
What&amp;rsquo;s the buzz all about? Unfortunately, there is no buzz. This post is about development of Penticons.
Penticons. What? Remember those egg shaped profile pictures on Twitter? They are automaticaly linked to your profile, when you forget to upload your custom profile picture.
Different services uses different default profile pictures. For example, Quora uses this image of their co-founder Charlie Cheever.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>High school calculus</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/differential/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Feb 2015 10:44:08 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/differential/</guid>
      <description>I spent a good part of the morning going through KhanAcademy high school calculus series. Why? Well, I had a differential equation to solve.
During this week&amp;rsquo;s lecture on Gossip protocols the Prof gave an interesting challenge of solving a differential equation. Now generally, I suck at proofs and I used to be the student who directly jumps at the proofs rather than working through them on his/her own. But today was different from school days - I had no fear of exams, or pressure of deadlines or the need to quickly finish homework before it gets dark outside (which would ruin the little playtime I earned in the evenings).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What You Need Is Discipline</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/you-need-discipline/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2015 15:50:49 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/you-need-discipline/</guid>
      <description>Productivity, procrastination, discipline, motivation are topics all too common to appear on hacker forums - especially on HN where smart and (mostly) self-taught hackers gather around to discuss and learn from each other.
The below excerpt is from an article that surfaced today and unsurprisingly got a good bit of attention and discussion on the forum.
 Productivity has no requisite mental states. For consistent, long-term results, discipline trumps motivation, runs circles around it, bangs its mom and eats its lunch.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Compile - A Python Builtin</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/the-compile-function/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2015 14:37:44 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/the-compile-function/</guid>
      <description>Quick question - You have a settings.cfg file (a list of key-value pairs) and you are required to read it in your Python program as a dict? How do you do it?
I found myself thinking over this question very recently while working with a Flask app. My task was simple - query the database, generate a report and email it as an attachment.
The only catch was the fact that all these configuration parameters i.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parsing Infix in Clojure</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/infix-in-clojure/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2015 14:41:27 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/infix-in-clojure/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been spending a good amount of time lately working on 4clojure in my free time. For those who don&amp;rsquo;t know, 4clojure is archive of problems for practicing Clojure. It accepts solutions in Clojure, runs the test cases and gives you feedback right in the browser.
Today I&amp;rsquo;ll share my experience on solving an interesting problem and seeing how we can use Clojure&amp;rsquo;s vast repertoire of functions in the standard library to make the code elegant and idiomatic.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open Source Presence Infographic of Indian Startups</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/blog/open-source-presence-infographic/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/blog/open-source-presence-infographic/</guid>
      <description>Technically speaking, organizations used in this report are no more only a startup now, but I hope you people won&amp;rsquo;t mind this and aren&amp;rsquo;t gonna launch a drone on me.
Abstract I think, something is clear from the name itself, is it? Well! it should.
This report tries to plot all the involved organizations on the Open-Source portal. It tries to tell that, in the race to achieve their goals, what different organizations are doing there, for/in the community.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The git-game Write-up</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/blog/the-git-game-writeup/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/blog/the-git-game-writeup/</guid>
      <description>Spoiler Alert
You should go and check this out, git-game.
It&amp;rsquo;s a nice little complete-a-task-and-upgrade-level type of game layered on top of Git.
 It is a terminal game designed to test your knowledge of git commands. Each level in the game is a task to perform on this repo. Once you perform that task, you will be given your next task. There are a total of ten levels, each one harder than last!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>One Thing Today</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/one-thing-today/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2015 19:06:12 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/one-thing-today/</guid>
      <description>Every morning in basic SEAL training, my instructors, who at the time were all Vietnam veterans, would show up in my barracks room and the first thing they would inspect was your bed.
If you did it right, the corners would be square, the covers pulled tight, the pillow centered just under the headboard and the extra blanket folded neatly at the foot of the rack—rack—that’s Navy talk for bed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Post-mortem of an Internet Accident</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/blog/post-mortem-of-an-internet-accident/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/blog/post-mortem-of-an-internet-accident/</guid>
      <description>Hi scout, thanks for visiting this node of the Holy Internet Graph; Before the combination Internet Accident confuse you, let me decode its meaning in the context of this post.
 Encounter with something on an edge node of the Holy Internet.
 So this post is all about my attempt to solve a question, I saw on Quora.
 What good known projects on GitHub uses the largest number of programming languages?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2014 - A year in review</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/2014-year-in-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 23:15:24 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/2014-year-in-review/</guid>
      <description>With 2014 over, I think it&amp;rsquo;s a good time to get introspective and spend time thinking about key developments that happened throughout the year. My main motivation for this post is to be able to look back a couple of years from now and remember how 2014 was for me.
Writing 2014 was finally a year where I&amp;rsquo;d like to think that I succeeded in blogging. Although I did fall short of my initial goal of one post per week I averaged around 3 posts a month which, for someone who&amp;rsquo;s failed regularly at blogging, is a great success.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>University Courses</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/university-courses/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2014 20:33:29 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/university-courses/</guid>
      <description>It would be an understatement to say that one of my favorite pastime is hoarding (no not the kind where I can hoard physical goods to drive up prices). I hoard blog posts, videos, E-books, Dribbble screenshots and almost anything I can lay my hands on in the hope that one day I&amp;rsquo;ll have to time to actually go through it.
While working through recent MOOCs and frequently stumbling on academic papers, I felt that there&amp;rsquo;s a whole load of treasure hidden deep within university pages.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mining of Massive DataSets - A Review</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/mining-of-massive-datasets---a-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/mining-of-massive-datasets---a-review/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve been keeping track, I&amp;rsquo;ve hardly published a single article in the last month. In my defense, the last 7 months have been extremely hectic. High work pressure and a rather dense online course kept most of the drafts from seeing the light of day.   Before I jump in reviewing the course i.e. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.coursera.org/course/mmds&#34;&gt;Mining Massive DataSets (MMDS)&lt;/a&gt;, here&amp;rsquo;s a quick short story for some context.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>geopattern : going on the Go path</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/blog/going-on-the-go-path/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/blog/going-on-the-go-path/</guid>
      <description>You should have a look at geopattern, if you haven&amp;rsquo;t yet.
 What&amp;rsquo;s the buzz all about? This blog post is about development of geopattern library in golang.
What do you think about this my favorite colored concentric circle pattern?
 Concentric Circle Pattern  geopattern. What? Umm, actually I don&amp;rsquo;t know exactly why the name is geopattern but I know what it is.
It is a golang library that generates pretty image patterns.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bloom Filters for Dummies</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/bloom-filters-for-dummies/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Oct 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/bloom-filters-for-dummies/</guid>
      <description>Bloom Filters is one of those data structures that you don&amp;rsquo;t generally learn about in a typical data structures 101 class, but wish you had learnt once you know about them. Despite reading several articles on bloom filters I was still finding it hard to grasp the concepts until the last week when I decided to sit down and not get up until I get the hang of it. Below is an article where I attempt to explain what I understood in a clear way (hopefully) so that others can learn.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Just Learn</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/just-learn/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/just-learn/</guid>
      <description>So strangely enough the optimal thing do to in college if you want to be a successful startup founder is not some sort of new, vocational version of college focused on &#34;entrepreneurship.&#34; It&#39;s the classic version of college as education for its own sake. If you want to start a startup after college, what you should do in college is learn powerful things. And if you have genuine intellectual curiosity, that&#39;s what you&#39;ll naturally tend to do if you just follow your own inclinations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Armin on Rust</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/armin-on-rust/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/armin-on-rust/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been trying out Rust for some time and have been totally loving it so far. Glad to see that Armin Ronacher, one of the programmers I highly respect feels the same!
 Rust is inspiring for many reasons. The biggest reason I like it is because it&amp;rsquo;s practical. I tried Haskell, I tried Erlang and neither of those languages spoke &amp;ldquo;I am a practical language&amp;rdquo; to me. I know there are many programmers that adore them, but they are not for me.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Happy Accident</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/a-happy-accident/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Sep 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/a-happy-accident/</guid>
      <description>Last week, I was pleasantly surprised to find an email by a correspondent of Economic Times (a leading newspaper in India) asking for permission to quote a comment I made on Hacker News in the newspaper&amp;rsquo;s front page!
 I hope they have India on their radar! It would be awesome for the Indian Startup scene to hear all those great speakers live!
   Who knew that a comment on HN would end up on the front-page of a newspaper!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Do You Want To Do Great Things?</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/why-do-you-want-to-do-great-things/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/why-do-you-want-to-do-great-things/</guid>
      <description>During my usual late night lurking on HN today, I came across this gem of a comment and couldn&amp;rsquo;t help sharing it here.
 Why do you want to do great things? Seriously, dig into it. When I ask a lot of people in startups this question and dig long enough, it comes down to money&amp;ndash; they want to be rich, they want to be free.
Fact: I&amp;rsquo;ve met these rich/free people and they are largely working their asses off to get more rich (and presumably more free?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Maciej on Matasano</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/maciej-on-matasano/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/maciej-on-matasano/</guid>
      <description>Just when you promise yourself that you are going to work on systems for a couple of weeks and not get diverted, you get to hear about new ways to kill time learning crypto
 As a programmer, my core strengths have always been knowing how to apologize to users, and composing funny tweets. While I can hook up a web template to a database and make the squigglies come out right, I cannot efficiently sort something for you on a whiteboard, or tell you where to get a monad.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Weekend Hack - Monte Pi</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/pi-approximations-using-monte-carlo/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/pi-approximations-using-monte-carlo/</guid>
      <description>I spent this weekend building a cool visualization to better understand Monte Carlo methods. With [p5.js]() just being released last week, I was anxiously looking for a project idea that I could use this library for. Thanks to a Functional Programming course that I was working on last week, the idea came soon enough.
Monti Pi is a simple app that shows how you can carry out multiple Monte Carlo simulations to approximate the value of Pi.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Organizing Angular Apps for Testing</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/organizing-angular-apps-for-testing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Aug 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/organizing-angular-apps-for-testing/</guid>
      <description>In the last post, I talked about how we moved away from jQuery to Angularjs to power our single page application. To recap, the major problems with our existing code which convinced us to do a rewrite -
 The existing code was written by a team which was no longer with the project. No one on the existing team had a strong understanding of how the code worked. Without any structure, the code was extremely hard to maintain and understand.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GOOOAL</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/goooal/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jul 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/goooal/</guid>
      <description>Today morning while browsing The Changelog, I came across this interesting project called - Goal.
 g()(&amp;lsquo;al&amp;rsquo;) is a challenge whereby you need to write in as many languages as possible code which enables the code g()(&amp;lsquo;al&amp;rsquo;) to return the string &amp;ldquo;goal&amp;rdquo;, the code g()()(&amp;lsquo;al&amp;rsquo;) to return the string &amp;ldquo;gooal&amp;rdquo;, the code g()()()(&amp;lsquo;al&amp;rsquo;) return the string &amp;ldquo;goooal&amp;rdquo;, etc.
 This sounded a good way to kill a couple of hours on a lazy holiday so I decided to give this a shot in a couple of programming languages I know.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>termping : &lt;3 &#43; Node.js &#43; Streams &#43; CoffeeScript</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/blog/termping/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/blog/termping/</guid>
      <description>You should have a look at termping, if you haven&amp;rsquo;t yet.
 What&amp;rsquo;s the fuss about This Blog is all about development of a game(kind of) termping, which is a prototype of one of the oldest video game Pong.
 But this prototype runs in your system&amp;rsquo;s terminal
  termping in action  Emergence  One thing that I just feel, I am getting good at is &amp;ldquo;reading and understanding other people&amp;rsquo;s code&amp;rdquo; &amp;#35;notprasingmyself</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The String Rotation Problem</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/the-string-rotation-problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/the-string-rotation-problem/</guid>
      <description>On a recent (rather long) flight, while I was devouring Jon Bentley&amp;rsquo;s Programming Pearls, I came across this rather interesting problem.
The problem is simple - How will you a rotate a string of length n by i steps in place i.e. without using any extra space?
  The example shown below makes it quite clear. Now the easiest way to do this is to simply save the i chars in a separate vector, shift the remaining chars by i and finally, paste the initial i items at the back.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Heidi Roizen on ETL</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/heidi-roizen-on-etl/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Jul 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/heidi-roizen-on-etl/</guid>
      <description>Last week, Marco Arment launched a new product on HN, Overcast - An iPhone app that makes listening to podcasts much easier (and more fun).
There was a lot of productive discussion which made me realize that I need to give podcasts a serious chance. Given that I would be travelling soon, I went ahead, downloaded the most popular podcast app for Android and added a couple of feeds (thanks to this HN thread for recommendations).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fun with SparkFun</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/fun-with-sparkfun/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/fun-with-sparkfun/</guid>
      <description>This is about a quick hack that I did. Couple of days back, I came across a cool project called SparkFun on HN which is free online service to push your data. It allows you to create streams and then push data via a simple HTTP call. The primary motivation behind the service is to enable devices connected via Internet of Things to push data online easily.
I had been crawling a few websites to need of latest remittance rates to my home country (the rates offered for remittance differ quite substantially from the current spot rates).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Choosing Angular</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/choosing-angular/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Jul 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/choosing-angular/</guid>
      <description>For the last couple of weeks I&amp;rsquo;ve spent a good deal of time on building a brand new checkout for Xcite.com. Like other ecommerce websites, our website has a conventional 3 step checkout - login/signup, delivery and finally, payment. As a part of new project our goal is to allow customers to checkout as guests i.e. without the need of creating an account with Xcite. This allows us to reduce a step for customers who just want quickly purchase something off the website and be on their way.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Swift - First Impressions</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/swift-first-impressions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jun 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/swift-first-impressions/</guid>
      <description>Last week at WWDC Apple made the most exciting announcement (for developers at least) of launching a new programming language - Swift. Although I have never written a single line of code for iOS (in Objective C) I got so excited that within no time I was installing Xcode 6 to give playground &amp;amp; Swift a shot.
After spending a week with Swift I&amp;rsquo;ve come to the conclusion that it is a very well designed programming language.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>No Excuses</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/no-excuses/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 May 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/no-excuses/</guid>
      <description>Stop Making Excuses. Go Build Something  The point is, that you can and should teach yourself some new skills. You’re way closer to being employable than I was, that’s for sure. It may take some evenings and weekends, but they’ll be some of the most fun evening and weekends you ever have. Find something that you want to do and build it. Fall in love with the idea, but be ready to dump it for something better.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>It Ends</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/it-ends/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/it-ends/</guid>
      <description>Github Streak.  And so it ends! For the past 64 days, I&amp;rsquo;ve been working hard to keep contributing to open source, to keep committing meaningful commits each day. Yesterday, I decided to end it. Nearing the end, it started getting a bit tiring. I was spending my time in office thinking what will I work on today. In the start it was good, I had a couple of good postman projects to take care of.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evan Priestly on PHP</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/evan-priestly-on-php/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 May 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/evan-priestly-on-php/</guid>
      <description>At Facebook, I described myself as &amp;ldquo;the engineer who hates PHP the least&amp;rdquo; and have also been called a &amp;ldquo;PHP idiot savant&amp;rdquo;. While I&amp;rsquo;m not really a fan of PHP, my understanding of it is extremely deep so there&amp;rsquo;s a huge activation energy for me to learn something else. I also think language choice is far less important than most people make it out to be; in my experience, the people who I have encountered who scoff the hardest at PHP and cry the most loudly about the importance of languages tend to also be really bad at doing any useful work in the languages they advocate.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Automated Testing With Newman</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/automated-testing-with-newman/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 May 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/automated-testing-with-newman/</guid>
      <description>Steve Klabnik, the developer at Balanced recently put up a post on the company blog talking about doing TDD for APIs where he advocates a strong case for following Test Driven Development for APIs. For a lot of companies like Balanced, Stripe, Parse etc the API is their primary product. Hence, it makes sense to have strong development and testing practices for these APIs.
TDD has taken off quite well with DHH and the ruby community strongly making claims of it solving a lot of problems and guaranteeing robust code.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introducing modified-lanyon, Harry, and me</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/blog/introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2014 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/blog/introduction/</guid>
      <description>Yes, you don&#39;t know me. Cool, I&#39;m telling you that.
 I am Pravendra. Developer at awesome SDSLabs.
Also a Computer Science undergraduate student at IIT Roorkee.
When I&amp;rsquo;m not scrolling in sublime-text or vim, I am watching Discovery Channel :bowtie:
I am a sincere reader and It feels nice to read about other&amp;rsquo;s experiences in different fields.
Sometimes it shows new things that you are not aware about.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enums in Python</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/enums-in-python/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 May 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/enums-in-python/</guid>
      <description>On 12th May 2013, Guido accepted the Python Enhancement Proposal 435 which suggests adding an Enum type to the Python standard library. The news caused a lot of commotion in the Python community and generated (mostly) healthy discussions on Hacker News. In this post I&amp;rsquo;ll give an introduction to what enums are and talk about how you can use them in your programs.
Enumerated Types According to Wikipedia, an enumerated type is a data type consisting of a set of named values called elements, members or enumerators of the type.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Blueprints</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/using-blueprints/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 May 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/using-blueprints/</guid>
      <description>In today&amp;rsquo;s short lesson we&amp;rsquo;ll continue where we left off and completely wrap up the topic of code organization by learning about blueprints. Blueprints have been a rather recent addition to flask (introduced in version 0.7) and were added to help users structure large applications into reusable components.
Blueprints What exactly are blueprints? Lets see what the official documentation has to say. Flask uses a concept of blueprints for making application components and supporting common patterns within an application or across applications.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Newman Is Live</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/newman-is-live/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/newman-is-live/</guid>
      <description>And finally, after working non-stop on the project for 45 days Newman is finally in beta. Newman is a command-line collection runner for Postman built fully on Node.js. Newman is my first-ever node.js project and I&amp;rsquo;m extremely glad to have got a chance to build something useful and learn a new technology.
  Newman Demo.  Node has been on my radar for quite some time given its meteoric rise and hype.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Write Code Everyday</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/write-code-everyday/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Apr 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/write-code-everyday/</guid>
      <description>It’s important to note that that I don’t particularly care about the outward perception of the above Github chart. I think that’s the most important take away from this experiment: this is about a change that you’re making in your life for yourself not a change that you’re making to satisfy someone else’s perception of your work. The same goes for any form of dieting or exercise: if you don’t care about improving yourself then you’ll never actually succeed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thinking For Programmers</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/thinking-for-programmers/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/thinking-for-programmers/</guid>
      <description>Leslie Lamport, the creator the famous Paxos&amp;rsquo; Algorithm and LaTeX, in his paper talks about what programmers are doing wrong?
Answer: Not thinking enough
 For quite a while, I’ve been disturbed by the emphasis on language in computer science. One result of that emphasis is programmers who are C++ experts but can’t write programs that do what they’re supposed to. The typical computer science response is that programmers need to use the right programming/specification/development language instead of/in addition to C++.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Being A Senior Engineer</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/being-a-senior-engineer/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/being-a-senior-engineer/</guid>
      <description>Brilliant article on what differentiates senior engineers.
 Every successful engineer I’ve met, upon finishing up a design or getting ready for a project, will continually ask their peers questions along the lines of:  What could I be missing? How will this not work? Will you please shoot as many holes as possible into my thinking on this? Even if it’s technically sound, is it understandable enough for the rest of the organization to operate, troubleshoot, and extend it?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flask on Nginx and Gunicorn</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/flask-on-nginx-and-gunicorn/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Mar 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/flask-on-nginx-and-gunicorn/</guid>
      <description>Even after deploying a number of Flask apps I always find myself googling up blog posts on how to get the trio of nginx, gunicorn and supervisor working together. Below is simple, straight, no-nonsense guide on how to deploy a flask app on a Linux server using Nginx, Gunicorn and Supervisor.
A disclaimer: this guide will not tell you what these technologies are. Specifically, I will not talk about why you should use nginx + gunicorn instead of apache + mod_wsgi.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Few Git Tricks</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/a-few-git-tricks/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/a-few-git-tricks/</guid>
      <description>I just finished reading the Think Like (a) Git book which is a advanced beginners introduction to Git. Below is a quick rundown of a few cool git commands I learned about. Read on below to level up your Git skillz!
git add file &amp;ndash;patch Touted as the most powerful feature that you will ever use the patch mode allows you to selectively move changes from your working copy into the staging area.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deal With It</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/deal-with-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Feb 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/deal-with-it/</guid>
      <description>Hilarious fable on HN featuring the superhero Unix and its trusted sidekick - Vim!
ring ring ring
yeah, what&amp;rsquo;s up?
Nagios is paging, something with that code you pushed live a couple hours ago is throwing a fit&amp;hellip; looks like half the web cluster is on the verge of going to swap, can you look into it? asap!
Well, I&amp;rsquo;m on at the bus stop and won&amp;rsquo;t be near a computer for at least an hour&amp;hellip;yeah, I&amp;rsquo;ll sort it out, will text you when we can push fix live.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why We Dont Sell Ads</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/why-we-dont-sell-ads/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/why-we-dont-sell-ads/</guid>
      <description>I found this great statement made by the WhatsApp founders on their blog about why they don&amp;rsquo;t rely on ads and instead charge customers for the service. This is getting recirculated now that WhatsApp is looking at being acquired by Facebook at a valuation of around $19B. It interesting to see that while tons of apps rely on advertising as a key part of their business model there are companies who strive to go against it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Checksum</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/kuwait-civil-id-checksum/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/kuwait-civil-id-checksum/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s been around 8 months since I&amp;rsquo;ve started working in Kuwait &amp;amp; I can still vividly remember the hoopla we had to go through in order to get our Civil IDs. The Kuwaiti Government assigns a unique identification number to each and every resident of Kuwait which is called the Civil ID. This is quite similar to how it works in all the countries, however, the process in Kuwait is protracted and quite laborious for expats.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quantity</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/quantity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/quantity/</guid>
      <description>The ceramics teacher announced on opening day that he was dividing the class into two groups. All those on the left side of the studio, he said, would be graded solely on the quantity of work they produced, all those on the right solely on its quality. His procedure was simple: on the final day of class he would bring in his bathroom scales and weigh the work of the “quantity” group: fifty pound of pots rated an “A”, forty pounds a “B”, and so on.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Making the Blog Instant</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/making-the-blog-instant/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/making-the-blog-instant/</guid>
      <description>InstantClick.js was released on Hacker News today and I thought I will give it a whirl on my blog.
InstantClick is a simple library takes makes your pages faster by prefetching the target URL on hover (&amp;amp; touchstart in case of mobile). Based on the concept of Turbolinks and PJAX it works by utilizing the 200ms-300ms difference between a hover and a click to fetch the target content via an Ajax call.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Debugging Akamai Headers</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/debugging-akamai/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/debugging-akamai/</guid>
      <description>If you&amp;rsquo;ve got anything to do with Akamai&amp;rsquo;s caching, surely there must have come a time where you needed to find out whether your content is being cached at Akamai.
Pragma Headers The easiest way to test whether your content is cached at Akamai is to do via custom Pragma headers. What are Pragma headers you might say? The HTTP Specification has a simple definition of Pragma headers.
 The Pragma general-header field is used to include implementation-specific directives that might apply to any recipient along the request/response chain.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Programming is Hard</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/programming-is-hard/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/programming-is-hard/</guid>
      <description>When Joe Armstrong, the creator of Erlang, writes a post on &amp;ldquo;Programming is Hard&amp;rdquo; you cant help but say to yourself - You&amp;rsquo;re not alone!
 If you’ve got this far, you’ll understand that I think programming is pretty damn difficult. That’s why workplaces are designed to make programming even more difficult. We have open plan offices which provide a noisy environment to break our concentration, mobile phones to disturb us, and internet to distract us.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Class Based Views</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/class-based-views/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 May 2013 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/class-based-views/</guid>
      <description>If you&amp;rsquo;ve used Django before, one of the things that you surely miss (apart from the django-admin, of course) is class based (or generic) views. Class based views allow you to structure your views and reuse code by harnessing inheritance and mixins. This allows you to create generic views for routine tasks and simply inherit from them for similar views.
In flask 0.7 class based views were introduced which act similar to generic views in Django.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Application Structure</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/application-structure/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2013 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/application-structure/</guid>
      <description>In this post, we&amp;rsquo;re going to talk about a seemingly easy but an important topic - organizing and structuring your flask applications.
As mentioned earlier, getting started with flask is super easy. Unlike django, flask doesn&amp;rsquo;t follow a directory structure when you start a new app. Flask will not complain even if all of your code resides in a single main.py file. But we all know that that is not the way to go.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beginning Flask</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/beginning-flask/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2013 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/beginning-flask/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been meaning to start a write a series on Flask which is a micro-framework for developing web applications in python. In Ruby parlance, flask is to Sinatra what Django is to Rails.
The nicest thing (and most confusing for beginners) about Flask is that its quite barebones on the onset. A simple hello world application in Flask is just about 7 lines as shown below. However, going from hello world to full fledged application is a daunting task in itself for a beginner.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/quotes/deming/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/quotes/deming/</guid>
      <description>In god we trust, all others must bring data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/quotes/einstein/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/quotes/einstein/</guid>
      <description>We act as though comfort and luxury were the chief requirements of life, when all that we need to make us happy is something to be enthusiastic about.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/quotes/jim-carrey/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/quotes/jim-carrey/</guid>
      <description>I think everybody should get rich and famous and do everything they ever dreamed of, so they can see that it&amp;rsquo;s not the answer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/quotes/john-nash/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/quotes/john-nash/</guid>
      <description>Classes will dull your mind, destroy the potential for authentic creativity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/quotes/passenger/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/quotes/passenger/</guid>
      <description>Tie your scarf on tight, it&amp;rsquo;s to be a cold night.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/quotes/pull-request/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/quotes/pull-request/</guid>
      <description>Be the pull request you want to see in the repository.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/quotes/realization/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/quotes/realization/</guid>
      <description>Realize that everything matters only as much as you want it to matter. You have a choice of deciding your priorities, rest everything doesn&amp;rsquo;t really matter to you. Once you convince yourself of the non-importance of most issues, you won&amp;rsquo;t think about them much.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/quotes/robin-williams/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/quotes/robin-williams/</guid>
      <description>You&amp;rsquo;re only given a little spark of madness. You mustn&amp;rsquo;t lose it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/about/</guid>
      <description>I am a man of vehement disposition, with violent enthusiasms, and extreme immoderation in all my passions. - Oliver Sacks  Heya!
I&amp;rsquo;m Pravendra Singh, passionate about solving real life problems.
I obtained my undergraduate degree from the Indian Institute of Technology, Roorkee (Computer Science and Engineering, 2016).
My interests are Data Analysis and Visualization, Information Retrieval, and Distributed Systems. I&amp;rsquo;m eager to work on a combination of these areas to build products having an impact on someone&amp;rsquo;s daily life.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/projects/</guid>
      <description>Projects, out of thin air.
 I nurture my secret chores in the ~/projects/ directory. If you want to see all of my projects that managed to get out of that directory, you can head over to my GitHub.
 Jump in to ride all the Bangalore taxis, at once Data Science, Information Retrieval, Architecture
 Cab availability in Bangalore  How many UBER cars are there around you, 5 to 7?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>