<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Inspiration on hack(pravj)</title>
    <link>https://pravj.github.io/tags/inspiration/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Inspiration on hack(pravj)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2015 12:06:43 +0300</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://pravj.github.io/tags/inspiration/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Becoming a Better Developer</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/a-better-developer/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2015 12:06:43 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/a-better-developer/</guid>
      <description>Every programmer has his/her own ideas on becoming a better developer. But if you read into what a few programming greats have to say, you will find a lot of overlap. One such point is about the importance of diving deeper rather than jumping around for variety. Below is a comment by Rich Hickey that I found posted in a gist. Due to the lack of original source, I&amp;rsquo;ve edited and added emphasis while reproducing his response.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What You Need Is Discipline</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/you-need-discipline/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2015 15:50:49 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/you-need-discipline/</guid>
      <description>Productivity, procrastination, discipline, motivation are topics all too common to appear on hacker forums - especially on HN where smart and (mostly) self-taught hackers gather around to discuss and learn from each other.
The below excerpt is from an article that surfaced today and unsurprisingly got a good bit of attention and discussion on the forum.
 Productivity has no requisite mental states. For consistent, long-term results, discipline trumps motivation, runs circles around it, bangs its mom and eats its lunch.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>One Thing Today</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/one-thing-today/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2015 19:06:12 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/one-thing-today/</guid>
      <description>Every morning in basic SEAL training, my instructors, who at the time were all Vietnam veterans, would show up in my barracks room and the first thing they would inspect was your bed.
If you did it right, the corners would be square, the covers pulled tight, the pillow centered just under the headboard and the extra blanket folded neatly at the foot of the rack—rack—that’s Navy talk for bed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Just Learn</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/just-learn/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/just-learn/</guid>
      <description>So strangely enough the optimal thing do to in college if you want to be a successful startup founder is not some sort of new, vocational version of college focused on &#34;entrepreneurship.&#34; It&#39;s the classic version of college as education for its own sake. If you want to start a startup after college, what you should do in college is learn powerful things. And if you have genuine intellectual curiosity, that&#39;s what you&#39;ll naturally tend to do if you just follow your own inclinations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Do You Want To Do Great Things?</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/why-do-you-want-to-do-great-things/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/why-do-you-want-to-do-great-things/</guid>
      <description>During my usual late night lurking on HN today, I came across this gem of a comment and couldn&amp;rsquo;t help sharing it here.
 Why do you want to do great things? Seriously, dig into it. When I ask a lot of people in startups this question and dig long enough, it comes down to money&amp;ndash; they want to be rich, they want to be free.
Fact: I&amp;rsquo;ve met these rich/free people and they are largely working their asses off to get more rich (and presumably more free?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>No Excuses</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/no-excuses/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 May 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/no-excuses/</guid>
      <description>Stop Making Excuses. Go Build Something  The point is, that you can and should teach yourself some new skills. You’re way closer to being employable than I was, that’s for sure. It may take some evenings and weekends, but they’ll be some of the most fun evening and weekends you ever have. Find something that you want to do and build it. Fall in love with the idea, but be ready to dump it for something better.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Write Code Everyday</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/write-code-everyday/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Apr 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/write-code-everyday/</guid>
      <description>It’s important to note that that I don’t particularly care about the outward perception of the above Github chart. I think that’s the most important take away from this experiment: this is about a change that you’re making in your life for yourself not a change that you’re making to satisfy someone else’s perception of your work. The same goes for any form of dieting or exercise: if you don’t care about improving yourself then you’ll never actually succeed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thinking For Programmers</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/thinking-for-programmers/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/thinking-for-programmers/</guid>
      <description>Leslie Lamport, the creator the famous Paxos&amp;rsquo; Algorithm and LaTeX, in his paper talks about what programmers are doing wrong?
Answer: Not thinking enough
 For quite a while, I’ve been disturbed by the emphasis on language in computer science. One result of that emphasis is programmers who are C++ experts but can’t write programs that do what they’re supposed to. The typical computer science response is that programmers need to use the right programming/specification/development language instead of/in addition to C++.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Being A Senior Engineer</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/being-a-senior-engineer/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/being-a-senior-engineer/</guid>
      <description>Brilliant article on what differentiates senior engineers.
 Every successful engineer I’ve met, upon finishing up a design or getting ready for a project, will continually ask their peers questions along the lines of:  What could I be missing? How will this not work? Will you please shoot as many holes as possible into my thinking on this? Even if it’s technically sound, is it understandable enough for the rest of the organization to operate, troubleshoot, and extend it?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why We Dont Sell Ads</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/why-we-dont-sell-ads/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/why-we-dont-sell-ads/</guid>
      <description>I found this great statement made by the WhatsApp founders on their blog about why they don&amp;rsquo;t rely on ads and instead charge customers for the service. This is getting recirculated now that WhatsApp is looking at being acquired by Facebook at a valuation of around $19B. It interesting to see that while tons of apps rely on advertising as a key part of their business model there are companies who strive to go against it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quantity</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/quantity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/quantity/</guid>
      <description>The ceramics teacher announced on opening day that he was dividing the class into two groups. All those on the left side of the studio, he said, would be graded solely on the quantity of work they produced, all those on the right solely on its quality. His procedure was simple: on the final day of class he would bring in his bathroom scales and weigh the work of the “quantity” group: fifty pound of pots rated an “A”, forty pounds a “B”, and so on.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Programming is Hard</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/programming-is-hard/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2014 12:34:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/programming-is-hard/</guid>
      <description>When Joe Armstrong, the creator of Erlang, writes a post on &amp;ldquo;Programming is Hard&amp;rdquo; you cant help but say to yourself - You&amp;rsquo;re not alone!
 If you’ve got this far, you’ll understand that I think programming is pretty damn difficult. That’s why workplaces are designed to make programming even more difficult. We have open plan offices which provide a noisy environment to break our concentration, mobile phones to disturb us, and internet to distract us.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>