<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Rethinkdb on hack(pravj)</title>
    <link>http://pravj.github.io/tags/rethinkdb/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Rethinkdb on hack(pravj)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://pravj.github.io/tags/rethinkdb/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Breaking into the Indian E-commerce</title>
      <link>http://pravj.github.io/blog/indian-ecommerce/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pravj.github.io/blog/indian-ecommerce/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Before I start telling you the story, I&amp;rsquo;m going to do an experiment. I&amp;rsquo;ll write the summary of this post first, just to stick you around, in case you are one among the people who don&amp;rsquo;t read to the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;tl-dr&#34;&gt;tl;dr&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.myntra.com/&#34;&gt;Myntra&lt;/a&gt; is India&amp;rsquo;s largest online fashion and lifestyle store, as they say. Which is owned by &lt;a href=&#34;http://flipkart.com/&#34;&gt;Flipkart&lt;/a&gt;, one of the big players in Indian E-commerce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found a little opening in the flow of their online movement and used it to collect some information(&lt;em&gt;not private though&lt;/em&gt;). Using this information we can see the way &amp;lsquo;online shopping&amp;rsquo; is escalating in the country, and the role &lt;em&gt;Myntra&lt;/em&gt; and the people are playing in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sounds interesting? Hold on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;emergence-of-the-idea&#34;&gt;Emergence of the idea&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me tell you, how did I get started with this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this happened recently, when I was looking for some &lt;em&gt;T-Shirts&lt;/em&gt; with my friend. We placed a shared order for two and a pair of shoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever you order from Myntra, you get a &lt;em&gt;text message&lt;/em&gt; on your registered mobile number, giving you a link where you can &lt;em&gt;track your order&lt;/em&gt;. Each order is given a unique identifier of length 4 because it&amp;rsquo;s a shortened URL to fit well in a text message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I opened that link in my phone and it worked, saying that the details of your order are yet to be updated. Then I tried a different URL, not mine, of course, all thanks to my disruptive mind. It worked again, now this was something to pay attention to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know, 4 is a &lt;em&gt;nanoscopic&lt;/em&gt; number if a computer is your best friend. I think you can guess what happened next, I couldn&amp;rsquo;t sleep properly thinking about my next move to just have all the order details. Right from crawling and storing the data to analysing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;crawler-infrastructure&#34;&gt;Crawler Infrastructure&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being a &lt;em&gt;pessimistic&lt;/em&gt; person, as one of my friends calls me. I end up thinking too much about all the possible edge cases. Something similar happened with the design of the crawling system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the saying goes, &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;A thief believes everybody steals&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;. I was afraid that my collection signatures(IP) will be blocked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have read my last post &lt;a href=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/blog/bangalore-taxis/&#34;&gt;Jump in to ride all the Bangalore taxis, at once&lt;/a&gt;; I said that you should not hit the resource at a constant time period, it&amp;rsquo;s a basic heuristic to identify bots. I considered that, it was a simple thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now comes the main thing I was afraid of, &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;What if they catch me while trying to collect all the orders in a sequential manner (alphabetically increasing uid)&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I couldn&amp;rsquo;t take a risk of losing the data, I designed my solution around it. I developed two things, &lt;em&gt;Engine&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Station&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Engine&lt;/em&gt; is the one who takes care of the identifier generation and distribution. It uses a little &lt;em&gt;group theory&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;anagram properties&lt;/em&gt; to generate &lt;em&gt;non-sequential unique identifiers of fixed length&lt;/em&gt;. It generates them in advance and serve you &lt;em&gt;on demand&lt;/em&gt; while taking care of the stock by generating in the background when you start approaching the bottom of the vessel. To know more about &lt;em&gt;Engine&lt;/em&gt;, you can stalk its &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/engine&#34;&gt;repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Station&lt;/em&gt; is a Node.js package(&lt;em&gt;private obviously&lt;/em&gt;) running a &lt;em&gt;Nightmare&lt;/em&gt; instance for &lt;em&gt;headless browsing&lt;/em&gt;. From &lt;em&gt;Engine&lt;/em&gt;, it collects the next set of identifiers to fetch and then assemble all the necessary information before shipping it to the storage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/crawler-infra.png&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Crawler Design&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together they solve the problem with sequential crawling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now one more thing, the collection signature(IP) is still vulnerable to blocking. I found a (working) solution for it right on the Engineering blog of Myntra. They have an interesting post named &lt;a href=&#34;http://myntra.github.io/2015/01/19/dynamic-bot-detection-using-bloom-filters/&#34;&gt;Dynamic Bot Detection Using Bloom Filters&lt;/a&gt;, which labels you as a &lt;em&gt;bot&lt;/em&gt; if you have sent relatively more requests in the past 60 seconds. So the time difference &lt;em&gt;station&lt;/em&gt; assigns between two consecutive requests is dynamically set such that the &lt;em&gt;Bloom Filter&lt;/em&gt; is unable to catch it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Planning too much on the &lt;em&gt;Information Retrieval&lt;/em&gt; part has been a good exercise though, I&amp;rsquo;m thinking about working on a &lt;em&gt;Machine Learning approach of Bot Detection&lt;/em&gt;, where movement of a user from one page to another on service/website is mapped as &lt;em&gt;state transitions&lt;/em&gt; of a &lt;em&gt;Markov Chain&lt;/em&gt;, and anyone who violates the &lt;em&gt;transition probability range&lt;/em&gt; is a suspicious visitor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rough idea, leave that for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;statistical-nature-of-the-data&#34;&gt;Statistical nature of the data&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I read more and more research papers and live next to some great statistician&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Internet Residences&lt;/em&gt;, I know that you can&amp;rsquo;t conclude &lt;em&gt;a thing&lt;/em&gt; from a small dataset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the dataset that I have collected, there are 1045 &lt;em&gt;Returned Orders&lt;/em&gt;, 4406 &lt;em&gt;Cancelled Orders&lt;/em&gt; and 6368 &lt;em&gt;Completed Orders&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Returned Order&lt;/em&gt; means the package was returned back due to some reasons, and &lt;em&gt;Cancelled Orders&lt;/em&gt; means it was cancelled by the customer before shipping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This could have been a bigger one, so I&amp;rsquo;ll try not to &lt;em&gt;conclude&lt;/em&gt; a result here but we can see the customer behavior and the service &lt;em&gt;Myntra&lt;/em&gt; provides. Coming to a result from this data would be a case of &lt;em&gt;overfitting&lt;/em&gt; essentially.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the dataset is small, it&amp;rsquo;s distributed over a &lt;em&gt;time continuum&lt;/em&gt; instead of being a &lt;em&gt;discrete segment&lt;/em&gt;, because of the internal working of &lt;em&gt;Engine&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/engine.png&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;How Engine generate identifiers&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are all set to take off now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;when-does-india-shops&#34;&gt;When does India shops?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As long as I remember, I have ordered something online in the evening, around 06-07 PM. But this is not the case for everyone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://plot.ly/~pravj/51/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; title=&#34;When does India shops?&#34; style=&#34;display: block; text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://plot.ly/~pravj/51.png&#34; alt=&#34;When does India shops?&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;width: 600px;&#34;  width=&#34;600&#34; onerror=&#34;this.onerror=null;this.src=&#39;https://plot.ly/404.png&#39;;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;script data-plotly=&#34;pravj:51&#34;  src=&#34;https://plot.ly/embed.js&#34; async&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can see that there are two concerted segments. One from 09:00 AM to 05:00 PM in the evening and the other is from 06:00 PM to midnight. Not many orders are there during the &lt;em&gt;bed time&lt;/em&gt;, after midnight till the dawn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The morning peak is around 10:00 AM, which is near the usual opening hours of &lt;em&gt;Myntra&amp;rsquo;s big discount sales&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Returned Orders&lt;/em&gt; are present throughout the days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The presence of orders at every possible time of day shows the ease in the life of people using &amp;lsquo;online shopping&amp;rsquo;. You have got a need and there are platforms to fulfill that. Otherwise, why would someone order at 02:00 AM in the morning?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Myntra&lt;/em&gt; also runs a &lt;em&gt;same day delivery&lt;/em&gt; program where they ship your order in 24 hours, across the country. And in our dataset, a significant number of such orders were placed after midnight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;from-where-does-india-shops&#34;&gt;From where does India shops?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div id=&#39;customer-map&#39; style=&#34;height:400px;&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a clustered map of places in the country, that I found as &lt;em&gt;final destinations&lt;/em&gt; of &lt;em&gt;completed orders&lt;/em&gt;. This means that the map ignores the number of orders at a place, it just represents the &lt;em&gt;geographic distribution&lt;/em&gt; of the orders. Also, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t count a locality multiple times. For example, &lt;em&gt;Agartala&lt;/em&gt; has 2-3 different final destinations but they are clustered to a single place/centre, &lt;em&gt;Agartala COD Centre 3&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was magnificent to see this map when I plotted it first time. Not because my program worked, but to see the markers in extreme areas of the country, especially in the &lt;em&gt;Northeast India&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s good to see that almost every region of the country is here. There are 432 different places in here. You are free to zoom in and check out your region, if available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After seeing this big coverage I would say, they can expand easily to &lt;em&gt;Bangladesh&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have used &lt;em&gt;Google&amp;rsquo;s Geocoding API&lt;/em&gt; to convert a place name to its coordinates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-long-does-it-take-to-deliver-your-order&#34;&gt;How long does it take to deliver your order?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://plot.ly/~pravj648/16/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; title=&#34;How long does it take to deliver your order?&#34; style=&#34;display: block; text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://plot.ly/~pravj648/16.png&#34; alt=&#34;How long does it take to deliver your order?&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;width: 600px;&#34;  width=&#34;600&#34; onerror=&#34;this.onerror=null;this.src=&#39;https://plot.ly/404.png&#39;;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;script data-plotly=&#34;pravj648:16&#34;  src=&#34;https://plot.ly/embed.js&#34; async&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you live in north India or near(&lt;em&gt;measured in terms of direct road connectivity&lt;/em&gt;) the warehouses of &lt;em&gt;Myntra&lt;/em&gt;, you &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; have your package in 24 hours. In the dataset, many orders from Nation Capital Region, Jaipur and Bangalore have delivered in the same day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Otherwise, majority of the orders takes 3 to 4 days across the country, except the &lt;em&gt;North East&lt;/em&gt;(Guwahati, Imphal) and &lt;em&gt;West Coast&lt;/em&gt;(Mumbai Parel, Antop Hill) region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have calculated the delivery delay by subtracting the time of order being placed from the &lt;em&gt;last event time&lt;/em&gt; in the events timeline of a &lt;em&gt;complete order&lt;/em&gt;. The timeline consists of all the sub-details like &lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;Order is placed&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;Order is packed&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;In transit&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;Arrived at delivery center&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;Order out for delivery&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;Delivered&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt; etc. Which is &lt;em&gt;error prone&lt;/em&gt; because they seems to update some order after awhile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the &lt;em&gt;tail&lt;/em&gt; of the curve, the delay in some cases seems to be caused by customers actually, some reason were &lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;CID - COD(cash on delivery) AMOUNT NOT READY&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt;, &amp;lsquo;&lt;em&gt;Consignee Out Of Station; Shipment un-delivered&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;&lt;em&gt;Undelivered due to - Consignee Residence Closed&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rsquo; etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;shared-logistics&#34;&gt;Shared Logistics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://plot.ly/~pravj648/145/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; title=&#34;Shared Logistics&#34; style=&#34;display: block; text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://plot.ly/~pravj648/145.png&#34; alt=&#34;Shared Logistics&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;width: 1258px;&#34;  width=&#34;1258&#34; onerror=&#34;this.onerror=null;this.src=&#39;https://plot.ly/404.png&#39;;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;script data-plotly=&#34;pravj648:145&#34;  src=&#34;https://plot.ly/embed.js&#34; async&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having a great logistics service is a key point for online shops. Both &lt;em&gt;Myntra&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Flipkart&lt;/em&gt; have their own such services named &lt;em&gt;Myntra Logistics&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;EKart Logistics&lt;/em&gt; respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To deliver products out of their range or to overcome the heavy demand during &lt;em&gt;big discount sales&lt;/em&gt;, they ship the products with third party logistic providers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the dataset you can see that majority of the orders have been shipped by &lt;em&gt;Myntra Logistics&lt;/em&gt; itself, and then by &lt;em&gt;EKart&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Delhivery&lt;/em&gt; is an emerging logistic solution provider in the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we can see the regions in which &lt;em&gt;FedEx&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;DTDC&lt;/em&gt; were used for delivery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://plot.ly/~pravj648/159/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; title=&#34;Outsourced Logistic Partner Network&#34; style=&#34;display: block; text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://plot.ly/~pravj648/159.png&#34; alt=&#34;Outsourced Logistic Partner Network&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;width: 1258px;&#34;  width=&#34;1258&#34; onerror=&#34;this.onerror=null;this.src=&#39;https://plot.ly/404.png&#39;;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;script data-plotly=&#34;pravj648:159&#34;  src=&#34;https://plot.ly/embed.js&#34; async&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;end-of-reason-sale-purchase-behavior&#34;&gt;&amp;lsquo;End of Reason Sale&amp;rsquo; Purchase Behavior&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;End of Reason Sale&amp;rsquo; (&lt;em&gt;EORS&lt;/em&gt;) from 18-19 July was one of the biggest sales by &lt;em&gt;Myntra&lt;/em&gt; in the year 2015. It was after when their previous sale faced criticism because of &lt;a href=&#34;http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/tech/tech-news/After-botching-up-sale-Myntra-apologizes-to-users/articleshow/47528824.cms&#34;&gt;technical glitches&lt;/a&gt; in May 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;EORS&lt;/em&gt; started on 18th July from 08:00 AM. Here is a heatmap of order from dataset ranging from 17th July to 20th July.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://plot.ly/~pravj648/166/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; title=&#34;EORS Purchase Behavior&#34; style=&#34;display: block; text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://plot.ly/~pravj648/166.png&#34; alt=&#34;EORS Purchase Behavior&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;width: 1258px;&#34;  width=&#34;1258&#34; onerror=&#34;this.onerror=null;this.src=&#39;https://plot.ly/404.png&#39;;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;script data-plotly=&#34;pravj648:166&#34;  src=&#34;https://plot.ly/embed.js&#34; async&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can see a pattern similar to the &lt;em&gt;sale days&lt;/em&gt; for 20th July, which supports the notion that &lt;em&gt;EORS&lt;/em&gt; was &lt;a href=&#34;http://webcache.googleusercontent.com/search?q=cache:DuSB-kY2Il4J:https://batch.com/insights/push/ey8v28jv00zd+&amp;amp;cd=7&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;ct=clnk&amp;amp;gl=in&#34;&gt;extended after its official period&lt;/a&gt; for some styles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;brands-on-the-platform&#34;&gt;Brands on the platform&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Myntra&lt;/em&gt; being an online shopping service mainly, also &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rediff.com/business/report/myntra-to-have-usd-100-mn-in-house-brands/20150805.htm&#34;&gt;owns in-house fashion brands&lt;/a&gt; like Roadster, Dressberry, Anouk (for women), Mast &amp;amp; Harbour, Kook N Keech, Yellow Kite (for kids) and Invictus etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is an &lt;em&gt;approx&lt;/em&gt; gender segmentation of brands(top 50 in the dataset) on the platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://plot.ly/~pravj648/105/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; title=&#34;Gender Segmentation of brands&#34; style=&#34;display: block; text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://plot.ly/~pravj648/105.png&#34; alt=&#34;Gender Segmentation of brands&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;width: 600px;&#34;  width=&#34;600&#34; onerror=&#34;this.onerror=null;this.src=&#39;https://plot.ly/404.png&#39;;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;script data-plotly=&#34;pravj648:105&#34;  src=&#34;https://plot.ly/embed.js&#34; async&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;do-small-shopkeepers-purchase-online-to-sell-in-their-locality&#34;&gt;Do small shopkeepers purchase online to sell in their locality?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do you generally purchase online? Whatever it&amp;rsquo;s, but you don&amp;rsquo;t actually buy 3 shirts of the same type, do you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is something I found suspicious when I was looking in the dataset for orders having a lot of products in one shipment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/bulk-order.png&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Does small shopkeepers purchase from Myntra to sell in their locality?&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This picture shows products in a shipment which contains shoes only, of similar types.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although it&amp;rsquo;s exactly how the selling process works, you buy from a person and sell to someone else. But in this case, it seems weird to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought &amp;lsquo;online shopping services&amp;rsquo; are just adjacent node to us on the &lt;em&gt;Internet Services Graph&lt;/em&gt; and this is how people use it. This indicates towards the existence of a community which is still away from the Internet, its benefits and is being cheated. Cheating in the sense that shopkeepers may buy from online services during sales and then sell them at relatively high prices to local customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;inference&#34;&gt;Inference&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I have said that I won&amp;rsquo;t conclude results from this data, but I guess we can&amp;rsquo;t deny some facts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;Online Shopping&amp;rsquo; is a perk that the boom on Internet and Startups has given to the country. It&amp;rsquo;s shaping the economy by creating a variety of employments. Still a lot of people are yet to go through this makeover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the number of Internet users is growing in the country, we can expect more good to happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;probable-fix&#34;&gt;Probable Fix&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think a simple solution can be employed here to avoid intruders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To ask for the associated &lt;em&gt;mobile number&lt;/em&gt; while checking details of an order, if the user is not logged in. One can guess the &lt;em&gt;unique id&lt;/em&gt; for orders but not the &lt;em&gt;mobile number&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;disclaimer&#34;&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is going to be a little contradictory. According to Oxford Dictionary, &lt;em&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/em&gt; means &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;A statement that denies something, especially responsibility&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won&amp;rsquo;t do that. This time again, I&amp;rsquo;m aware that such collection of data is a wrong act in &lt;em&gt;Internet terms&lt;/em&gt;. But I can&amp;rsquo;t control myself when I get such an idea and some questions that can only be solved by visualizing the data, referring to &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anscombe%27s_quartet&#34;&gt;Anscombe&amp;rsquo;s quartet&lt;/a&gt;. I just wish I&amp;rsquo;m not getting prosecuted for this. The dataset doesn&amp;rsquo;t contain any private information(&lt;em&gt;name, mobile number, home address&lt;/em&gt;) of someone, &lt;em&gt;it&amp;rsquo;s not at all available.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/blitz.engine&#34;&gt;Engine&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Station&lt;/em&gt;? I have decided not to open source the &lt;em&gt;Station&lt;/em&gt;, which was used to collect the data. Almost all programs I have used to &lt;em&gt;analyse&lt;/em&gt; the data are available at &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/Fuel&#34;&gt;Fuel&lt;/a&gt;, without the actual data I have collected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are reading this, you have passed my experiment. Let me gift you a free &lt;b&gt;Happy New Year&lt;/b&gt; wish.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jump in to ride all the Bangalore taxis, at once</title>
      <link>http://pravj.github.io/blog/bangalore-taxis/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pravj.github.io/blog/bangalore-taxis/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;All right, just imagine that you have popcorn with you, because I know that you don&amp;rsquo;t have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to do this report when I was in Bangalore this summer, &lt;em&gt;Sillicon Valley of India&lt;/em&gt;. You can observe a gob of information flowing through in such metropolitan population. People ordering/delivering meal, groceries or literally everything by online orders, people booking a vehicle and riding in no time, people booking a seat for dinner/movie and many more thing to generate the logs. Which is fascinating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One day while riding a cab, I got this plan to go into the rectangle map the app was showing, and run around. Just like what &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oKCIMX2dsEc&#34;&gt;Joey did in an episode of Friends&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To execute this all, I had to collect the relavent information and work on the possible outcomes of the collected information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here in this post I have written the procedure I followed, things I have feared of, interesting results I saw and count of tea cups I have sipped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-brick-wall&#34;&gt;The brick wall&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A little more theory and then we will get right to the practicals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While setting up the collection infrastucture, I realised that I might be under the &lt;em&gt;terms and services&lt;/em&gt; monster. This suspicion helped me lading in the depression zone where I wasn&amp;rsquo;t sure if the work I have done so far was worth doing or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought about asking the respective organization for a permission but I was too afraid to hear a negative reply. So I went ahead and ignored this. Because this report does not publicize any private property like vehicle numbers, mobile numbers and all. Even I wasn&amp;rsquo;t able to access such private properties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The major reason was, I have already bunked too many classes for this, so terminating the work wasn&amp;rsquo;t an option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m aware that it&amp;rsquo;s a wrong act but I couldn&amp;rsquo;t stop the &lt;em&gt;David McCandless&lt;/em&gt; inside me from doing this. I hope I&amp;rsquo;m not getting sued for this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This report is based on the data from a particular taxi service in a single day&amp;rsquo;s time span, so it may be a little baised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;information-retrieval&#34;&gt;Information Retrieval&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Collecting the right information was the foundation for the whole game. Possibility of getting blocked was also there, once you come under the &lt;em&gt;Night&amp;rsquo;s watch&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The task reduces to finding &lt;em&gt;how many taxis are there in the city&lt;/em&gt; (at a time), &lt;em&gt;where they are&lt;/em&gt; and then keep doing this all the day &lt;em&gt;without getting caught&lt;/em&gt;. Easy Peasy?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I came up with the solution to find places in the city which are equally seperated and then drawing circles on those points would cover the entire city. A fake &lt;em&gt;cab search request&lt;/em&gt; would return us the status of cabs around that place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For that I planned to start from the center of the city, iterate this on adjacent places using a &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Finite-state_machine&#34;&gt;Finite State Machine&lt;/a&gt; to stay aware of the ending state (when we are done with all such place-combinations) and state changes (when we are out of the city&amp;rsquo;s boundary in a particular direction).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While writing the FSM, I found an efficient alternative to iterate over all the equally separated places which comes under the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minimum_bounding_rectangle&#34;&gt;Minimum Bounding Rectangle&lt;/a&gt; of Bangalore, and check if the cab service is available in that area or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Equally spacing those spots minimizes the total number of requests made, which descreases the chances of getting blocked, &lt;em&gt;if there is such service on the other side&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/point-net.png&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Equally separated places&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once all those places were spotted, I made a &lt;em&gt;cab search request&lt;/em&gt; on all those spots every 15 minutes. I think it&amp;rsquo;s a bit more time than the &lt;em&gt;average trip duration&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later I realised a mistake that I have forgot to count the time making requests to all the places, so the separation went up to almost 19 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I continuously pumped all those responses to a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iron.io/mq/&#34;&gt;IronMQ&lt;/a&gt; powered message queue and then imported all the data into a local &lt;a href=&#34;http://rethinkdb.com/&#34;&gt;RethinkDB&lt;/a&gt; instance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One should try not to hit the source at a constant timeperiod (like 15 minutes in this case), because that&amp;rsquo;s the basic heuristic for smart &lt;em&gt;bot detection&lt;/em&gt; systems. I had to do that because it was needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;service-availability&#34;&gt;Service Availability&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;em&gt;Minimum Bounding Rectangle&lt;/em&gt;, I found a total of 272 spots but only 96 of them have the cab service available. The distance between adjacent places is 2 Mile (3.2186 KM.), which is almost same as the equivalent area we see while booking a cab on mobile applications (on default zoom level).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&#39;availability-map&#39; style=&#34;height:400px;&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although this is biased because it represent only a single day of activity but it gives us a little overview of the situation. I&amp;rsquo;m not that familier with the places in the bangalore but I found an interesting thing, maybe a native resident can confirm this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See those two circles at the top of the rectangle, they are too far from the main localities but we have the service there. Those circles contains places like &lt;em&gt;Rajanukunte&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Doddajala&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Chikkajala&lt;/em&gt; etc. On googling their name, you will get comparatively more listings about property/real-estate business compared to other areas in the city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s like the scenario we had with &lt;em&gt;Delhi - Gurgaon&lt;/em&gt; some time back, those places are under &lt;em&gt;Industrialization&lt;/em&gt;. Which makes it a good reason to have the taxi services availability, no matter some famous places around the city doesn&amp;rsquo;t have this cab service, like the &lt;em&gt;Bannerghatta National Park&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;guardians-vehicles&#34;&gt;Guardians (Vehicles)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the day, the system spotted a total of 897 different cabs, with 4 different types.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;RethinkDB query&lt;/em&gt; to count different type of cabs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;r.db(&#39;taxis&#39;).table(&#39;datacenter&#39;)
	.filter({available: true})
	.pluck(&#39;type&#39;, &#39;cab_id&#39;)
	.distinct()
	.group(&#39;type&#39;)
	.count()
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;row&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;col s12 m6 l3 center-align&#34; style=&#34;color:#DDD;background:#00648C;&#34;&gt;
      &lt;h4&gt;#Hatchback 525&lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;col s12 m6 l3 center-align&#34; style=&#34;color:#DDD;background:#10698C;&#34;&gt;
      &lt;h4&gt;#Sedan 324&lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;col s12 m6 l3 center-align&#34; style=&#34;color:#DDD;background:#4F7B8C;&#34;&gt;
      &lt;h4&gt;#Nano 46&lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;col s12 m6 l3 center-align&#34; style=&#34;color:#DDD;background:#7497A5;&#34;&gt;
      &lt;h4&gt;#SUV 2&lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cab-availability-according-to-time&#34;&gt;Cab Availability (according to time)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do you think about the number of cabs available at 8:30 AM and 8:30 PM? You will see that the number is more in the morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a theory, &lt;em&gt;Utilitarianism&lt;/em&gt;. Which states that everyone wants to maximize their utility. Take the example of E-commerce. Between so many brands, sellers and customers, everyone wants to increase their benefits. For e-sellers, scheduling an online sell is just like a game of chess. Each team want to win it. (Quoted by a good person)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is how the cab availability distribution over time looks like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/distribution.png&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Cab availability distribution over time&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it goes like, the probability of a taxi being hired is high during the morning when people are going to the office/college, then it decreases during the noon-time, increases again during the 4 PM - 6 PM window when people are going back home or going out for their evening gig, and decreses in the night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is how drivers play their part as per &lt;em&gt;Utilitarianism&lt;/em&gt;, which reflects in the number of available taxis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;rise-of-the-guardians-vehicles&#34;&gt;Rise of the Guardians (Vehicles)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the responses I got for the cab search requests, there was a field representing a timestamp, constant for a particular cab. Initially when I saw that, I thought it&amp;rsquo;s the last time a cab was booked but it wasn&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5 out of the 897 total cabs have that field equal to 1, which translates to January 1, 1970. This indicates that initially the field wasn&amp;rsquo;t part of their architecture, but later they adopted it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The uniqueness and time range of all those fields strongly supports that it was the time when a cab got associated with the organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/cab-timeline.png&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Cab timeline&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Horizontal scale for this graph is cropped because almost 85+ % events belongs to the year 2015 itself. Which seems a bit weird, but it&amp;rsquo;s what it&amp;rsquo;s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cabs-around-the-city-throughout-the-day&#34;&gt;Cabs around the city throughout the day&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div id=&#39;map&#39; style=&#34;height:400px;&#34;&gt;
    &lt;span id=&#39;info&#39; class=&#39;info&#39; style=&#39;padding:10px;background:#fff;position:relative;top:17px;right:-50px;z-index:100;&#39;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This particular map represents the geographic view of the &lt;em&gt;cab availability&lt;/em&gt; (according to time) diagram. Where total cabs at a time are distributed accross the city according to their actual positions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now if you are thinking about the places where most of the cabs are, I have created another map for that, scroll down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cab-availability-index&#34;&gt;Cab Availability Index&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This map is somewhat inspired from the Housing&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://housing.com/blog/2013/11/14/launching-child-friendliness-index-heat-maps/&#34;&gt;Child Friendly Index&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It uses those equally seperated circles to count total cabs in them throughout the day, and uses the relative percentage as the opacity of each circle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;RethinkDB query&lt;/em&gt; that counts the cabs which are in a 2 mile circle centered at &amp;lsquo;centerPoint&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;r.db(&#39;taxis&#39;).table(&#39;datacenter&#39;)
	.filter({available: true})
	.pluck(&#39;cab_lat&#39;, &#39;cab_lng&#39;)
	.distinct()
	.map(function(instance) {
		return r.circle(centerPoint, 2, {unit: &#39;mi&#39;})
			.includes(r.point(instance(&#39;cab_lat&#39;), instance(&#39;cab_lat&#39;)))
	})
	.count(true)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;div id=&#39;dmap&#39; style=&#39;height:400px;&#39;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neighbourhoods having maximum availability index are mostly in the &lt;em&gt;northern-western&lt;/em&gt; and a little &lt;em&gt;central&lt;/em&gt; part of the bangalore. Which consists of some big educational institutes as &lt;em&gt;Indian Institute of Science&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Bangalore University&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;R.V. College of Engineering&lt;/em&gt;, some famous tourist spots as &lt;em&gt;Lalbagh Botanical Garden&lt;/em&gt; to contribute to the higher availability density.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along with that, reports shows that &lt;em&gt;northern-western&lt;/em&gt; bangalore has maximum population density in the city. Check out these images (&lt;a href=&#34;http://wgbis.ces.iisc.ernet.in/biodiversity/pubs/ETR/ETR55/Population%20Density.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;latest&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://wgbis.ces.iisc.ernet.in/biodiversity/pubs/ces_tr/TR118_SPoonancha/Index1_clip_image002_0000.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;old&lt;/a&gt;) from &lt;em&gt;Centre for Ecological Sciences, IISc&lt;/em&gt; for the reference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cab-that-travelled-the-most&#34;&gt;Cab that travelled the most&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I have told you that initially I&amp;rsquo;d misread a timestamp field as the time when a cab was last hired. Writing a precise (almost) algorithm to find the path travelled by cab using current/past location and the last booking time would have been easy that way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the currecnt implementation, I have used the locations between adjacent appearances of a cab to find the approximate distance travelled by the vehicle. It assumes that the cab travelled from position A to position B despite being sufficient time difference between both appearances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;RethinkDB query&lt;/em&gt; that collects the chronological appearances of each taxi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;r.db(&#39;taxis&#39;).table(&#39;datacenter&#39;)
	.filter({available: true})
	.without(&#39;id&#39;, &#39;place_lat&#39;, &#39;place_lng&#39;, &#39;duration&#39;, &#39;distance&#39;)
	.group(&#39;cab_id&#39;)
	.pluck(&#39;cab_lat&#39;, &#39;cab_lng&#39;, &#39;index&#39;, &#39;timestamp&#39;)
	.orderBy(&#39;index&#39;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To watch the jounrney &lt;em&gt;time-lapse&lt;/em&gt; of the cab who travelled the most, press the &lt;em&gt;play button&lt;/em&gt; below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&#39;cmap&#39; style=&#39;height:400px;&#39;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style=&#39;width:60px;margin: 0 auto;&#39;&gt;
    &lt;h2 id=&#34;replay-btn&#34; style=&#39;position:relative;top:-100px;padding-left:15px;color:#343434;background-color:rgba(255, 255, 255, 0.8);width:60px;height:50px;cursor:pointer;&#39;&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#39;ion-play&#39;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;is-this-all-fake-just-like-uber-illusion&#34;&gt;Is this all fake, just like Uber illusion?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you remember those &lt;em&gt;phantom car&lt;/em&gt; stories of Uber?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a research which revealed that Uber shows a mirage of tiny black cabs moving around you, when you do a cab search. Just to convince you that a cab is there for you. Study concluded that the cab network you see around, is not real-time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to analyse the &lt;em&gt;traffic status&lt;/em&gt; using the response data I had. My objective was to find the regression in the &lt;em&gt;cab response time&lt;/em&gt; (time taken by a cab to reach you) and &lt;em&gt;time of the day&lt;/em&gt;. Because the sixth sense says that the &lt;em&gt;cab response time&lt;/em&gt; should be high when there is &lt;em&gt;high traffic&lt;/em&gt; in some areas of the city, likely in those peek hours (morning and evening time).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;cab response time&lt;/em&gt; seems to be dependant on the distance only, which looks like a &lt;em&gt;step function&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/restime.png&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Cab Response Time&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I realised that there wasn&amp;rsquo;t any fluctuation in the &lt;em&gt;response time&lt;/em&gt;, it was same for a particular distance between the cab and the user (simulated), all the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which implies that similar to Uber, this cab network isn&amp;rsquo;t real-time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A nice explanation of the &lt;em&gt;phantom cars&lt;/em&gt; is available &lt;a href=&#34;http://motherboard.vice.com/read/Ubers-phantom-cabs?update&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;people-don-t-solve-a-problem-until-they-get-one&#34;&gt;People don&amp;rsquo;t solve a problem until they get one&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This simulated user interaction is wrong to the system. Can be easily converted into a &lt;em&gt;service denial&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my case, I was changing the user(simulated) location frequently, so fast that a human can&amp;rsquo;t reach there in a fraction of second (traversing whole Bangalore in 3 minutes).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the service allows a user to book a cab for someone else (who is far away from where the real user is), the monitoring system should take care of the conversion rates. Someone trying to book a cab for someone else this fast, then not booking a single cab, and then repeating this every 15 minute all the day is a plain pattern to detect. Which should be detected. I hope somebody will fix this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s it, get out of the cab now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have decided not to release the collected data and code for the data retrieval. Everything else including the data processing part can be found at &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj&#34;&gt;pravj/bangalore-taxis&lt;/a&gt; repository. Thanks to &lt;em&gt;RethinkDB&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Mapbox&lt;/em&gt;, you guys are really amazing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script src=&#39;{{http://localhost:4000}}/public/lib/taxis.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>