<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Image on hack(pravj)</title>
    <link>http://pravj.github.io/tags/image/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Image on hack(pravj)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://pravj.github.io/tags/image/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Holy Aesthete : painting a virtual wall</title>
      <link>http://pravj.github.io/blog/virtual-wall/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pravj.github.io/blog/virtual-wall/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, it&amp;rsquo;s the day of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holi&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Holi&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, the festival of colors in India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, it was the end of our midterm exams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such Time. Much Rhyme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/wall.jpg&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Virtual Wall&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the last minutes, I decided to stop writing after matching an answer with the person sitting next to me. I was all set to run outside the hall and smell the &lt;em&gt;woot! no more exams left&lt;/em&gt; scent in the air.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have one strange habit of drawing random things in my notebook, ranging from literally anything to &lt;em&gt;K-nearest&lt;/em&gt; girls. All the drawings are terrible though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I started utilizing rest of the time by drawing in the backside of exam paper. After a little journey to some wonderland, I had this weird sounding thought in my mind, &lt;em&gt;to write something that simulates a painted wall.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then the exam ended, we left the hall, enjoyed the &lt;em&gt;Holi&lt;/em&gt; all day with batchmates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That &lt;em&gt;weird thought&lt;/em&gt; was still there in my mind, deep somewhere. I decided to give it a shout next morning. And you never need a &lt;em&gt;halcion&lt;/em&gt; after ~40 hours of &lt;em&gt;not sleeping&lt;/em&gt; and doing &lt;em&gt;not so successful&lt;/em&gt; attempt of &lt;em&gt;cram&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I started justifying that thought, picked up &lt;em&gt;golang&lt;/em&gt; for it and created a directory, &lt;em&gt;~/go/src/github/pravj/wall&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wait! let&amp;rsquo;s talk over. Have you ever painted a wall before?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well! I have. If not, you must have seen people doing it. &lt;em&gt;What happens when you start with the brush?&lt;/em&gt; Something like this picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/wall-paint.jpg&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Wall Paint&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here in the picture, the part painted by each color doesn&amp;rsquo;t have a specific shape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, in my attempt, I assumed that there exists a central rectangular shape in color block generated by each brush swipe. And the final block also contains some &lt;em&gt;noise&lt;/em&gt; around that rectangle, resulting in the final irregular shape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started with those rectangles, equally spaced with each other. The space was for the noise interference I was planning. Result was this, fix colored image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/first-stage.jpg&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;First Stage&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I added the &lt;em&gt;noise&lt;/em&gt; on each rectangle. For this, instead of fix sized rectangle. I added some random lengthy stripes around the block, colored same as the block. The result was this image, fixed color again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/second-stage.jpg&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Second Stage&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After applying random colors to each block, it generates image similar to the one given below. The ideal thing to do would be, coloring each block in a way that it&amp;rsquo;s different from its surrounding block color. Something like the classical &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Four_color_theorem&#34;&gt;Four Color Theorem&lt;/a&gt;, variant of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constraint_satisfaction_problem&#34;&gt;Constraint satisfaction problem&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/third-stage.jpg&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Third Stage&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in this case, the probability of the ideal case violation is &lt;em&gt;lilliputian&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Precisely, for a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cross&#34;&gt;slanted saltire(cross)&lt;/a&gt; shape divided in five squares, the probability of central square having same color as any surrounding square will be around 2 in 10 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/probability.png&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Probability&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let&amp;rsquo;s ignore it like a pigeon closing its eyes in front of a venerer cat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I was concerned about the equally spaced color blocks. Things were still not in the way I wanted them to be. It looked like there is a pattern inside. As systems having more entropy are more stable and &lt;em&gt;beautiful&lt;/em&gt;. I decided to put color blocks at random places in the image, result was this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/fourth-stage.jpg&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Fourth Stage&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After this all, the central rectangle that I have assumed for the structure, was clearly visible in the block. To conceal that, I formatted the block such that the &lt;em&gt;noise&lt;/em&gt; along the block-width depends on the index of the row in block matrix. Now, it was better than the last one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://pravj.github.io/images/final-stage.jpg&#34;&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Final Stage&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what I have thought about. A wall painted by some children in their tiffin time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may sound like a dumb thing to work on, it&amp;rsquo;s actually. It&amp;rsquo;s just a combination of some &lt;em&gt;for&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;if-else&lt;/em&gt; loops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is more than just dumb, now I feel relieved as I made it real what I have thought about, something like Aaron has said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;behind-the-scene&#34;&gt;Behind the scene&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;While doing this, I painted one of my room wall, &lt;em&gt;hypothetically&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You must have got the idea behind this post&amp;rsquo;s heading. &lt;em&gt;The Holi Fever&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Today, my room&amp;rsquo;s light is not working and I wrote this in the screen light.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source Code : &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pravj/virtual-wall&#34;&gt;virtual-wall&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>