<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>R on hack(pravj)</title>
    <link>https://hackpravj.com/tags/r/</link>
    <description>Recent content in R on hack(pravj)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://hackpravj.com/tags/r/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Jump in to ride all the Bangalore taxis, at once</title>
      <link>https://hackpravj.com/blog/bangalore-taxis/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hackpravj.com/blog/bangalore-taxis/</guid>
      <description>All right, just imagine that you have popcorn with you, because I know that you don&amp;rsquo;t have.
I decided to do this report when I was in Bangalore this summer, Sillicon Valley of India. You can observe a gob of information flowing through in such metropolitan population. People ordering/delivering meal, groceries or literally everything by online orders, people booking a vehicle and riding in no time, people booking a seat for dinner/movie and many more thing to generate the logs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open Source Presence Infographic of Indian Startups</title>
      <link>https://hackpravj.com/blog/open-source-presence-infographic/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hackpravj.com/blog/open-source-presence-infographic/</guid>
      <description>Technically speaking, organizations used in this report are no more only a startup now, but I hope you people won&amp;rsquo;t mind this and aren&amp;rsquo;t gonna launch a drone on me.
Abstract I think, something is clear from the name itself, is it? Well! it should.
This report tries to plot all the involved organizations on the Open-Source portal. It tries to tell that, in the race to achieve their goals, what different organizations are doing there, for/in the community.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Post-mortem of an Internet Accident</title>
      <link>https://hackpravj.com/blog/post-mortem-of-an-internet-accident/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hackpravj.com/blog/post-mortem-of-an-internet-accident/</guid>
      <description>Hi scout, thanks for visiting this node of the Holy Internet Graph; Before the combination Internet Accident confuse you, let me decode its meaning in the context of this post.
 Encounter with something on an edge node of the Holy Internet.
 So this post is all about my attempt to solve a question, I saw on Quora.
 What good known projects on GitHub uses the largest number of programming languages?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>