<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Github on hack(pravj)</title>
    <link>https://hackpravj.com/tags/github/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Github on hack(pravj)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://hackpravj.com/tags/github/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Using GitHub to build a missing GitHub feature</title>
      <link>https://hackpravj.com/blog/building-missing-github-feature/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hackpravj.com/blog/building-missing-github-feature/</guid>
      <description>After the Microsoft acquisition, GitHub has been on a roller coaster ride. It has been winning the developer community’s affinity by launching a series of offerings, one after another, starting from the free private repositories to the GitHub Sponsors program.
Still, there are unmatched expectations that users have from the hub of open-source. This guide is about one such expectation, a feature that is missing from GitHub and my product-first approach to building that as a side-project.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Information Dynamics on the GitHub Network</title>
      <link>https://hackpravj.com/blog/information-dynamics-on-github/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hackpravj.com/blog/information-dynamics-on-github/</guid>
      <description>Exploring the &amp;ldquo;social coding&amp;rdquo; behavior.
 Social groups have a system of behaviors occurring within the group or between groups, called “Group dynamics”. GitHub, being a social coding network, is the host to millions of developers and software projects. This report will use openly available data to unveil such behaviors in an intellectual-focused social network.
Social Coding The growth of GitHub has been significantly different from other OSS communities such as Alioth, Freecode, and Savannah.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introducing Penticons : The Hash Game</title>
      <link>https://hackpravj.com/blog/penticons-the-hash-game/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hackpravj.com/blog/penticons-the-hash-game/</guid>
      <description>Jennifer Lawrence fan, huh? It was The Hash Game by the way. Still in? Kewl.
What&amp;rsquo;s the buzz all about? Unfortunately, there is no buzz. This post is about development of Penticons.
Penticons. What? Remember those egg shaped profile pictures on Twitter? They are automaticaly linked to your profile, when you forget to upload your custom profile picture.
Different services uses different default profile pictures. For example, Quora uses this image of their co-founder Charlie Cheever.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open Source Presence Infographic of Indian Startups</title>
      <link>https://hackpravj.com/blog/open-source-presence-infographic/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hackpravj.com/blog/open-source-presence-infographic/</guid>
      <description>Technically speaking, organizations used in this report are no more only a startup now, but I hope you people won&amp;rsquo;t mind this and aren&amp;rsquo;t gonna launch a drone on me.
Abstract I think, something is clear from the name itself, is it? Well! it should.
This report tries to plot all the involved organizations on the Open-Source portal. It tries to tell that, in the race to achieve their goals, what different organizations are doing there, for/in the community.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The git-game Write-up</title>
      <link>https://hackpravj.com/blog/the-git-game-writeup/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hackpravj.com/blog/the-git-game-writeup/</guid>
      <description>Spoiler Alert
You should go and check this out, git-game.
It&amp;rsquo;s a nice little complete-a-task-and-upgrade-level type of game layered on top of Git.
 It is a terminal game designed to test your knowledge of git commands. Each level in the game is a task to perform on this repo. Once you perform that task, you will be given your next task. There are a total of ten levels, each one harder than last!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Post-mortem of an Internet Accident</title>
      <link>https://hackpravj.com/blog/post-mortem-of-an-internet-accident/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hackpravj.com/blog/post-mortem-of-an-internet-accident/</guid>
      <description>Hi scout, thanks for visiting this node of the Holy Internet Graph; Before the combination Internet Accident confuse you, let me decode its meaning in the context of this post.
 Encounter with something on an edge node of the Holy Internet.
 So this post is all about my attempt to solve a question, I saw on Quora.
 What good known projects on GitHub uses the largest number of programming languages?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>geopattern : going on the Go path</title>
      <link>https://hackpravj.com/blog/going-on-the-go-path/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hackpravj.com/blog/going-on-the-go-path/</guid>
      <description>You should have a look at geopattern, if you haven&amp;rsquo;t yet.
 What&amp;rsquo;s the buzz all about? This blog post is about development of geopattern library in golang.
What do you think about this my favorite colored concentric circle pattern?
 Concentric Circle Pattern  geopattern. What? Umm, actually I don&amp;rsquo;t know exactly why the name is geopattern but I know what it is.
It is a golang library that generates pretty image patterns.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>