<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>React on hack(pravj)</title>
    <link>https://pravj.github.io/tags/react/</link>
    <description>Recent content in React on hack(pravj)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2015 15:50:49 +0300</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://pravj.github.io/tags/react/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 10 - Surveyman</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/surveyman-week10/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2015 15:50:49 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/surveyman-week10/</guid>
      <description>After a fun and productive two weeks at home, I have now rejoined office back in Kuwait. As all good things in life, the vacation has come to an end and it&amp;rsquo;s now time to head back to the usual humdrum of 9 to 5. What also didn&amp;rsquo;t help was the fact that since most of easy (low hanging fruits, if you will) features had already been built, I had no option but to start work on the feature which I most dreaded - implementing sortable on blocks / questions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 9 - Surveyman</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/surveyman-week9/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2015 15:50:49 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/surveyman-week9/</guid>
      <description>This is my last week at home (India) and the fact that I had a pretty productive week shows that I&amp;rsquo;m ensconced within the comforts of my home. After the hectic last week which involved traveling, meeting relatives and getting documentation ready for the Visa interview this week was just me sitting at home working on this project without any distractions.
So there were three key features that I tackled this week, namely - TreeView, Option Lists and React transitions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 8 - Surveyman</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/surveyman-week8/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2015 15:50:49 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/surveyman-week8/</guid>
      <description>If you&amp;rsquo;ve read the previous blog post, you would be aware that I&amp;rsquo;m right now back to my home country on a vacation. This week has been quite hectic and filled with anxiety owing to the visa interview that I had scheduled during the start of the week. Since this was my first time appearing for a US Visa interview, I was quite in awe of how the smooth and planned the entire process was, especially compared to the other interview processes I&amp;rsquo;d been in (I&amp;rsquo;m looking at you Kuwait).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 7 - Surveyman</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/surveyman-week7/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jun 2015 15:50:49 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/surveyman-week7/</guid>
      <description>Guess what, I&amp;rsquo;m writing this blog post from my home in Delhi! I&amp;rsquo;ll be in India for full 2 weeks where apart from visiting my family, cousins and friends I&amp;rsquo;ll also be giving my visa interview - which is the main reason why I&amp;rsquo;ve taken a vacation.
As I had been traveling the progress this week has been rather minimal. Keeping the travel schedule in mind, I had kept the goal to be reasonable which was upgrading the react-surveyman project to use React-DnD&amp;rsquo;s latest 1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 6 - Surveyman</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/surveyman-week6/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2015 15:50:49 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/surveyman-week6/</guid>
      <description>So I started this week with the primary goal of re-writing my stores and migrating them to use Immutable collections. In the last week&amp;rsquo;s post, I laid out the motivation on why this is a good idea and how it will speed up the React application.
While the benefits were clear, I was still not sure on how I could implement and exploit the collections provided by Immutable to my advantage.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 5 - Surveyman</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/surveyman-week5/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 May 2015 15:50:49 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/surveyman-week5/</guid>
      <description>I signed off the last post mentioning that I&amp;rsquo;ll be integrating the React tags component into Surveyman which did not turn out to be difficult. As the API of the component was simple, it just meant adding the component and providing the necessary event handlers.
The suggestions are loaded as soon as a Question component is dropped, which after careful thought, sounds like a practical tradeoff. Suggestions are maintained as a set and whenever is new Option is added by the user, it gets appended to the set.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 4 - Surveyman</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/surveyman-week4/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 May 2015 15:50:49 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/surveyman-week4/</guid>
      <description>I closed last week&amp;rsquo;s update giving an indication that I started work on a standalone React component. After working on the component this week, I was finally able to finish it and publish it on NPM.
So before I go into what React-tag-input does, I&amp;rsquo;ll try and explain the motivation for building it. If you&amp;rsquo;ve been following closely, the primary way of building the survey in Surveyman is via Drag and Drop.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 3 - Surveyman</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/surveyman-week3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2015 15:50:49 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/surveyman-week3/</guid>
      <description>This update is coming in a bit late, especially after the week 1 and week 2 updates posted earlier. After progressing a bit on the initial setup and features I decided to take a week off Surveyman and instead wait for the GSOC results to arrive so that I could get feedback from Emma, my mentor for this project and see if I were on the right track.
Much to my delight I got selected in GSOC to work for Surveyman!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 2 - Surveyman</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/surveyman-week2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Apr 2015 06:58:24 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/surveyman-week2/</guid>
      <description>After the drop targets and drag sources were configured last week, this week my primary motive was to develop a better UI for adding Question types. After mulling over the UI a bit, I decided to replace the existing Javascript prompt with a modal which would allow text entry and multiple radio buttons / checkboxes to configure various parts of a Question type.
  Adding a Bootstrap Modal   UI  The key idea behind Surveyman is that by giving survey authors a way to write their surveys that steers them away from unnecessary ordering constraints, we can apply static analysis, randomization, and statistical dynamic analysis to locate survey errors and ensure the quality of responses.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 1 - Surveyman</title>
      <link>https://pravj.github.io/articles/surveyman-week1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Apr 2015 06:58:24 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pravj.github.io/articles/surveyman-week1/</guid>
      <description>Last week, I announced that I have applied for GSOC project called Surveyman as a part of which I&amp;rsquo;ll be building a React application that allows users to build a survey.
How will this be different from the countless other similar tools that exist? For the long answer, I&amp;rsquo;d advise you to read the paper but the short answer is that SurveyMan exposes a lightweight Domain Specific Language for designing and deploying surveys.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>