<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Open Source on hack(pravj)</title>
    <link>https://hackpravj.com/tags/open-source/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Open Source on hack(pravj)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://hackpravj.com/tags/open-source/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Contributing to the Go programming language</title>
      <link>https://hackpravj.com/blog/first-golang-contribution-experience/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hackpravj.com/blog/first-golang-contribution-experience/</guid>
      <description>This article describes my experience contributing the first commit to the Go programming language. It might be one small step for you, but it&amp;rsquo;s one giant leap for the gopher inside me.
 Along with my experience, I will outline the article as a (beginner&amp;rsquo;s) gopher&amp;rsquo;s guide for contributing to an open source project (the Go project in this case).
I have started learning Go in the late 2014 and I was lucky enough to receive a healthy appreciation from the community for my very first project in the language.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Information Dynamics on the GitHub Network</title>
      <link>https://hackpravj.com/blog/information-dynamics-on-github/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hackpravj.com/blog/information-dynamics-on-github/</guid>
      <description>Exploring the &amp;ldquo;social coding&amp;rdquo; behavior.
 Social groups have a system of behaviors occurring within the group or between groups, called “Group dynamics”. GitHub, being a social coding network, is the host to millions of developers and software projects. This report will use openly available data to unveil such behaviors in an intellectual-focused social network.
Social Coding The growth of GitHub has been significantly different from other OSS communities such as Alioth, Freecode, and Savannah.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open Source Presence Infographic of Indian Startups</title>
      <link>https://hackpravj.com/blog/open-source-presence-infographic/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hackpravj.com/blog/open-source-presence-infographic/</guid>
      <description>Technically speaking, organizations used in this report are no more only a startup now, but I hope you people won&amp;rsquo;t mind this and aren&amp;rsquo;t gonna launch a drone on me.
Abstract I think, something is clear from the name itself, is it? Well! it should.
This report tries to plot all the involved organizations on the Open-Source portal. It tries to tell that, in the race to achieve their goals, what different organizations are doing there, for/in the community.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>geopattern : going on the Go path</title>
      <link>https://hackpravj.com/blog/going-on-the-go-path/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hackpravj.com/blog/going-on-the-go-path/</guid>
      <description>You should have a look at geopattern, if you haven&amp;rsquo;t yet.
 What&amp;rsquo;s the buzz all about? This blog post is about development of geopattern library in golang.
What do you think about this my favorite colored concentric circle pattern?
 Concentric Circle Pattern  geopattern. What? Umm, actually I don&amp;rsquo;t know exactly why the name is geopattern but I know what it is.
It is a golang library that generates pretty image patterns.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>